<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<usx version="2.6">
  <book code="NUM" style="id">World English Bible British Edition (WEBBE)</book>
  <para style="ide">UTF-8</para>
  <para style="h">Numbers</para>
  <para style="toc1">The Fourth Book of Moses, Commonly Called Numbers</para>
  <para style="toc2">Numbers</para>
  <para style="toc3">Numbers</para>
  <para style="mt2">The Fourth Book of Moses,</para>
  <para style="mt3">Commonly Called</para>
  <para style="mt1">Numbers</para>
  <chapter number="1" style="c" />
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="1" style="v" />The LORD<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">1:1 </char><char style="ft" closed="false">When rendered in ALL CAPITAL LETTERS, “LORD” or “GOD” is the translation of God’s Proper Name.</char></note> spoke to Moses in the wilderness of Sinai, in the Tent of Meeting, on the first day of the second month, in the second year after they had come out of the land of Egypt, saying, <verse number="2" style="v" />“Take a census of all the congregation of the children of Israel, by their families, by their fathers’ houses, according to the number of the names, every male, one by one, <verse number="3" style="v" />from twenty years old and upward, all who are able to go out to war in Israel. You and Aaron shall count them by their divisions. <verse number="4" style="v" />With you there shall be a man of every tribe, each one head of his fathers’ house. <verse number="5" style="v" />These are the names of the men who shall stand with you:</para>
  <para style="p">Of Reuben: Elizur the son of Shedeur.</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="6" style="v" />Of Simeon: Shelumiel the son of Zurishaddai.</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="7" style="v" />Of Judah: Nahshon the son of Amminadab.</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="8" style="v" />Of Issachar: Nethanel the son of Zuar.</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="9" style="v" />Of Zebulun: Eliab the son of Helon.</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="10" style="v" />Of the children of Joseph: of Ephraim: Elishama the son of Ammihud; of Manasseh: Gamaliel the son of Pedahzur.</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="11" style="v" />Of Benjamin: Abidan the son of Gideoni.</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="12" style="v" />Of Dan: Ahiezer the son of Ammishaddai.</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="13" style="v" />Of Asher: Pagiel the son of Ochran.</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="14" style="v" />Of Gad: Eliasaph the son of Deuel.</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="15" style="v" />Of Naphtali: Ahira the son of Enan.”</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="16" style="v" />These are those who were called of the congregation, the princes<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">1:16 </char><char style="ft" closed="false">or, chiefs, or, leaders</char></note> of the tribes of their fathers; they were the heads of the thousands of Israel. <verse number="17" style="v" />Moses and Aaron took these men who are mentioned by name. <verse number="18" style="v" />They assembled all the congregation together on the first day of the second month; and they declared their ancestry by their families, by their fathers’ houses, according to the number of the names, from twenty years old and upward, one by one. <verse number="19" style="v" />As the LORD commanded Moses, so he counted them in the wilderness of Sinai.</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="20" style="v" />The children of Reuben, Israel’s firstborn, their generations, by their families, by their fathers’ houses, according to the number of the names, one by one, every male from twenty years old and upward, all who were able to go out to war: <verse number="21" style="v" />those who were counted of them, of the tribe of Reuben, were forty-six thousand and five hundred.</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="22" style="v" />Of the children of Simeon, their generations, by their families, by their fathers’ houses, those who were counted of it, according to the number of the names, one by one, every male from twenty years old and upward, all who were able to go out to war: <verse number="23" style="v" />those who were counted of them, of the tribe of Simeon, were fifty-nine thousand and three hundred.</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="24" style="v" />Of the children of Gad, their generations, by their families, by their fathers’ houses, according to the number of the names, from twenty years old and upward, all who were able to go out to war: <verse number="25" style="v" />those who were counted of them, of the tribe of Gad, were forty-five thousand and six hundred and fifty.</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="26" style="v" />Of the children of Judah, their generations, by their families, by their fathers’ houses, according to the number of the names, from twenty years old and upward, all who were able to go out to war: <verse number="27" style="v" />those who were counted of them, of the tribe of Judah, were seventy-four thousand and six hundred.</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="28" style="v" />Of the children of Issachar, their generations, by their families, by their fathers’ houses, according to the number of the names, from twenty years old and upward, all who were able to go out to war: <verse number="29" style="v" />those who were counted of them, of the tribe of Issachar, were fifty-four thousand and four hundred.</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="30" style="v" />Of the children of Zebulun, their generations, by their families, by their fathers’ houses, according to the number of the names, from twenty years old and upward, all who were able to go out to war: <verse number="31" style="v" />those who were counted of them, of the tribe of Zebulun, were fifty-seven thousand and four hundred.</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="32" style="v" />Of the children of Joseph: of the children of Ephraim, their generations, by their families, by their fathers’ houses, according to the number of the names, from twenty years old and upward, all who were able to go out to war: <verse number="33" style="v" />those who were counted of them, of the tribe of Ephraim, were forty thousand and five hundred.</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="34" style="v" />Of the children of Manasseh, their generations, by their families, by their fathers’ houses, according to the number of the names, from twenty years old and upward, all who were able to go out to war: <verse number="35" style="v" />those who were counted of them, of the tribe of Manasseh, were thirty-two thousand and two hundred.</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="36" style="v" />Of the children of Benjamin, their generations, by their families, by their fathers’ houses, according to the number of the names, from twenty years old and upward, all who were able to go out to war: <verse number="37" style="v" />those who were counted of them, of the tribe of Benjamin, were thirty-five thousand and four hundred.</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="38" style="v" />Of the children of Dan, their generations, by their families, by their fathers’ houses, according to the number of the names, from twenty years old and upward, all who were able to go out to war: <verse number="39" style="v" />those who were counted of them, of the tribe of Dan, were sixty-two thousand and seven hundred.</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="40" style="v" />Of the children of Asher, their generations, by their families, by their fathers’ houses, according to the number of the names, from twenty years old and upward, all who were able to go out to war: <verse number="41" style="v" />those who were counted of them, of the tribe of Asher, were forty-one thousand and five hundred.</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="42" style="v" />Of the children of Naphtali, their generations, by their families, by their fathers’ houses, according to the number of the names, from twenty years old and upward, all who were able to go out to war: <verse number="43" style="v" />those who were counted of them, of the tribe of Naphtali, were fifty-three thousand and four hundred.</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="44" style="v" />These are those who were counted, whom Moses and Aaron counted, and the twelve men who were princes of Israel, each one for his fathers’ house. <verse number="45" style="v" />So all those who were counted of the children of Israel by their fathers’ houses, from twenty years old and upward, all who were able to go out to war in Israel— <verse number="46" style="v" />all those who were counted were six hundred and three thousand and five hundred and fifty. <verse number="47" style="v" />But the Levites after the tribe of their fathers were not counted amongst them. <verse number="48" style="v" />For the LORD spoke to Moses, saying, <verse number="49" style="v" />“Only the tribe of Levi you shall not count, neither shall you take a census of them amongst the children of Israel; <verse number="50" style="v" />but appoint the Levites over the Tabernacle of the Testimony, and over all its furnishings, and over all that belongs to it. They shall carry the tabernacle and all its furnishings; and they shall take care of it, and shall encamp around it. <verse number="51" style="v" />When the tabernacle is to move, the Levites shall take it down; and when the tabernacle is to be set up, the Levites shall set it up. The stranger who comes near shall be put to death. <verse number="52" style="v" />The children of Israel shall pitch their tents, every man by his own camp, and every man by his own standard, according to their divisions. <verse number="53" style="v" />But the Levites shall encamp around the Tabernacle of the Testimony, that there may be no wrath on the congregation of the children of Israel. The Levites shall be responsible for the Tabernacle of the Testimony.”</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="54" style="v" />Thus the children of Israel did. According to all that the LORD commanded Moses, so they did.</para>
  <chapter number="2" style="c" />
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="1" style="v" />The LORD spoke to Moses and to Aaron, saying, <verse number="2" style="v" />“The children of Israel shall encamp every man by his own standard, with the banners of their fathers’ houses. They shall encamp around the Tent of Meeting at a distance from it.”</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="3" style="v" />Those who encamp on the east side towards the sunrise shall be of the standard of the camp of Judah, according to their divisions. The prince of the children of Judah shall be Nahshon the son of Amminadab. <verse number="4" style="v" />His division, and those who were counted of them, were seventy-four thousand and six hundred.</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="5" style="v" />Those who encamp next to him shall be the tribe of Issachar. The prince of the children of Issachar shall be Nethanel the son of Zuar. <verse number="6" style="v" />His division, and those who were counted of it, were fifty-four thousand and four hundred.</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="7" style="v" />The tribe of Zebulun: the prince of the children of Zebulun shall be Eliab the son of Helon. <verse number="8" style="v" />His division, and those who were counted of it, were fifty-seven thousand and four hundred.</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="9" style="v" />All who were counted of the camp of Judah were one hundred and eighty-six thousand and four hundred, according to their divisions. They shall set out first.</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="10" style="v" />“On the south side shall be the standard of the camp of Reuben according to their divisions. The prince of the children of Reuben shall be Elizur the son of Shedeur. <verse number="11" style="v" />His division, and those who were counted of it, were forty-six thousand and five hundred.</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="12" style="v" />“Those who encamp next to him shall be the tribe of Simeon. The prince of the children of Simeon shall be Shelumiel the son of Zurishaddai. <verse number="13" style="v" />His division, and those who were counted of them, were fifty-nine thousand and three hundred.</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="14" style="v" />“The tribe of Gad: the prince of the children of Gad shall be Eliasaph the son of Reuel. <verse number="15" style="v" />His division, and those who were counted of them, were forty-five thousand and six hundred and fifty.</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="16" style="v" />“All who were counted of the camp of Reuben were one hundred and fifty-one thousand and four hundred and fifty, according to their armies. They shall set out second.</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="17" style="v" />“Then the Tent of Meeting shall set out, with the camp of the Levites in the middle of the camps. As they encamp, so shall they set out, every man in his place, by their standards.</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="18" style="v" />“On the west side shall be the standard of the camp of Ephraim according to their divisions. The prince of the children of Ephraim shall be Elishama the son of Ammihud. <verse number="19" style="v" />His division, and those who were counted of them, were forty thousand and five hundred.</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="20" style="v" />“Next to him shall be the tribe of Manasseh. The prince of the children of Manasseh shall be Gamaliel the son of Pedahzur. <verse number="21" style="v" />His division, and those who were counted of them, were thirty-two thousand and two hundred.</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="22" style="v" />“The tribe of Benjamin: the prince of the children of Benjamin shall be Abidan the son of Gideoni. <verse number="23" style="v" />His army, and those who were counted of them, were thirty-five thousand and four hundred.</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="24" style="v" />“All who were counted of the camp of Ephraim were one hundred and eight thousand and one hundred, according to their divisions. They shall set out third.</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="25" style="v" />“On the north side shall be the standard of the camp of Dan according to their divisions. The prince of the children of Dan shall be Ahiezer the son of Ammishaddai. <verse number="26" style="v" />His division, and those who were counted of them, were sixty-two thousand and seven hundred.</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="27" style="v" />“Those who encamp next to him shall be the tribe of Asher. The prince of the children of Asher shall be Pagiel the son of Ochran. <verse number="28" style="v" />His division, and those who were counted of them, were forty-one thousand and five hundred.</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="29" style="v" />“The tribe of Naphtali: the prince of the children of Naphtali shall be Ahira the son of Enan. <verse number="30" style="v" />His division, and those who were counted of them, were fifty-three thousand and four hundred.</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="31" style="v" />“All who were counted of the camp of Dan were one hundred and fifty-seven thousand and six hundred. They shall set out last by their standards.”</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="32" style="v" />These are those who were counted of the children of Israel by their fathers’ houses. All who were counted of the camps according to their armies were six hundred and three thousand and five hundred and fifty. <verse number="33" style="v" />But the Levites were not counted amongst the children of Israel, as the LORD commanded Moses.</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="34" style="v" />Thus the children of Israel did. According to all that the LORD commanded Moses, so they encamped by their standards, and so they set out, everyone by their families, according to their fathers’ houses.</para>
  <chapter number="3" style="c" />
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="1" style="v" />Now this is the history of the generations of Aaron and Moses in the day that the LORD spoke with Moses in Mount Sinai. <verse number="2" style="v" />These are the names of the sons of Aaron: Nadab the firstborn, and Abihu, Eleazar, and Ithamar.</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="3" style="v" />These are the names of the sons of Aaron, the priests who were anointed, whom he consecrated to minister in the priest’s office. <verse number="4" style="v" />Nadab and Abihu died before the LORD when they offered strange fire before the LORD in the wilderness of Sinai, and they had no children. Eleazar and Ithamar ministered in the priest’s office in the presence of Aaron their father.</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="5" style="v" />The LORD spoke to Moses, saying, <verse number="6" style="v" />“Bring the tribe of Levi near, and set them before Aaron the priest, that they may minister to him. <verse number="7" style="v" />They shall keep his requirements, and the requirements of the whole congregation before the Tent of Meeting, to do the service of the tabernacle. <verse number="8" style="v" />They shall keep all the furnishings of the Tent of Meeting, and the obligations of the children of Israel, to do the service of the tabernacle. <verse number="9" style="v" />You shall give the Levites to Aaron and to his sons. They are wholly given to him on the behalf of the children of Israel. <verse number="10" style="v" />You shall appoint Aaron and his sons, and they shall keep their priesthood, but the stranger who comes near shall be put to death.”</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="11" style="v" />The LORD spoke to Moses, saying, <verse number="12" style="v" />“Behold,<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">3:12 </char><char style="ft" closed="false">“Behold”, from “הִנֵּה”, means look at, take notice, observe, see, or gaze at. It is often used as an interjection.</char></note> I have taken the Levites from amongst the children of Israel instead of all the firstborn who open the womb amongst the children of Israel; and the Levites shall be mine, <verse number="13" style="v" />for all the firstborn are mine. On the day that I struck down all the firstborn in the land of Egypt I made holy to me all the firstborn in Israel, both man and animal. They shall be mine. I am the LORD.”</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="14" style="v" />The LORD spoke to Moses in the wilderness of Sinai, saying, <verse number="15" style="v" />“Count the children of Levi by their fathers’ houses, by their families. You shall count every male from a month old and upward.”</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="16" style="v" />Moses counted them according to the LORD’s word, as he was commanded.</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="17" style="v" />These were the sons of Levi by their names: Gershon, Kohath, and Merari.</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="18" style="v" />These are the names of the sons of Gershon by their families: Libni and Shimei.</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="19" style="v" />The sons of Kohath by their families: Amram, Izhar, Hebron, and Uzziel.</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="20" style="v" />The sons of Merari by their families: Mahli and Mushi.</para>
  <para style="p">These are the families of the Levites according to their fathers’ houses.</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="21" style="v" />Of Gershon was the family of the Libnites, and the family of the Shimeites. These are the families of the Gershonites.</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="22" style="v" />Those who were counted of them, according to the number of all the males from a month old and upward, even those who were counted of them were seven thousand and five hundred.</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="23" style="v" />The families of the Gershonites shall encamp behind the tabernacle westward.</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="24" style="v" />Eliasaph the son of Lael shall be the prince of the fathers’ house of the Gershonites. <verse number="25" style="v" />The duty of the sons of Gershon in the Tent of Meeting shall be the tabernacle, the tent, its covering, the screen for the door of the Tent of Meeting, <verse number="26" style="v" />the hangings of the court, the screen for the door of the court which is by the tabernacle and around the altar, and its cords for all of its service.</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="27" style="v" />Of Kohath was the family of the Amramites, the family of the Izharites, the family of the Hebronites, and the family of the Uzzielites. These are the families of the Kohathites. <verse number="28" style="v" />According to the number of all the males from a month old and upward, there were eight thousand and six hundred keeping the requirements of the sanctuary.</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="29" style="v" />The families of the sons of Kohath shall encamp on the south side of the tabernacle. <verse number="30" style="v" />The prince of the fathers’ house of the families of the Kohathites shall be Elizaphan the son of Uzziel. <verse number="31" style="v" />Their duty shall be the ark, the table, the lamp stand, the altars, the vessels of the sanctuary with which they minister, the screen, and all its service. <verse number="32" style="v" />Eleazar the son of Aaron the priest shall be prince of the princes of the Levites, with the oversight of those who keep the requirements of the sanctuary.</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="33" style="v" />Of Merari was the family of the Mahlites and the family of the Mushites. These are the families of Merari. <verse number="34" style="v" />Those who were counted of them, according to the number of all the males from a month old and upward, were six thousand and two hundred.<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">3:34 </char><char style="ft" closed="false">+ 22,000 is the sum rounded to 2 significant digits. The sum of the Gershonites, Kohathites, and Merarites given above is 22,300, but the traditional Hebrew text has the number rounded to 2 significant digits, not 3 significant digits.</char></note></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="35" style="v" />The prince of the fathers’ house of the families of Merari was Zuriel the son of Abihail. They shall encamp on the north side of the tabernacle. <verse number="36" style="v" />The appointed duty of the sons of Merari shall be the tabernacle’s boards, its bars, its pillars, its sockets, all its instruments, all its service, <verse number="37" style="v" />the pillars of the court around it, their sockets, their pins, and their cords.</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="38" style="v" />Those who encamp before the tabernacle eastward, in front of the Tent of Meeting towards the sunrise, shall be Moses, with Aaron and his sons, keeping the requirements of the sanctuary for the duty of the children of Israel. The outsider who comes near shall be put to death. <verse number="39" style="v" />All who were counted of the Levites, whom Moses and Aaron counted at the commandment of the LORD, by their families, all the males from a month old and upward, were twenty-two thousand.</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="40" style="v" />The LORD said to Moses, “Count all the firstborn males of the children of Israel from a month old and upward, and take the number of their names. <verse number="41" style="v" />You shall take the Levites for me—I am the LORD—instead of all the firstborn amongst the children of Israel; and the livestock of the Levites instead of all the firstborn amongst the livestock of the children of Israel.”</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="42" style="v" />Moses counted, as the LORD commanded him, all the firstborn amongst the children of Israel. <verse number="43" style="v" />All the firstborn males according to the number of names from a month old and upward, of those who were counted of them, were twenty-two thousand and two hundred and seventy-three.</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="44" style="v" />The LORD spoke to Moses, saying, <verse number="45" style="v" />“Take the Levites instead of all the firstborn amongst the children of Israel, and the livestock of the Levites instead of their livestock; and the Levites shall be mine. I am the LORD. <verse number="46" style="v" />For the redemption of the two hundred and seventy-three of the firstborn of the children of Israel who exceed the number of the Levites, <verse number="47" style="v" />you shall take five shekels apiece for each one; according to the shekel<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">3:47 </char><char style="ft" closed="false">A shekel is about 10 grams or about 0.35 ounces.</char></note> of the sanctuary you shall take them (the shekel is twenty gerahs<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">3:47 </char><char style="ft" closed="false">A gerah is about 0.5 grams or about 7.7 grains.</char></note>); <verse number="48" style="v" />and you shall give the money, with which their remainder is redeemed, to Aaron and to his sons.”</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="49" style="v" />Moses took the redemption money from those who exceeded the number of those who were redeemed by the Levites; <verse number="50" style="v" />from the firstborn of the children of Israel he took the money, one thousand and three hundred and sixty-five shekels,<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">3:50 </char><char style="ft" closed="false">A shekel is about 10 grams or about 0.35 ounces, so 1365 shekels is about 13.65 kilograms or about 30 pounds.</char></note> according to the shekel of the sanctuary; <verse number="51" style="v" />and Moses gave the redemption money to Aaron and to his sons, according to the LORD’s word, as the LORD commanded Moses.</para>
  <chapter number="4" style="c" />
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="1" style="v" />The LORD spoke to Moses and to Aaron, saying, <verse number="2" style="v" />“Take a census of the sons of Kohath from amongst the sons of Levi, by their families, by their fathers’ houses, <verse number="3" style="v" />from thirty years old and upward even until fifty years old, all who enter into the service to do the work in the Tent of Meeting.</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="4" style="v" />“This is the service of the sons of Kohath in the Tent of Meeting, regarding the most holy things. <verse number="5" style="v" />When the camp moves forward, Aaron shall go in with his sons; and they shall take down the veil of the screen, cover the ark of the Testimony with it, <verse number="6" style="v" />put a covering of sealskin on it, spread a blue cloth over it, and put in its poles.</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="7" style="v" />“On the table of show bread they shall spread a blue cloth, and put on it the dishes, the spoons, the bowls, and the cups with which to pour out; and the continual bread shall be on it. <verse number="8" style="v" />They shall spread on them a scarlet cloth, and cover it with a covering of sealskin, and shall put in its poles.</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="9" style="v" />“They shall take a blue cloth and cover the lamp stand of the light, its lamps, its snuffers, its snuff dishes, and all its oil vessels, with which they minister to it. <verse number="10" style="v" />They shall put it and all its vessels within a covering of sealskin, and shall put it on the frame.</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="11" style="v" />“On the golden altar they shall spread a blue cloth, and cover it with a covering of sealskin, and shall put in its poles.</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="12" style="v" />“They shall take all the vessels of ministry with which they minister in the sanctuary, and put them in a blue cloth, cover them with a covering of sealskin, and shall put them on the frame.</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="13" style="v" />“They shall take away the ashes from the altar, and spread a purple cloth on it. <verse number="14" style="v" />They shall put on it all its vessels with which they minister about it, the fire pans, the meat hooks, the shovels, and the basins—all the vessels of the altar; and they shall spread on it a covering of sealskin, and put in its poles.</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="15" style="v" />“When Aaron and his sons have finished covering the sanctuary and all the furniture of the sanctuary, as the camp moves forward; after that, the sons of Kohath shall come to carry it; but they shall not touch the sanctuary, lest they die. The sons of Kohath shall carry these things belonging to the Tent of Meeting.</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="16" style="v" />“The duty of Eleazar the son of Aaron the priest shall be the oil for the light, the sweet incense, the continual meal offering, and the anointing oil, the requirements of all the tabernacle, and of all that is in it, the sanctuary, and its furnishings.”</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="17" style="v" />The LORD spoke to Moses and to Aaron, saying, <verse number="18" style="v" />“Don’t cut off the tribe of the families of the Kohathites from amongst the Levites; <verse number="19" style="v" />but do this to them, that they may live, and not die, when they approach the most holy things: Aaron and his sons shall go in and appoint everyone to his service and to his burden; <verse number="20" style="v" />but they shall not go in to see the sanctuary even for a moment, lest they die.”</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="21" style="v" />The LORD spoke to Moses, saying, <verse number="22" style="v" />“Take a census of the sons of Gershon also, by their fathers’ houses, by their families; <verse number="23" style="v" />you shall count them from thirty years old and upward until fifty years old: all who enter in to wait on the service, to do the work in the Tent of Meeting.</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="24" style="v" />“This is the service of the families of the Gershonites, in serving and in bearing burdens: <verse number="25" style="v" />they shall carry the curtains of the tabernacle and the Tent of Meeting, its covering, the covering of sealskin that is on it, the screen for the door of the Tent of Meeting, <verse number="26" style="v" />the hangings of the court, the screen for the door of the gate of the court which is by the tabernacle and around the altar, their cords, and all the instruments of their service, and whatever shall be done with them. They shall serve in there. <verse number="27" style="v" />At the commandment of Aaron and his sons shall be all the service of the sons of the Gershonites, in all their burden and in all their service; and you shall appoint their duty to them in all their responsibilities. <verse number="28" style="v" />This is the service of the families of the sons of the Gershonites in the Tent of Meeting. Their duty shall be under the hand of Ithamar the son of Aaron the priest.</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="29" style="v" />“As for the sons of Merari, you shall count them by their families, by their fathers’ houses; <verse number="30" style="v" />you shall count them from thirty years old and upward even to fifty years old—everyone who enters on the service, to do the work of the Tent of Meeting. <verse number="31" style="v" />This is the duty of their burden, according to all their service in the Tent of Meeting: the tabernacle’s boards, its bars, its pillars, its sockets, <verse number="32" style="v" />the pillars of the court around it, their sockets, their pins, their cords, with all their instruments, and with all their service. You shall appoint the instruments of the duty of their burden to them by name. <verse number="33" style="v" />This is the service of the families of the sons of Merari, according to all their service in the Tent of Meeting, under the hand of Ithamar the son of Aaron the priest.”</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="34" style="v" />Moses and Aaron and the princes of the congregation counted the sons of the Kohathites by their families, and by their fathers’ houses, <verse number="35" style="v" />from thirty years old and upward even to fifty years old, everyone who entered into the service for work in the Tent of Meeting. <verse number="36" style="v" />Those who were counted of them by their families were two thousand and seven hundred and fifty. <verse number="37" style="v" />These are those who were counted of the families of the Kohathites, all who served in the Tent of Meeting, whom Moses and Aaron counted according to the commandment of the LORD by Moses.</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="38" style="v" />Those who were counted of the sons of Gershon, by their families, and by their fathers’ houses, <verse number="39" style="v" />from thirty years old and upward even to fifty years old—everyone who entered into the service for work in the Tent of Meeting, <verse number="40" style="v" />even those who were counted of them, by their families, by their fathers’ houses, were two thousand and six hundred and thirty. <verse number="41" style="v" />These are those who were counted of the families of the sons of Gershon, all who served in the Tent of Meeting, whom Moses and Aaron counted according to the commandment of the LORD.</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="42" style="v" />Those who were counted of the families of the sons of Merari, by their families, by their fathers’ houses, <verse number="43" style="v" />from thirty years old and upward even to fifty years old—everyone who entered into the service for work in the Tent of Meeting, <verse number="44" style="v" />even those who were counted of them by their families, were three thousand and two hundred. <verse number="45" style="v" />These are those who were counted of the families of the sons of Merari, whom Moses and Aaron counted according to the commandment of the LORD by Moses.</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="46" style="v" />All those who were counted of the Levites whom Moses and Aaron and the princes of Israel counted, by their families and by their fathers’ houses, <verse number="47" style="v" />from thirty years old and upward even to fifty years old, everyone who entered in to do the work of service and the work of bearing burdens in the Tent of Meeting, <verse number="48" style="v" />even those who were counted of them, were eight thousand and five hundred and eighty. <verse number="49" style="v" />According to the commandment of the LORD they were counted by Moses, everyone according to his service and according to his burden. Thus they were counted by him, as the LORD commanded Moses.</para>
  <chapter number="5" style="c" />
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="1" style="v" />The LORD spoke to Moses, saying, <verse number="2" style="v" />“Command the children of Israel that they put out of the camp every leper, everyone who has a discharge, and whoever is unclean by a corpse. <verse number="3" style="v" />You shall put both male and female outside of the camp so that they don’t defile their camp, in the midst of which I dwell.”</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="4" style="v" />The children of Israel did so, and put them outside of the camp; as the LORD spoke to Moses, so the children of Israel did.</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="5" style="v" />The LORD spoke to Moses, saying, <verse number="6" style="v" />“Speak to the children of Israel: ‘When a man or woman commits any sin that men commit, so as to trespass against the LORD, and that soul is guilty, <verse number="7" style="v" />then he shall confess his sin which he has done; and he shall make restitution for his guilt in full, add to it the fifth part of it, and give it to him in respect of whom he has been guilty. <verse number="8" style="v" />But if the man has no kinsman to whom restitution may be made for the guilt, the restitution for guilt which is made to the LORD shall be the priest’s, in addition to the ram of the atonement, by which atonement shall be made for him. <verse number="9" style="v" />Every heave offering of all the holy things of the children of Israel, which they present to the priest, shall be his. <verse number="10" style="v" />Every man’s holy things shall be his; whatever any man gives the priest, it shall be his.’”</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="11" style="v" />The LORD spoke to Moses, saying, <verse number="12" style="v" />“Speak to the children of Israel, and tell them: ‘If any man’s wife goes astray and is unfaithful to him, <verse number="13" style="v" />and a man lies with her carnally, and it is hidden from the eyes of her husband and this is kept concealed, and she is defiled, there is no witness against her, and she isn’t taken in the act; <verse number="14" style="v" />and the spirit of jealousy comes on him, and he is jealous of his wife and she is defiled; or if the spirit of jealousy comes on him, and he is jealous of his wife and she isn’t defiled; <verse number="15" style="v" />then the man shall bring his wife to the priest, and shall bring her offering for her: one tenth of an ephah<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">5:15 </char><char style="ft" closed="false">1 ephah is about 22 litres or about 2/3 of a bushel</char></note> of barley meal. He shall pour no oil on it, nor put frankincense on it, for it is a meal offering of jealousy, a meal offering of memorial, bringing iniquity to memory. <verse number="16" style="v" />The priest shall bring her near, and set her before the LORD. <verse number="17" style="v" />The priest shall take holy water in an earthen vessel; and the priest shall take some of the dust that is on the floor of the tabernacle and put it into the water. <verse number="18" style="v" />The priest shall set the woman before the LORD, and let the hair of the woman’s head go loose, and put the meal offering of memorial in her hands, which is the meal offering of jealousy. The priest shall have in his hand the water of bitterness that brings a curse. <verse number="19" style="v" />The priest shall cause her to take an oath and shall tell the woman, “If no man has lain with you, and if you haven’t gone aside to uncleanness, being under your husband’s authority, be free from this water of bitterness that brings a curse. <verse number="20" style="v" />But if you have gone astray, being under your husband’s authority, and if you are defiled, and some man has lain with you besides your husband—” <verse number="21" style="v" />then the priest shall cause the woman to swear with the oath of cursing, and the priest shall tell the woman, “May The LORD make you a curse and an oath amongst your people, when the LORD allows your thigh to fall away, and your body to swell; <verse number="22" style="v" />and this water that brings a curse will go into your bowels, and make your body swell, and your thigh fall away.” The woman shall say, “Amen, Amen.”</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="23" style="v" />“‘The priest shall write these curses in a book, and he shall wipe them into the water of bitterness. <verse number="24" style="v" />He shall make the woman drink the water of bitterness that causes the curse; and the water that causes the curse shall enter into her and become bitter. <verse number="25" style="v" />The priest shall take the meal offering of jealousy out of the woman’s hand, and shall wave the meal offering before the LORD, and bring it to the altar. <verse number="26" style="v" />The priest shall take a handful of the meal offering, as its memorial portion, and burn it on the altar, and afterward shall make the woman drink the water. <verse number="27" style="v" />When he has made her drink the water, then it shall happen, if she is defiled and has committed a trespass against her husband, that the water that causes the curse will enter into her and become bitter, and her body will swell, and her thigh will fall away; and the woman will be a curse amongst her people. <verse number="28" style="v" />If the woman isn’t defiled, but is clean; then she shall be free, and shall conceive offspring.<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">5:28 </char><char style="ft" closed="false">or, seed</char></note></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="29" style="v" />“‘This is the law of jealousy, when a wife, being under her husband, goes astray, and is defiled, <verse number="30" style="v" />or when the spirit of jealousy comes on a man, and he is jealous of his wife; then he shall set the woman before the LORD, and the priest shall execute on her all this law. <verse number="31" style="v" />The man shall be free from iniquity, and that woman shall bear her iniquity.’”</para>
  <chapter number="6" style="c" />
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="1" style="v" />The LORD spoke to Moses, saying, <verse number="2" style="v" />“Speak to the children of Israel, and tell them: ‘When either man or woman shall make a special vow, the vow of a Nazirite, to separate himself to the LORD, <verse number="3" style="v" />he shall separate himself from wine and strong drink. He shall drink no vinegar of wine, or vinegar of fermented drink, neither shall he drink any juice of grapes, nor eat fresh grapes or dried. <verse number="4" style="v" />All the days of his separation he shall eat nothing that is made of the grapevine, from the seeds even to the skins.</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="5" style="v" />“‘All the days of his vow of separation no razor shall come on his head, until the days are fulfilled in which he separates himself to the LORD. He shall be holy. He shall let the locks of the hair of his head grow long.</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="6" style="v" />“‘All the days that he separates himself to the LORD he shall not go near a dead body. <verse number="7" style="v" />He shall not make himself unclean for his father, or for his mother, for his brother, or for his sister, when they die, because his separation to God<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">6:7 </char><char style="ft" closed="false">The Hebrew word rendered “God” is “אֱלֹהִ֑ים” (Elohim).</char></note> is on his head. <verse number="8" style="v" />All the days of his separation he is holy to the LORD.</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="9" style="v" />“‘If any man dies very suddenly beside him, and he defiles the head of his separation, then he shall shave his head in the day of his cleansing. On the seventh day he shall shave it. <verse number="10" style="v" />On the eighth day he shall bring two turtledoves or two young pigeons to the priest, to the door of the Tent of Meeting. <verse number="11" style="v" />The priest shall offer one for a sin offering, and the other for a burnt offering, and make atonement for him, because he sinned by reason of the dead, and shall make his head holy that same day. <verse number="12" style="v" />He shall separate to the LORD the days of his separation, and shall bring a male lamb a year old for a trespass offering; but the former days shall be void, because his separation was defiled.</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="13" style="v" />“‘This is the law of the Nazirite: when the days of his separation are fulfilled, he shall be brought to the door of the Tent of Meeting, <verse number="14" style="v" />and he shall offer his offering to the LORD: one male lamb a year old without defect for a burnt offering, one ewe lamb a year old without defect for a sin offering, one ram without defect for peace offerings, <verse number="15" style="v" />a basket of unleavened bread, cakes of fine flour mixed with oil, and unleavened wafers anointed with oil with their meal offering and their drink offerings. <verse number="16" style="v" />The priest shall present them before the LORD, and shall offer his sin offering and his burnt offering. <verse number="17" style="v" />He shall offer the ram for a sacrifice of peace offerings to the LORD, with the basket of unleavened bread. The priest shall offer also its meal offering and its drink offering. <verse number="18" style="v" />The Nazirite shall shave the head of his separation at the door of the Tent of Meeting, take the hair of the head of his separation, and put it on the fire which is under the sacrifice of peace offerings. <verse number="19" style="v" />The priest shall take the boiled shoulder of the ram, one unleavened cake out of the basket, and one unleavened wafer, and shall put them on the hands of the Nazirite after he has shaved the head of his separation; <verse number="20" style="v" />and the priest shall wave them for a wave offering before the LORD. They are holy for the priest, together with the breast that is waved and the thigh that is offered. After that the Nazirite may drink wine.</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="21" style="v" />“‘This is the law of the Nazirite who vows and of his offering to the LORD for his separation, in addition to that which he is able to afford. According to his vow which he vows, so he must do after the law of his separation.’”</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="22" style="v" />The LORD spoke to Moses, saying, <verse number="23" style="v" />“Speak to Aaron and to his sons, saying, ‘This is how you shall bless the children of Israel.’ You shall tell them,</para>
  <para style="q1">
    <verse number="24" style="v" />‘The LORD bless you, and keep you.</para>
  <para style="q2">
    <verse number="25" style="v" />The LORD make his face to shine on you,</para>
  <para style="q2">and be gracious to you.</para>
  <para style="q1">
    <verse number="26" style="v" />The LORD lift up his face towards you,</para>
  <para style="q2">and give you peace.’</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="27" style="v" />“So they shall put my name on the children of Israel; and I will bless them.”</para>
  <chapter number="7" style="c" />
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="1" style="v" />On the day that Moses had finished setting up the tabernacle, and had anointed it and sanctified it with all its furniture, and the altar with all its vessels, and had anointed and sanctified them; <verse number="2" style="v" />the princes of Israel, the heads of their fathers’ houses, offered. These were the princes of the tribes. These are they who were over those who were counted; <verse number="3" style="v" />and they brought their offering before the LORD, six covered wagons and twelve oxen; a wagon for every two of the princes, and for each one an ox. They presented them before the tabernacle. <verse number="4" style="v" />The LORD spoke to Moses, saying, <verse number="5" style="v" />“Accept these from them, that they may be used in doing the service of the Tent of Meeting; and you shall give them to the Levites, to every man according to his service.”</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="6" style="v" />Moses took the wagons and the oxen, and gave them to the Levites. <verse number="7" style="v" />He gave two wagons and four oxen to the sons of Gershon, according to their service. <verse number="8" style="v" />He gave four wagons and eight oxen to the sons of Merari, according to their service, under the direction of Ithamar the son of Aaron the priest. <verse number="9" style="v" />But to the sons of Kohath he gave none, because the service of the sanctuary belonged to them; they carried it on their shoulders.</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="10" style="v" />The princes gave offerings for the dedication of the altar in the day that it was anointed. The princes gave their offerings before the altar.</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="11" style="v" />The LORD said to Moses, “They shall offer their offering, each prince on his day, for the dedication of the altar.”</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="12" style="v" />He who offered his offering the first day was Nahshon the son of Amminadab, of the tribe of Judah, <verse number="13" style="v" />and his offering was:</para>
  <para style="p">one silver platter, the weight of which was one hundred and thirty shekels,<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">7:13 </char><char style="ft" closed="false">A shekel is about 10 grams or about 0.35 ounces.</char></note></para>
  <para style="p">one silver bowl of seventy shekels, according to the shekel of the sanctuary, both of them full of fine flour mixed with oil for a meal offering;</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="14" style="v" />one golden ladle of ten shekels, full of incense;</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="15" style="v" />one young bull,</para>
  <para style="p">one ram,</para>
  <para style="p">one male lamb a year old, for a burnt offering;</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="16" style="v" />one male goat for a sin offering;</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="17" style="v" />and for the sacrifice of peace offerings, two head of cattle, five rams, five male goats, and five male lambs a year old. This was the offering of Nahshon the son of Amminadab.</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="18" style="v" />On the second day Nethanel the son of Zuar, prince of Issachar, gave his offering. <verse number="19" style="v" />He offered for his offering:</para>
  <para style="p">one silver platter, the weight of which was one hundred and thirty shekels,</para>
  <para style="p">one silver bowl of seventy shekels, according to the shekel of the sanctuary, both of them full of fine flour mixed with oil for a meal offering;</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="20" style="v" />one golden ladle of ten shekels, full of incense;</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="21" style="v" />one young bull,</para>
  <para style="p">one ram,</para>
  <para style="p">one male lamb a year old, for a burnt offering;</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="22" style="v" />one male goat for a sin offering;</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="23" style="v" />and for the sacrifice of peace offerings, two head of cattle, five rams, five male goats, five male lambs a year old. This was the offering of Nethanel the son of Zuar.</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="24" style="v" />On the third day Eliab the son of Helon, prince of the children of Zebulun, <verse number="25" style="v" />gave his offering:</para>
  <para style="p">one silver platter, the weight of which was a hundred and thirty shekels,</para>
  <para style="p">one silver bowl of seventy shekels, according to the shekel of the sanctuary, both of them full of fine flour mixed with oil for a meal offering;</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="26" style="v" />one golden ladle of ten shekels, full of incense;</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="27" style="v" />one young bull,</para>
  <para style="p">one ram,</para>
  <para style="p">one male lamb a year old, for a burnt offering;</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="28" style="v" />one male goat for a sin offering;</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="29" style="v" />and for the sacrifice of peace offerings, two head of cattle, five rams, five male goats, and five male lambs a year old. This was the offering of Eliab the son of Helon.</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="30" style="v" />On the fourth day Elizur the son of Shedeur, prince of the children of Reuben, <verse number="31" style="v" />gave his offering:</para>
  <para style="p">one silver platter, the weight of which was one hundred and thirty shekels,</para>
  <para style="p">one silver bowl of seventy shekels, according to the shekel of the sanctuary, both of them full of fine flour mixed with oil for a meal offering;</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="32" style="v" />one golden ladle of ten shekels, full of incense;</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="33" style="v" />one young bull,</para>
  <para style="p">one ram,</para>
  <para style="p">one male lamb a year old, for a burnt offering;</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="34" style="v" />one male goat for a sin offering;</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="35" style="v" />and for the sacrifice of peace offerings, two head of cattle, five rams, five male goats, and five male lambs a year old. This was the offering of Elizur the son of Shedeur.</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="36" style="v" />On the fifth day Shelumiel the son of Zurishaddai, prince of the children of Simeon, <verse number="37" style="v" />gave his offering:</para>
  <para style="p">one silver platter, the weight of which was one hundred and thirty shekels,</para>
  <para style="p">one silver bowl of seventy shekels, according to the shekel of the sanctuary, both of them full of fine flour mixed with oil for a meal offering;</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="38" style="v" />one golden ladle of ten shekels, full of incense;</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="39" style="v" />one young bull,</para>
  <para style="p">one ram,</para>
  <para style="p">one male lamb a year old, for a burnt offering;</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="40" style="v" />one male goat for a sin offering;</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="41" style="v" />and for the sacrifice of peace offerings, two head of cattle, five rams, five male goats, and five male lambs a year old: this was the offering of Shelumiel the son of Zurishaddai.</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="42" style="v" />On the sixth day, Eliasaph the son of Deuel, prince of the children of Gad, <verse number="43" style="v" />gave his offering:</para>
  <para style="p">one silver platter, the weight of which was one hundred and thirty shekels,</para>
  <para style="p">one silver bowl of seventy shekels, according to the shekel of the sanctuary, both of them full of fine flour mixed with oil for a meal offering;</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="44" style="v" />one golden ladle of ten shekels, full of incense;</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="45" style="v" />one young bull,</para>
  <para style="p">one ram,</para>
  <para style="p">one male lamb a year old, for a burnt offering;</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="46" style="v" />one male goat for a sin offering;</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="47" style="v" />and for the sacrifice of peace offerings, two head of cattle, five rams, five male goats, and five male lambs a year old. This was the offering of Eliasaph the son of Deuel.</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="48" style="v" />On the seventh day Elishama the son of Ammihud, prince of the children of Ephraim, <verse number="49" style="v" />gave his offering:</para>
  <para style="p">one silver platter, the weight of which was one hundred and thirty shekels,</para>
  <para style="p">one silver bowl of seventy shekels, according to the shekel of the sanctuary, both of them full of fine flour mixed with oil for a meal offering;</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="50" style="v" />one golden ladle of ten shekels, full of incense;</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="51" style="v" />one young bull,</para>
  <para style="p">one ram,</para>
  <para style="p">one male lamb a year old, for a burnt offering;</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="52" style="v" />one male goat for a sin offering;</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="53" style="v" />and for the sacrifice of peace offerings, two head of cattle, five rams, five male goats, and five male lambs a year old. This was the offering of Elishama the son of Ammihud.</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="54" style="v" />On the eighth day Gamaliel the son of Pedahzur, prince of the children of Manasseh, <verse number="55" style="v" />gave his offering:</para>
  <para style="p">one silver platter, the weight of which was one hundred and thirty shekels,</para>
  <para style="p">one silver bowl of seventy shekels, according to the shekel of the sanctuary, both of them full of fine flour mixed with oil for a meal offering;</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="56" style="v" />one golden ladle of ten shekels, full of incense;</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="57" style="v" />one young bull,</para>
  <para style="p">one ram,</para>
  <para style="p">one male lamb a year old, for a burnt offering;</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="58" style="v" />one male goat for a sin offering;</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="59" style="v" />and for the sacrifice of peace offerings, two head of cattle, five rams, five male goats, and five male lambs a year old. This was the offering of Gamaliel the son of Pedahzur.</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="60" style="v" />On the ninth day Abidan the son of Gideoni, prince of the children of Benjamin, <verse number="61" style="v" />gave his offering:</para>
  <para style="p">one silver platter, the weight of which was one hundred and thirty shekels,</para>
  <para style="p">one silver bowl of seventy shekels, according to the shekel of the sanctuary, both of them full of fine flour mixed with oil for a meal offering;</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="62" style="v" />one golden ladle of ten shekels, full of incense;</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="63" style="v" />one young bull,</para>
  <para style="p">one ram,</para>
  <para style="p">one male lamb a year old, for a burnt offering;</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="64" style="v" />one male goat for a sin offering;</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="65" style="v" />and for the sacrifice of peace offerings, two head of cattle, five rams, five male goats, and five male lambs a year old. This was the offering of Abidan the son of Gideoni.</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="66" style="v" />On the tenth day Ahiezer the son of Ammishaddai, prince of the children of Dan, <verse number="67" style="v" />gave his offering:</para>
  <para style="p">one silver platter, the weight of which was one hundred and thirty shekels,</para>
  <para style="p">one silver bowl of seventy shekels, according to the shekel of the sanctuary, both of them full of fine flour mixed with oil for a meal offering;</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="68" style="v" />one golden ladle of ten shekels, full of incense;</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="69" style="v" />one young bull,</para>
  <para style="p">one ram,</para>
  <para style="p">one male lamb a year old, for a burnt offering;</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="70" style="v" />one male goat for a sin offering;</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="71" style="v" />and for the sacrifice of peace offerings, two head of cattle, five rams, five male goats, and five male lambs a year old. This was the offering of Ahiezer the son of Ammishaddai.</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="72" style="v" />On the eleventh day Pagiel the son of Ochran, prince of the children of Asher, <verse number="73" style="v" />gave his offering:</para>
  <para style="p">one silver platter, the weight of which was one hundred and thirty shekels,</para>
  <para style="p">one silver bowl of seventy shekels, according to the shekel of the sanctuary, both of them full of fine flour mixed with oil for a meal offering;</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="74" style="v" />one golden ladle of ten shekels, full of incense;</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="75" style="v" />one young bull,</para>
  <para style="p">one ram,</para>
  <para style="p">one male lamb a year old, for a burnt offering;</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="76" style="v" />one male goat for a sin offering;</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="77" style="v" />and for the sacrifice of peace offerings, two head of cattle, five rams, five male goats, and five male lambs a year old. This was the offering of Pagiel the son of Ochran.</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="78" style="v" />On the twelfth day Ahira the son of Enan, prince of the children of Naphtali, <verse number="79" style="v" />gave his offering:</para>
  <para style="p">one silver platter, the weight of which was one hundred and thirty shekels,</para>
  <para style="p">one silver bowl of seventy shekels, according to the shekel of the sanctuary, both of them full of fine flour mixed with oil for a meal offering;</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="80" style="v" />one golden spoon of ten shekels, full of incense;</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="81" style="v" />one young bull,</para>
  <para style="p">one ram,</para>
  <para style="p">one male lamb a year old, for a burnt offering;</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="82" style="v" />one male goat for a sin offering;</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="83" style="v" />and for the sacrifice of peace offerings, two head of cattle, five rams, five male goats, and five male lambs a year old. This was the offering of Ahira the son of Enan.</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="84" style="v" />This was the dedication offering of the altar, on the day when it was anointed, by the princes of Israel: twelve silver platters, twelve silver bowls, twelve golden ladles; <verse number="85" style="v" />each silver platter weighing one hundred and thirty shekels, and each bowl seventy; all the silver of the vessels two thousand and four hundred shekels, according to the shekel of the sanctuary; <verse number="86" style="v" />the twelve golden ladles, full of incense, weighing ten shekels apiece, according to the shekel of the sanctuary; all the gold of the ladles weighed one hundred and twenty shekels; <verse number="87" style="v" />all the cattle for the burnt offering twelve bulls, the rams twelve, the male lambs a year old twelve, and their meal offering; and twelve male goats for a sin offering; <verse number="88" style="v" />and all the cattle for the sacrifice of peace offerings: twenty-four bulls, sixty rams, sixty male goats, and sixty male lambs a year old. This was the dedication offering of the altar, after it was anointed.</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="89" style="v" />When Moses went into the Tent of Meeting to speak with the LORD, he heard his voice speaking to him from above the mercy seat that was on the ark of the Testimony, from between the two cherubim; and he spoke to him.</para>
  <chapter number="8" style="c" />
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="1" style="v" />The LORD spoke to Moses, saying, <verse number="2" style="v" />“Speak to Aaron, and tell him, ‘When you light the lamps, the seven lamps shall give light in front of the lamp stand.’”</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="3" style="v" />Aaron did so. He lit its lamps to light the area in front of the lamp stand, as the LORD commanded Moses. <verse number="4" style="v" />This was the workmanship of the lamp stand, beaten work of gold. From its base to its flowers, it was beaten work. He made the lamp stand according to the pattern which the LORD had shown Moses.</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="5" style="v" />The LORD spoke to Moses, saying, <verse number="6" style="v" />“Take the Levites from amongst the children of Israel, and cleanse them. <verse number="7" style="v" />You shall do this to them to cleanse them: sprinkle the water of cleansing on them, let them shave their whole bodies with a razor, let them wash their clothes, and cleanse themselves. <verse number="8" style="v" />Then let them take a young bull and its meal offering, fine flour mixed with oil; and another young bull you shall take for a sin offering. <verse number="9" style="v" />You shall present the Levites before the Tent of Meeting. You shall assemble the whole congregation of the children of Israel. <verse number="10" style="v" />You shall present the Levites before the LORD. The children of Israel shall lay their hands on the Levites, <verse number="11" style="v" />and Aaron shall offer the Levites before the LORD for a wave offering on the behalf of the children of Israel, that it may be theirs to do the service of the LORD.</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="12" style="v" />“The Levites shall lay their hands on the heads of the bulls, and you shall offer the one for a sin offering and the other for a burnt offering to the LORD, to make atonement for the Levites. <verse number="13" style="v" />You shall set the Levites before Aaron and before his sons, and offer them as a wave offering to the LORD. <verse number="14" style="v" />Thus you shall separate the Levites from amongst the children of Israel, and the Levites shall be mine.</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="15" style="v" />“After that, the Levites shall go in to do the service of the Tent of Meeting. You shall cleanse them, and offer them as a wave offering. <verse number="16" style="v" />For they are wholly given to me from amongst the children of Israel; instead of all who open the womb, even the firstborn of all the children of Israel, I have taken them to me. <verse number="17" style="v" />For all the firstborn amongst the children of Israel are mine, both man and animal. On the day that I struck all the firstborn in the land of Egypt, I sanctified them for myself. <verse number="18" style="v" />I have taken the Levites instead of all the firstborn amongst the children of Israel. <verse number="19" style="v" />I have given the Levites as a gift to Aaron and to his sons from amongst the children of Israel, to do the service of the children of Israel in the Tent of Meeting, and to make atonement for the children of Israel, so that there will be no plague amongst the children of Israel when the children of Israel come near to the sanctuary.”</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="20" style="v" />Moses, and Aaron, and all the congregation of the children of Israel did so to the Levites. According to all that the LORD commanded Moses concerning the Levites, so the children of Israel did to them. <verse number="21" style="v" />The Levites purified themselves from sin, and they washed their clothes; and Aaron offered them for a wave offering before the LORD and Aaron made atonement for them to cleanse them. <verse number="22" style="v" />After that, the Levites went in to do their service in the Tent of Meeting before Aaron and before his sons: as the LORD had commanded Moses concerning the Levites, so they did to them.</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="23" style="v" />The LORD spoke to Moses, saying, <verse number="24" style="v" />“This is what is assigned to the Levites: from twenty-five years old and upward they shall go in to wait on the service in the work of the Tent of Meeting; <verse number="25" style="v" />and from the age of fifty years they shall retire from doing the work, and shall serve no more, <verse number="26" style="v" />but shall assist their brothers in the Tent of Meeting, to perform the duty, and shall perform no service. This is how you shall have the Levites do their duties.”</para>
  <chapter number="9" style="c" />
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="1" style="v" />The LORD spoke to Moses in the wilderness of Sinai, in the first month of the second year after they had come out of the land of Egypt, saying, <verse number="2" style="v" />“Let the children of Israel keep the Passover in its appointed season. <verse number="3" style="v" />On the fourteenth day of this month, at evening, you shall keep it in its appointed season. You shall keep it according to all its statutes and according to all its ordinances.”</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="4" style="v" />Moses told the children of Israel that they should keep the Passover. <verse number="5" style="v" />They kept the Passover in the first month, on the fourteenth day of the month at evening, in the wilderness of Sinai. According to all that the LORD commanded Moses, so the children of Israel did. <verse number="6" style="v" />There were certain men, who were unclean because of the dead body of a man, so that they could not keep the Passover on that day, and they came before Moses and Aaron on that day. <verse number="7" style="v" />Those men said to him, “We are unclean because of the dead body of a man. Why are we kept back, that we may not offer the offering of the LORD in its appointed season amongst the children of Israel?”</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="8" style="v" />Moses answered them, “Wait, that I may hear what the LORD will command concerning you.”</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="9" style="v" />The LORD spoke to Moses, saying, <verse number="10" style="v" />“Say to the children of Israel, ‘If any man of you or of your generations is unclean by reason of a dead body, or is on a journey far away, he shall still keep the Passover to the LORD. <verse number="11" style="v" />In the second month, on the fourteenth day at evening they shall keep it; they shall eat it with unleavened bread and bitter herbs. <verse number="12" style="v" />They shall leave none of it until the morning, nor break a bone of it. According to all the statute of the Passover they shall keep it. <verse number="13" style="v" />But the man who is clean, and is not on a journey, and fails to keep the Passover, that soul shall be cut off from his people. Because he didn’t offer the offering of the LORD in its appointed season, that man shall bear his sin.</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="14" style="v" />“‘If a foreigner lives amongst you, and desires to keep the Passover to the LORD, then he shall do so according to the statute of the Passover, and according to its ordinance. You shall have one statute, both for the foreigner, and for him who is born in the land.’”</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="15" style="v" />On the day that the tabernacle was raised up, the cloud covered the tabernacle, even the Tent of the Testimony. At evening it was over the tabernacle, as it were the appearance of fire, until morning. <verse number="16" style="v" />So it was continually. The cloud covered it, and the appearance of fire by night. <verse number="17" style="v" />Whenever the cloud was taken up from over the Tent, then after that the children of Israel travelled; and in the place where the cloud remained, there the children of Israel encamped. <verse number="18" style="v" />At the commandment of the LORD, the children of Israel travelled, and at the commandment of the LORD they encamped. As long as the cloud remained on the tabernacle they remained encamped. <verse number="19" style="v" />When the cloud stayed on the tabernacle many days, then the children of Israel kept the LORD’s command, and didn’t travel. <verse number="20" style="v" />Sometimes the cloud was a few days on the tabernacle; then according to the commandment of the LORD they remained encamped, and according to the commandment of the LORD they travelled. <verse number="21" style="v" />Sometimes the cloud was from evening until morning; and when the cloud was taken up in the morning, they travelled; or by day and by night, when the cloud was taken up, they travelled. <verse number="22" style="v" />Whether it was two days, or a month, or a year that the cloud stayed on the tabernacle, remaining on it, the children of Israel remained encamped, and didn’t travel; but when it was taken up, they travelled. <verse number="23" style="v" />At the commandment of the LORD they encamped, and at the commandment of the LORD they travelled. They kept the LORD’s command, at the commandment of the LORD by Moses.</para>
  <chapter number="10" style="c" />
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="1" style="v" />The LORD spoke to Moses, saying, <verse number="2" style="v" />“Make two trumpets of silver. You shall make them of beaten work. You shall use them for the calling of the congregation, and for the journeying of the camps. <verse number="3" style="v" />When they blow them, all the congregation shall gather themselves to you at the door of the Tent of Meeting. <verse number="4" style="v" />If they blow just one, then the princes, the heads of the thousands of Israel, shall gather themselves to you. <verse number="5" style="v" />When you blow an alarm, the camps that lie on the east side shall go forward. <verse number="6" style="v" />When you blow an alarm the second time, the camps that lie on the south side shall go forward. They shall blow an alarm for their journeys. <verse number="7" style="v" />But when the assembly is to be gathered together, you shall blow, but you shall not sound an alarm.</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="8" style="v" />“The sons of Aaron, the priests, shall blow the trumpets. This shall be to you for a statute forever throughout your generations. <verse number="9" style="v" />When you go to war in your land against the adversary who oppresses you, then you shall sound an alarm with the trumpets. Then you will be remembered before the LORD your God, and you will be saved from your enemies.</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="10" style="v" />“Also in the day of your gladness, and in your set feasts, and in the beginnings of your months, you shall blow the trumpets over your burnt offerings, and over the sacrifices of your peace offerings; and they shall be to you for a memorial before your God. I am the LORD your God.”</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="11" style="v" />In the second year, in the second month, on the twentieth day of the month, the cloud was taken up from over the tabernacle of the covenant. <verse number="12" style="v" />The children of Israel went forward on their journeys out of the wilderness of Sinai; and the cloud stayed in the wilderness of Paran. <verse number="13" style="v" />They first went forward according to the commandment of the LORD by Moses.</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="14" style="v" />First, the standard of the camp of the children of Judah went forward according to their armies. Nahshon the son of Amminadab was over his army. <verse number="15" style="v" />Nethanel the son of Zuar was over the army of the tribe of the children of Issachar. <verse number="16" style="v" />Eliab the son of Helon was over the army of the tribe of the children of Zebulun. <verse number="17" style="v" />The tabernacle was taken down; and the sons of Gershon and the sons of Merari, who bore the tabernacle, went forward. <verse number="18" style="v" />The standard of the camp of Reuben went forward according to their armies. Elizur the son of Shedeur was over his army. <verse number="19" style="v" />Shelumiel the son of Zurishaddai was over the army of the tribe of the children of Simeon. <verse number="20" style="v" />Eliasaph the son of Deuel was over the army of the tribe of the children of Gad.</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="21" style="v" />The Kohathites set forward, bearing the sanctuary. The others set up the tabernacle before they arrived.</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="22" style="v" />The standard of the camp of the children of Ephraim set forward according to their armies. Elishama the son of Ammihud was over his army. <verse number="23" style="v" />Gamaliel the son of Pedahzur was over the army of the tribe of the children of Manasseh. <verse number="24" style="v" />Abidan the son of Gideoni was over the army of the tribe of the children of Benjamin.</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="25" style="v" />The standard of the camp of the children of Dan, which was the rear guard of all the camps, set forward according to their armies. Ahiezer the son of Ammishaddai was over his army. <verse number="26" style="v" />Pagiel the son of Ochran was over the army of the tribe of the children of Asher. <verse number="27" style="v" />Ahira the son of Enan was over the army of the tribe of the children of Naphtali. <verse number="28" style="v" />Thus were the travels of the children of Israel according to their armies; and they went forward.</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="29" style="v" />Moses said to Hobab, the son of Reuel the Midianite, Moses’ father-in-law, “We are journeying to the place of which the LORD said, ‘I will give it to you.’ Come with us, and we will treat you well; for the LORD has spoken good concerning Israel.”</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="30" style="v" />He said to him, “I will not go; but I will depart to my own land, and to my relatives.”</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="31" style="v" />Moses said, “Don’t leave us, please; because you know how we are to encamp in the wilderness, and you can be our eyes. <verse number="32" style="v" />It shall be, if you go with us—yes, it shall be—that whatever good the LORD does to us, we will do the same to you.”</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="33" style="v" />They set forward from the Mount of the LORD three days’ journey. The ark of the LORD’s covenant went before them three days’ journey, to seek out a resting place for them. <verse number="34" style="v" />The cloud of the LORD was over them by day, when they set forward from the camp. <verse number="35" style="v" />When the ark went forward, Moses said, “Rise up, LORD, and let your enemies be scattered! Let those who hate you flee before you!” <verse number="36" style="v" />When it rested, he said, “Return, LORD, to the ten thousands of the thousands of Israel.”</para>
  <chapter number="11" style="c" />
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="1" style="v" />The people were complaining in the ears of the LORD. When the LORD heard it, his anger burnt; and the LORD’s fire burnt amongst them, and consumed some of the outskirts of the camp. <verse number="2" style="v" />The people cried to Moses; and Moses prayed to the LORD, and the fire abated. <verse number="3" style="v" />The name of that place was called Taberah,<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">11:3 </char><char style="ft" closed="false">Taberah means “burning” </char></note> because the LORD’s fire burnt amongst them.</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="4" style="v" />The mixed multitude that was amongst them lusted exceedingly; and the children of Israel also wept again, and said, “Who will give us meat to eat? <verse number="5" style="v" />We remember the fish, which we ate in Egypt for nothing; the cucumbers, and the melons, and the leeks, and the onions, and the garlic; <verse number="6" style="v" />but now we have lost our appetite. There is nothing at all except this manna to look at.” <verse number="7" style="v" />The manna was like coriander seed, and it looked like bdellium.<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">11:7 </char><char style="ft" closed="false">Bdellium is a resin extracted from certain African trees.</char></note> <verse number="8" style="v" />The people went around, gathered it, and ground it in mills, or beat it in mortars, and boiled it in pots, and made cakes of it. Its taste was like the taste of fresh oil. <verse number="9" style="v" />When the dew fell on the camp in the night, the manna fell on it.</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="10" style="v" />Moses heard the people weeping throughout their families, every man at the door of his tent; and the LORD’s anger burnt greatly; and Moses was displeased. <verse number="11" style="v" />Moses said to the LORD, “Why have you treated your servant so badly? Why haven’t I found favour in your sight, that you lay the burden of all this people on me? <verse number="12" style="v" />Have I conceived all this people? Have I brought them out, that you should tell me, ‘Carry them in your bosom, as a nurse carries a nursing infant, to the land which you swore to their fathers?’ <verse number="13" style="v" />Where could I get meat to give all these people? For they weep before me, saying, ‘Give us meat, that we may eat.’ <verse number="14" style="v" />I am not able to bear all this people alone, because it is too heavy for me. <verse number="15" style="v" />If you treat me this way, please kill me right now, if I have found favour in your sight; and don’t let me see my wretchedness.”</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="16" style="v" />The LORD said to Moses, “Gather to me seventy men of the elders of Israel, whom you know to be the elders of the people and officers over them; and bring them to the Tent of Meeting, that they may stand there with you. <verse number="17" style="v" />I will come down and talk with you there. I will take of the Spirit which is on you, and will put it on them; and they shall bear the burden of the people with you, that you don’t bear it yourself alone.</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="18" style="v" />“Say to the people, ‘Sanctify yourselves in preparation for tomorrow, and you will eat meat; for you have wept in the ears of the LORD, saying, “Who will give us meat to eat? For it was well with us in Egypt.” Therefore the LORD will give you meat, and you will eat. <verse number="19" style="v" />You will not eat just one day, or two days, or five days, or ten days, or twenty days, <verse number="20" style="v" />but a whole month, until it comes out at your nostrils, and it is loathsome to you; because you have rejected the LORD who is amongst you, and have wept before him, saying, “Why did we come out of Egypt?”’”</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="21" style="v" />Moses said, “The people, amongst whom I am, are six hundred thousand men on foot; and you have said, ‘I will give them meat, that they may eat a whole month.’ <verse number="22" style="v" />Shall flocks and herds be slaughtered for them, to be sufficient for them? Shall all the fish of the sea be gathered together for them, to be sufficient for them?”</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="23" style="v" />The LORD said to Moses, “Has the LORD’s hand grown short? Now you will see whether my word will happen to you or not.”</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="24" style="v" />Moses went out, and told the people the LORD’s words; and he gathered seventy men of the elders of the people, and set them around the Tent. <verse number="25" style="v" />The LORD came down in the cloud, and spoke to him, and took of the Spirit that was on him, and put it on the seventy elders. When the Spirit rested on them, they prophesied, but they did so no more. <verse number="26" style="v" />But two men remained in the camp. The name of one was Eldad, and the name of the other Medad; and the Spirit rested on them. They were of those who were written, but had not gone out to the Tent; and they prophesied in the camp. <verse number="27" style="v" />A young man ran, and told Moses, and said, “Eldad and Medad are prophesying in the camp!”</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="28" style="v" />Joshua the son of Nun, the servant of Moses, one of his chosen men, answered, “My lord Moses, forbid them!”</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="29" style="v" />Moses said to him, “Are you jealous for my sake? I wish that all the LORD’s people were prophets, that the LORD would put his Spirit on them!”</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="30" style="v" />Moses went into the camp, he and the elders of Israel. <verse number="31" style="v" />A wind from the LORD went out and brought quails from the sea, and let them fall by the camp, about a day’s journey on this side, and a day’s journey on the other side, around the camp, and about two cubits<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">11:31 </char><char style="ft" closed="false">A cubit is the length from the tip of the middle finger to the elbow on a man’s arm, or about 18 inches or 46 centimetres.</char></note> above the surface of the earth. <verse number="32" style="v" />The people rose up all that day, and all of that night, and all the next day, and gathered the quails. He who gathered least gathered ten homers;<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">11:32 </char><char style="ft" closed="false">1 homer is about 220 litres or 6 bushels</char></note> and they spread them all out for themselves around the camp. <verse number="33" style="v" />While the meat was still between their teeth, before it was chewed, the LORD’s anger burnt against the people, and the LORD struck the people with a very great plague. <verse number="34" style="v" />The name of that place was called Kibroth Hattaavah,<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">11:34 </char><char style="ft" closed="false">Kibroth Hattaavah means “graves of lust”</char></note> because there they buried the people who lusted.</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="35" style="v" />From Kibroth Hattaavah the people travelled to Hazeroth; and they stayed at Hazeroth.</para>
  <chapter number="12" style="c" />
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="1" style="v" />Miriam and Aaron spoke against Moses because of the Cushite woman whom he had married; for he had married a Cushite woman. <verse number="2" style="v" />They said, “Has the LORD indeed spoken only with Moses? Hasn’t he spoken also with us?” And the LORD heard it.</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="3" style="v" />Now the man Moses was very humble, more than all the men who were on the surface of the earth. <verse number="4" style="v" />The LORD spoke suddenly to Moses, to Aaron, and to Miriam, “You three come out to the Tent of Meeting!”</para>
  <para style="p">The three of them came out. <verse number="5" style="v" />The LORD came down in a pillar of cloud, and stood at the door of the Tent, and called Aaron and Miriam; and they both came forward. <verse number="6" style="v" />He said, “Now hear my words. If there is a prophet amongst you, I, the LORD, will make myself known to him in a vision. I will speak with him in a dream. <verse number="7" style="v" />My servant Moses is not so. He is faithful in all my house. <verse number="8" style="v" />With him, I will speak mouth to mouth, even plainly, and not in riddles; and he shall see the LORD’s form. Why then were you not afraid to speak against my servant, against Moses?” <verse number="9" style="v" />The LORD’s anger burnt against them; and he departed.</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="10" style="v" />The cloud departed from over the Tent; and behold, Miriam was leprous, as white as snow. Aaron looked at Miriam, and behold, she was leprous.</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="11" style="v" />Aaron said to Moses, “Oh, my lord, please don’t count this sin against us, in which we have done foolishly, and in which we have sinned. <verse number="12" style="v" />Let her not, I pray, be as one dead, of whom the flesh is half consumed when he comes out of his mother’s womb.”</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="13" style="v" />Moses cried to the LORD, saying, “Heal her, God, I beg you!”</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="14" style="v" />The LORD said to Moses, “If her father had but spit in her face, shouldn’t she be ashamed seven days? Let her be shut up outside of the camp seven days, and after that she shall be brought in again.”</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="15" style="v" />Miriam was shut up outside of the camp seven days, and the people didn’t travel until Miriam was brought in again. <verse number="16" style="v" />Afterward the people travelled from Hazeroth, and encamped in the wilderness of Paran.</para>
  <chapter number="13" style="c" />
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="1" style="v" />The LORD spoke to Moses, saying, <verse number="2" style="v" />“Send men, that they may spy out the land of Canaan, which I give to the children of Israel. Of every tribe of their fathers, you shall send a man, every one a prince amongst them.”</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="3" style="v" />Moses sent them from the wilderness of Paran according to the commandment of the LORD. All of them were men who were heads of the children of Israel. <verse number="4" style="v" />These were their names:</para>
  <para style="m">Of the tribe of Reuben, Shammua the son of Zaccur.</para>
  <para style="m">
    <verse number="5" style="v" />Of the tribe of Simeon, Shaphat the son of Hori.</para>
  <para style="m">
    <verse number="6" style="v" />Of the tribe of Judah, Caleb the son of Jephunneh.</para>
  <para style="m">
    <verse number="7" style="v" />Of the tribe of Issachar, Igal the son of Joseph.</para>
  <para style="m">
    <verse number="8" style="v" />Of the tribe of Ephraim, Hoshea the son of Nun.</para>
  <para style="m">
    <verse number="9" style="v" />Of the tribe of Benjamin, Palti the son of Raphu.</para>
  <para style="m">
    <verse number="10" style="v" />Of the tribe of Zebulun, Gaddiel the son of Sodi.</para>
  <para style="m">
    <verse number="11" style="v" />Of the tribe of Joseph, of the tribe of Manasseh, Gaddi the son of Susi.</para>
  <para style="m">
    <verse number="12" style="v" />Of the tribe of Dan, Ammiel the son of Gemalli.</para>
  <para style="m">
    <verse number="13" style="v" />Of the tribe of Asher, Sethur the son of Michael.</para>
  <para style="m">
    <verse number="14" style="v" />Of the tribe of Naphtali, Nahbi the son of Vophsi.</para>
  <para style="m">
    <verse number="15" style="v" />Of the tribe of Gad, Geuel the son of Machi.</para>
  <para style="m">
    <verse number="16" style="v" />These are the names of the men who Moses sent to spy out the land. Moses called Hoshea the son of Nun Joshua. <verse number="17" style="v" />Moses sent them to spy out the land of Canaan, and said to them, “Go up this way by the South, and go up into the hill country. <verse number="18" style="v" />See the land, what it is; and the people who dwell therein, whether they are strong or weak, whether they are few or many; <verse number="19" style="v" />and what the land is that they dwell in, whether it is good or bad; and what cities they are that they dwell in, whether in camps, or in strongholds; <verse number="20" style="v" />and what the land is, whether it is fertile or poor, whether there is wood therein, or not. Be courageous, and bring some of the fruit of the land.” Now the time was the time of the first-ripe grapes.</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="21" style="v" />So they went up, and spied out the land from the wilderness of Zin to Rehob, to the entrance of Hamath. <verse number="22" style="v" />They went up by the South, and came to Hebron; and Ahiman, Sheshai, and Talmai, the children of Anak, were there. (Now Hebron was built seven years before Zoan in Egypt.) <verse number="23" style="v" />They came to the valley of Eshcol, and cut down from there a branch with one cluster of grapes, and they bore it on a staff between two. They also brought some of the pomegranates and figs. <verse number="24" style="v" />That place was called the valley of Eshcol, because of the cluster which the children of Israel cut down from there. <verse number="25" style="v" />They returned from spying out the land at the end of forty days. <verse number="26" style="v" />They went and came to Moses, to Aaron, and to all the congregation of the children of Israel, to the wilderness of Paran, to Kadesh; and brought back word to them and to all the congregation. They showed them the fruit of the land. <verse number="27" style="v" />They told him, and said, “We came to the land where you sent us. Surely it flows with milk and honey, and this is its fruit. <verse number="28" style="v" />However, the people who dwell in the land are strong, and the cities are fortified and very large. Moreover, we saw the children of Anak there. <verse number="29" style="v" />Amalek dwells in the land of the South. The Hittite, the Jebusite, and the Amorite dwell in the hill country. The Canaanite dwells by the sea, and along the side of the Jordan.”</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="30" style="v" />Caleb stilled the people before Moses, and said, “Let’s go up at once, and possess it; for we are well able to overcome it!”</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="31" style="v" />But the men who went up with him said, “We aren’t able to go up against the people; for they are stronger than we.” <verse number="32" style="v" />They brought up an evil report of the land which they had spied out to the children of Israel, saying, “The land, through which we have gone to spy it out, is a land that eats up its inhabitants; and all the people who we saw in it are men of great stature. <verse number="33" style="v" />There we saw the Nephilim,<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">13:33 </char><char style="ft" closed="false">or, giants</char></note> the sons of Anak, who come from the Nephilim.<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">13:33 </char><char style="ft" closed="false">or, giants</char></note> We were in our own sight as grasshoppers, and so we were in their sight.”</para>
  <chapter number="14" style="c" />
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="1" style="v" />All the congregation lifted up their voice, and cried; and the people wept that night. <verse number="2" style="v" />All the children of Israel murmured against Moses and against Aaron. The whole congregation said to them, “We wish that we had died in the land of Egypt, or that we had died in this wilderness! <verse number="3" style="v" />Why does the LORD bring us to this land, to fall by the sword? Our wives and our little ones will be captured or killed! Wouldn’t it be better for us to return into Egypt?” <verse number="4" style="v" />They said to one another, “Let’s choose a leader, and let’s return into Egypt.”</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="5" style="v" />Then Moses and Aaron fell on their faces before all the assembly of the congregation of the children of Israel.</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="6" style="v" />Joshua the son of Nun and Caleb the son of Jephunneh, who were of those who spied out the land, tore their clothes. <verse number="7" style="v" />They spoke to all the congregation of the children of Israel, saying, “The land, which we passed through to spy it out, is an exceedingly good land. <verse number="8" style="v" />If the LORD delights in us, then he will bring us into this land, and give it to us: a land which flows with milk and honey. <verse number="9" style="v" />Only don’t rebel against the LORD, neither fear the people of the land; for they are bread for us. Their defence is removed from over them, and the LORD is with us. Don’t fear them.”</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="10" style="v" />But all the congregation threatened to stone them with stones.</para>
  <para style="p">The LORD’s glory appeared in the Tent of Meeting to all the children of Israel. <verse number="11" style="v" />The LORD said to Moses, “How long will this people despise me? How long will they not believe in me, for all the signs which I have worked amongst them? <verse number="12" style="v" />I will strike them with the pestilence, and disinherit them, and will make of you a nation greater and mightier than they.”</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="13" style="v" />Moses said to the LORD, “Then the Egyptians will hear it; for you brought up this people in your might from amongst them. <verse number="14" style="v" />They will tell it to the inhabitants of this land. They have heard that you LORD are amongst this people; for you LORD are seen face to face, and your cloud stands over them, and you go before them, in a pillar of cloud by day, and in a pillar of fire by night. <verse number="15" style="v" />Now if you killed this people as one man, then the nations which have heard the fame of you will speak, saying, <verse number="16" style="v" />‘Because the LORD was not able to bring this people into the land which he swore to them, therefore he has slain them in the wilderness.’ <verse number="17" style="v" />Now please let the power of the Lord<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">14:17 </char><char style="ft" closed="false">The word translated “Lord” is “Adonai.”</char></note> be great, according as you have spoken, saying, <verse number="18" style="v" />‘The LORD is slow to anger, and abundant in loving kindness, forgiving iniquity and disobedience; and he will by no means clear the guilty, visiting the iniquity of the fathers on the children, on the third and on the fourth generation.’ <verse number="19" style="v" />Please pardon the iniquity of this people according to the greatness of your loving kindness, and just as you have forgiven this people, from Egypt even until now.”</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="20" style="v" />The LORD said, “I have pardoned according to your word; <verse number="21" style="v" />but in very deed—as I live, and as all the earth shall be filled with the LORD’s glory— <verse number="22" style="v" />because all those men who have seen my glory and my signs, which I worked in Egypt and in the wilderness, yet have tempted me these ten times, and have not listened to my voice; <verse number="23" style="v" />surely they shall not see the land which I swore to their fathers, neither shall any of those who despised me see it. <verse number="24" style="v" />But my servant Caleb, because he had another spirit with him, and has followed me fully, him I will bring into the land into which he went. His offspring shall possess it. <verse number="25" style="v" />Since the Amalekite and the Canaanite dwell in the valley, tomorrow turn and go into the wilderness by the way to the Red Sea.” <verse number="26" style="v" />The LORD spoke to Moses and to Aaron, saying, <verse number="27" style="v" />“How long shall I bear with this evil congregation that complain against me? I have heard the complaints of the children of Israel, which they complain against me. <verse number="28" style="v" />Tell them, ‘As I live, says the LORD, surely as you have spoken in my ears, so I will do to you. <verse number="29" style="v" />Your dead bodies shall fall in this wilderness; and all who were counted of you, according to your whole number, from twenty years old and upward, who have complained against me, <verse number="30" style="v" />surely you shall not come into the land concerning which I swore that I would make you dwell therein, except Caleb the son of Jephunneh, and Joshua the son of Nun. <verse number="31" style="v" />But I will bring in your little ones that you said should be captured or killed, and they shall know the land which you have rejected. <verse number="32" style="v" />But as for you, your dead bodies shall fall in this wilderness. <verse number="33" style="v" />Your children shall be wanderers in the wilderness forty years, and shall bear your prostitution, until your dead bodies are consumed in the wilderness. <verse number="34" style="v" />After the number of the days in which you spied out the land, even forty days, for every day a year, you will bear your iniquities, even forty years, and you will know my alienation.’ <verse number="35" style="v" />I, the LORD, have spoken. I will surely do this to all this evil congregation who are gathered together against me. In this wilderness they shall be consumed, and there they shall die.”</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="36" style="v" />The men whom Moses sent to spy out the land, who returned and made all the congregation to murmur against him by bringing up an evil report against the land, <verse number="37" style="v" />even those men who brought up an evil report of the land, died by the plague before the LORD. <verse number="38" style="v" />But Joshua the son of Nun and Caleb the son of Jephunneh remained alive of those men who went to spy out the land.</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="39" style="v" />Moses told these words to all the children of Israel, and the people mourned greatly. <verse number="40" style="v" />They rose up early in the morning and went up to the top of the mountain, saying, “Behold, we are here, and will go up to the place which the LORD has promised; for we have sinned.”</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="41" style="v" />Moses said, “Why now do you disobey the commandment of the LORD, since it shall not prosper? <verse number="42" style="v" />Don’t go up, for the LORD isn’t amongst you; that way you won’t be struck down before your enemies. <verse number="43" style="v" />For there the Amalekite and the Canaanite are before you, and you will fall by the sword because you turned back from following the LORD; therefore the LORD will not be with you.”</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="44" style="v" />But they presumed to go up to the top of the mountain. Nevertheless, the ark of the LORD’s covenant and Moses didn’t depart out of the camp. <verse number="45" style="v" />Then the Amalekites came down, and the Canaanites who lived in that mountain, and struck them and beat them down even to Hormah.</para>
  <chapter number="15" style="c" />
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="1" style="v" />The LORD spoke to Moses, saying, <verse number="2" style="v" />“Speak to the children of Israel, and tell them, ‘When you have come into the land of your habitations, which I give to you, <verse number="3" style="v" />and will make an offering by fire to the LORD—a burnt offering, or a sacrifice, to accomplish a vow, or as a free will offering, or in your set feasts, to make a pleasant aroma to the LORD, of the herd, or of the flock— <verse number="4" style="v" />then he who offers his offering shall offer to the LORD a meal offering of one tenth of an ephah<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">15:4 </char><char style="ft" closed="false">1 ephah is about 22 litres or about 2/3 of a bushel</char></note> of fine flour mixed with one fourth of a hin<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">15:4 </char><char style="ft" closed="false">A hin is about 6.5 litres or 1.7 gallons.</char></note> of oil. <verse number="5" style="v" />You shall prepare wine for the drink offering, one fourth of a hin, with the burnt offering or for the sacrifice, for each lamb.</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="6" style="v" />“‘For a ram, you shall prepare for a meal offering two tenths of an ephah<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">15:6 </char><char style="ft" closed="false">1 ephah is about 22 litres or about 2/3 of a bushel</char></note> of fine flour mixed with the third part of a hin of oil; <verse number="7" style="v" />and for the drink offering you shall offer the third part of a hin of wine, of a pleasant aroma to the LORD. <verse number="8" style="v" />When you prepare a bull for a burnt offering or for a sacrifice, to accomplish a vow, or for peace offerings to the LORD, <verse number="9" style="v" />then he shall offer with the bull a meal offering of three tenths of an ephah<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">15:9 </char><char style="ft" closed="false">1 ephah is about 22 litres or about 2/3 of a bushel</char></note> of fine flour mixed with half a hin of oil; <verse number="10" style="v" />and you shall offer for the drink offering half a hin of wine, for an offering made by fire, of a pleasant aroma to the LORD. <verse number="11" style="v" />Thus it shall be done for each bull, for each ram, for each of the male lambs, or of the young goats. <verse number="12" style="v" />According to the number that you shall prepare, so you shall do to everyone according to their number.</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="13" style="v" />“‘All who are native-born shall do these things in this way, in offering an offering made by fire, of a pleasant aroma to the LORD. <verse number="14" style="v" />If a stranger lives as a foreigner with you, or whoever may be amongst you throughout your generations, and will offer an offering made by fire, of a pleasant aroma to the LORD, as you do, so he shall do. <verse number="15" style="v" />For the assembly, there shall be one statute for you and for the stranger who lives as a foreigner, a statute forever throughout your generations. As you are, so the foreigner shall be before the LORD. <verse number="16" style="v" />One law and one ordinance shall be for you and for the stranger who lives as a foreigner with you.’”</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="17" style="v" />The LORD spoke to Moses, saying, <verse number="18" style="v" />“Speak to the children of Israel, and tell them, ‘When you come into the land where I bring you, <verse number="19" style="v" />then it shall be that when you eat of the bread of the land, you shall offer up a wave offering to the LORD. <verse number="20" style="v" />Of the first of your dough you shall offer up a cake for a wave offering. As the wave offering of the threshing floor, so you shall heave it. <verse number="21" style="v" />Of the first of your dough, you shall give to the LORD a wave offering throughout your generations.</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="22" style="v" />“‘When you err, and don’t observe all these commandments which the LORD has spoken to Moses— <verse number="23" style="v" />even all that the LORD has commanded you by Moses, from the day that the LORD gave commandment and onward throughout your generations— <verse number="24" style="v" />then it shall be, if it was done unwittingly, without the knowledge of the congregation, that all the congregation shall offer one young bull for a burnt offering, for a pleasant aroma to the LORD, with its meal offering and its drink offering, according to the ordinance, and one male goat for a sin offering. <verse number="25" style="v" />The priest shall make atonement for all the congregation of the children of Israel, and they shall be forgiven; for it was an error, and they have brought their offering, an offering made by fire to the LORD, and their sin offering before the LORD, for their error. <verse number="26" style="v" />All the congregation of the children of Israel shall be forgiven, as well as the stranger who lives as a foreigner amongst them; for with regard to all the people, it was done unwittingly.</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="27" style="v" />“‘If a person sins unwittingly, then he shall offer a female goat a year old for a sin offering. <verse number="28" style="v" />The priest shall make atonement for the soul who errs when he sins unwittingly before the LORD. He shall make atonement for him; and he shall be forgiven. <verse number="29" style="v" />You shall have one law for him who does anything unwittingly, for him who is native-born amongst the children of Israel, and for the stranger who lives as a foreigner amongst them.</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="30" style="v" />“‘But the soul who does anything with a high hand, whether he is native-born or a foreigner, blasphemes the LORD. That soul shall be cut off from amongst his people. <verse number="31" style="v" />Because he has despised the LORD’s word, and has broken his commandment, that soul shall be utterly cut off. His iniquity shall be on him.’”</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="32" style="v" />While the children of Israel were in the wilderness, they found a man gathering sticks on the Sabbath day. <verse number="33" style="v" />Those who found him gathering sticks brought him to Moses and Aaron, and to all the congregation. <verse number="34" style="v" />They put him in custody, because it had not been declared what should be done to him.</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="35" style="v" />The LORD said to Moses, “The man shall surely be put to death. All the congregation shall stone him with stones outside of the camp.” <verse number="36" style="v" />All the congregation brought him outside of the camp, and stoned him to death with stones, as the LORD commanded Moses.</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="37" style="v" />The LORD spoke to Moses, saying, <verse number="38" style="v" />“Speak to the children of Israel, and tell them that they should make themselves fringes<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">15:38 </char><char style="ft" closed="false">or, tassels (Hebrew צִיצִ֛ת)</char></note> on the borders of their garments throughout their generations, and that they put on the fringe<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">15:38 </char><char style="ft" closed="false">or, tassel</char></note> of each border a cord of blue. <verse number="39" style="v" />It shall be to you for a fringe,<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">15:39 </char><char style="ft" closed="false">or, tassel</char></note> that you may see it, and remember all the LORD’s commandments, and do them; and that you don’t follow your own heart and your own eyes, after which you used to play the prostitute; <verse number="40" style="v" />so that you may remember and do all my commandments, and be holy to your God. <verse number="41" style="v" />I am the LORD your God, who brought you out of the land of Egypt, to be your God: I am the LORD your God.”</para>
  <chapter number="16" style="c" />
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="1" style="v" />Now Korah, the son of Izhar, the son of Kohath, the son of Levi, with Dathan and Abiram, the sons of Eliab, and On, the son of Peleth, sons of Reuben, took some men. <verse number="2" style="v" />They rose up before Moses, with some of the children of Israel, two hundred and fifty princes of the congregation, called to the assembly, men of renown. <verse number="3" style="v" />They assembled themselves together against Moses and against Aaron, and said to them, “You take too much on yourself, since all the congregation are holy, everyone of them, and the LORD is amongst them! Why do you lift yourselves up above the LORD’s assembly?”</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="4" style="v" />When Moses heard it, he fell on his face. <verse number="5" style="v" />He said to Korah and to all his company, “In the morning, the LORD will show who are his, and who is holy, and will cause him to come near to him. Even him whom he shall choose, he will cause to come near to him. <verse number="6" style="v" />Do this: have Korah and all his company take censers, <verse number="7" style="v" />put fire in them, and put incense on them before the LORD tomorrow. It shall be that the man whom the LORD chooses, he shall be holy. You have gone too far, you sons of Levi!”</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="8" style="v" />Moses said to Korah, “Hear now, you sons of Levi! <verse number="9" style="v" />Is it a small thing to you that the God of Israel has separated you from the congregation of Israel, to bring you near to himself, to do the service of the LORD’s tabernacle, and to stand before the congregation to minister to them; <verse number="10" style="v" />and that he has brought you near, and all your brothers the sons of Levi with you? Do you seek the priesthood also? <verse number="11" style="v" />Therefore you and all your company have gathered together against the LORD! What is Aaron that you complain against him?”</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="12" style="v" />Moses sent to call Dathan and Abiram, the sons of Eliab; and they said, “We won’t come up! <verse number="13" style="v" />Is it a small thing that you have brought us up out of a land flowing with milk and honey, to kill us in the wilderness, but you must also make yourself a prince over us? <verse number="14" style="v" />Moreover you haven’t brought us into a land flowing with milk and honey, nor given us inheritance of fields and vineyards. Will you put out the eyes of these men? We won’t come up.”</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="15" style="v" />Moses was very angry, and said to the LORD, “Don’t respect their offering. I have not taken one donkey from them, neither have I hurt one of them.”</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="16" style="v" />Moses said to Korah, “You and all your company go before the LORD, you, and they, and Aaron, tomorrow. <verse number="17" style="v" />Each man take his censer and put incense on it, and each man bring before the LORD his censer, two hundred and fifty censers; you also, and Aaron, each with his censer.”</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="18" style="v" />They each took his censer, and put fire in it, and laid incense on it, and stood at the door of the Tent of Meeting with Moses and Aaron. <verse number="19" style="v" />Korah assembled all the congregation opposite them to the door of the Tent of Meeting.</para>
  <para style="p">The LORD’s glory appeared to all the congregation. <verse number="20" style="v" />The LORD spoke to Moses and to Aaron, saying, <verse number="21" style="v" />“Separate yourselves from amongst this congregation, that I may consume them in a moment!”</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="22" style="v" />They fell on their faces, and said, “God, the God of the spirits of all flesh, shall one man sin, and will you be angry with all the congregation?”</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="23" style="v" />The LORD spoke to Moses, saying, <verse number="24" style="v" />“Speak to the congregation, saying, ‘Get away from around the tent of Korah, Dathan, and Abiram!’”</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="25" style="v" />Moses rose up and went to Dathan and Abiram; and the elders of Israel followed him. <verse number="26" style="v" />He spoke to the congregation, saying, “Depart, please, from the tents of these wicked men, and touch nothing of theirs, lest you be consumed in all their sins!”</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="27" style="v" />So they went away from the tent of Korah, Dathan, and Abiram, on every side. Dathan and Abiram came out, and stood at the door of their tents with their wives, their sons, and their little ones.</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="28" style="v" />Moses said, “Hereby you shall know that the LORD has sent me to do all these works; for they are not from my own mind. <verse number="29" style="v" />If these men die the common death of all men, or if they experience what all men experience, then the LORD hasn’t sent me. <verse number="30" style="v" />But if the LORD makes a new thing, and the ground opens its mouth, and swallows them up with all that belong to them, and they go down alive into Sheol,<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">16:30 </char><char style="ft" closed="false">Sheol is the place of the dead.</char></note> then you shall understand that these men have despised the LORD.”</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="31" style="v" />As he finished speaking all these words, the ground that was under them split apart. <verse number="32" style="v" />The earth opened its mouth and swallowed them up with their households, all of Korah’s men, and all their goods. <verse number="33" style="v" />So they, and all that belonged to them went down alive into Sheol.<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">16:33 </char><char style="ft" closed="false">Sheol is the place of the dead.</char></note> The earth closed on them, and they perished from amongst the assembly. <verse number="34" style="v" />All Israel that were around them fled at their cry; for they said, “Lest the earth swallow us up!” <verse number="35" style="v" />Fire came out from the LORD, and devoured the two hundred and fifty men who offered the incense.</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="36" style="v" />The LORD spoke to Moses, saying, <verse number="37" style="v" />“Speak to Eleazar the son of Aaron the priest, that he take up the censers out of the burning, and scatter the fire away from the camp; for they are holy, <verse number="38" style="v" />even the censers of those who sinned against their own lives. Let them be beaten into plates for a covering of the altar, for they offered them before the LORD. Therefore they are holy. They shall be a sign to the children of Israel.”</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="39" style="v" />Eleazar the priest took the bronze censers which those who were burnt had offered; and they beat them out for a covering of the altar, <verse number="40" style="v" />to be a memorial to the children of Israel, to the end that no stranger who isn’t of the offspring of Aaron, would come near to burn incense before the LORD, that he not be as Korah and as his company; as the LORD spoke to him by Moses.</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="41" style="v" />But on the next day all the congregation of the children of Israel complained against Moses and against Aaron, saying, “You have killed the LORD’s people!”</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="42" style="v" />When the congregation was assembled against Moses and against Aaron, they looked towards the Tent of Meeting. Behold, the cloud covered it, and the LORD’s glory appeared. <verse number="43" style="v" />Moses and Aaron came to the front of the Tent of Meeting. <verse number="44" style="v" />The LORD spoke to Moses, saying, <verse number="45" style="v" />“Get away from amongst this congregation, that I may consume them in a moment!” They fell on their faces.</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="46" style="v" />Moses said to Aaron, “Take your censer, put fire from the altar in it, lay incense on it, carry it quickly to the congregation, and make atonement for them; for wrath has gone out from the LORD! The plague has begun.”</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="47" style="v" />Aaron did as Moses said, and ran into the middle of the assembly. The plague had already begun amongst the people. He put on the incense, and made atonement for the people. <verse number="48" style="v" />He stood between the dead and the living; and the plague was stayed. <verse number="49" style="v" />Now those who died by the plague were fourteen thousand and seven hundred, in addition to those who died about the matter of Korah. <verse number="50" style="v" />Aaron returned to Moses to the door of the Tent of Meeting, and the plague was stopped.</para>
  <chapter number="17" style="c" />
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="1" style="v" />The LORD spoke to Moses, saying, <verse number="2" style="v" />“Speak to the children of Israel, and take rods from them, one for each fathers’ house, of all their princes according to their fathers’ houses, twelve rods. Write each man’s name on his rod. <verse number="3" style="v" />You shall write Aaron’s name on Levi’s rod. There shall be one rod for each head of their fathers’ houses. <verse number="4" style="v" />You shall lay them up in the Tent of Meeting before the covenant, where I meet with you. <verse number="5" style="v" />It shall happen that the rod of the man whom I shall choose shall bud. I will make the murmurings of the children of Israel, which they murmur against you, cease from me.”</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="6" style="v" />Moses spoke to the children of Israel; and all their princes gave him rods, for each prince one, according to their fathers’ houses, a total of twelve rods. Aaron’s rod was amongst their rods. <verse number="7" style="v" />Moses laid up the rods before the LORD in the Tent of the Testimony.</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="8" style="v" />On the next day, Moses went into the Tent of the Testimony; and behold, Aaron’s rod for the house of Levi had sprouted, budded, produced blossoms, and bore ripe almonds. <verse number="9" style="v" />Moses brought out all the rods from before the LORD to all the children of Israel. They looked, and each man took his rod.</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="10" style="v" />The LORD said to Moses, “Put back the rod of Aaron before the covenant, to be kept for a token against the children of rebellion; that you may make an end of their complaining against me, that they not die.” <verse number="11" style="v" />Moses did so. As the LORD commanded him, so he did.</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="12" style="v" />The children of Israel spoke to Moses, saying, “Behold, we perish! We are undone! We are all undone! <verse number="13" style="v" />Everyone who keeps approaching the LORD’s tabernacle, dies! Will we all perish?”</para>
  <chapter number="18" style="c" />
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="1" style="v" />The LORD said to Aaron, “You and your sons and your fathers’ house with you shall bear the iniquity of the sanctuary; and you and your sons with you shall bear the iniquity of your priesthood. <verse number="2" style="v" />Bring your brothers also, the tribe of Levi, the tribe of your father, near with you, that they may be joined to you, and minister to you; but you and your sons with you shall be before the Tent of the Testimony. <verse number="3" style="v" />They shall keep your commands and the duty of the whole Tent; only they shall not come near to the vessels of the sanctuary and to the altar, that they not die, neither they nor you. <verse number="4" style="v" />They shall be joined to you and keep the responsibility of the Tent of Meeting, for all the service of the Tent. A stranger shall not come near to you.</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="5" style="v" />“You shall perform the duty of the sanctuary and the duty of the altar, that there be no more wrath on the children of Israel. <verse number="6" style="v" />Behold, I myself have taken your brothers the Levites from amongst the children of Israel. They are a gift to you, dedicated to the LORD, to do the service of the Tent of Meeting. <verse number="7" style="v" />You and your sons with you shall keep your priesthood for everything of the altar, and for that within the veil. You shall serve. I give you the service of the priesthood as a gift. The stranger who comes near shall be put to death.”</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="8" style="v" />The LORD spoke to Aaron, “Behold, I myself have given you the command of my wave offerings, even all the holy things of the children of Israel. I have given them to you by reason of the anointing, and to your sons, as a portion forever. <verse number="9" style="v" />This shall be yours of the most holy things from the fire: every offering of theirs, even every meal offering of theirs, and every sin offering of theirs, and every trespass offering of theirs, which they shall render to me, shall be most holy for you and for your sons. <verse number="10" style="v" />You shall eat of it like the most holy things. Every male shall eat of it. It shall be holy to you.</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="11" style="v" />“This is yours, too: the wave offering of their gift, even all the wave offerings of the children of Israel. I have given them to you, and to your sons and to your daughters with you, as a portion forever. Everyone who is clean in your house shall eat of it.</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="12" style="v" />“I have given to you all the best of the oil, all the best of the vintage, and of the grain, the first fruits of them which they give to the LORD. <verse number="13" style="v" />The first-ripe fruits of all that is in their land, which they bring to the LORD, shall be yours. Everyone who is clean in your house shall eat of it.</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="14" style="v" />“Everything devoted in Israel shall be yours. <verse number="15" style="v" />Everything that opens the womb, of all flesh which they offer to the LORD, both of man and animal, shall be yours. Nevertheless, you shall surely redeem the firstborn of man, and you shall redeem the firstborn of unclean animals. <verse number="16" style="v" />You shall redeem those who are to be redeemed of them from a month old, according to your estimation, for five shekels of money, according to the shekel<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">18:16 </char><char style="ft" closed="false">A shekel is about 10 grams or about 0.35 ounces.</char></note> of the sanctuary, which weighs twenty gerahs.<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">18:16 </char><char style="ft" closed="false">A gerah is about 0.5 grams or about 7.7 grains.</char></note></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="17" style="v" />“But you shall not redeem the firstborn of a cow, or the firstborn of a sheep, or the firstborn of a goat. They are holy. You shall sprinkle their blood on the altar, and shall burn their fat for an offering made by fire, for a pleasant aroma to the LORD. <verse number="18" style="v" />Their meat shall be yours, as the wave offering breast and as the right thigh, it shall be yours. <verse number="19" style="v" />All the wave offerings of the holy things which the children of Israel offer to the LORD, I have given you and your sons and your daughters with you, as a portion forever. It is a covenant of salt forever before the LORD to you and to your offspring with you.”</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="20" style="v" />The LORD said to Aaron, “You shall have no inheritance in their land, neither shall you have any portion amongst them. I am your portion and your inheritance amongst the children of Israel.</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="21" style="v" />“To the children of Levi, behold, I have given all the tithe in Israel for an inheritance, in return for their service which they serve, even the service of the Tent of Meeting. <verse number="22" style="v" />Henceforth the children of Israel shall not come near the Tent of Meeting, lest they bear sin, and die. <verse number="23" style="v" />But the Levites shall do the service of the Tent of Meeting, and they shall bear their iniquity. It shall be a statute forever throughout your generations. Amongst the children of Israel, they shall have no inheritance. <verse number="24" style="v" />For the tithe of the children of Israel, which they offer as a wave offering to the LORD, I have given to the Levites for an inheritance. Therefore I have said to them, ‘Amongst the children of Israel they shall have no inheritance.’”</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="25" style="v" />The LORD spoke to Moses, saying, <verse number="26" style="v" />“Moreover you shall speak to the Levites, and tell them, ‘When you take of the children of Israel the tithe which I have given you from them for your inheritance, then you shall offer up a wave offering of it for the LORD, a tithe of the tithe. <verse number="27" style="v" />Your wave offering shall be credited to you, as though it were the grain of the threshing floor, and as the fullness of the wine press. <verse number="28" style="v" />Thus you also shall offer a wave offering to the LORD of all your tithes, which you receive of the children of Israel; and of it you shall give the LORD’s wave offering to Aaron the priest. <verse number="29" style="v" />Out of all your gifts, you shall offer every wave offering to the LORD, of all its best parts, even the holy part of it.’</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="30" style="v" />“Therefore you shall tell them, ‘When you heave its best from it, then it shall be credited to the Levites as the increase of the threshing floor, and as the increase of the wine press. <verse number="31" style="v" />You may eat it anywhere, you and your households, for it is your reward in return for your service in the Tent of Meeting. <verse number="32" style="v" />You shall bear no sin by reason of it, when you have heaved from it its best. You shall not profane the holy things of the children of Israel, that you not die.’”</para>
  <chapter number="19" style="c" />
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="1" style="v" />The LORD spoke to Moses and to Aaron, saying, <verse number="2" style="v" />“This is the statute of the law which the LORD has commanded. Tell the children of Israel to bring you a red heifer without spot, in which is no defect, and which was never yoked. <verse number="3" style="v" />You shall give her to Eleazar the priest, and he shall bring her outside of the camp, and one shall kill her before his face. <verse number="4" style="v" />Eleazar the priest shall take some of her blood with his finger, and sprinkle her blood towards the front of the Tent of Meeting seven times. <verse number="5" style="v" />One shall burn the heifer in his sight; her skin, and her meat, and her blood, with her dung, shall he burn. <verse number="6" style="v" />The priest shall take cedar wood, hyssop, and scarlet, and cast it into the middle of the burning of the heifer. <verse number="7" style="v" />Then the priest shall wash his clothes, and he shall bathe his flesh in water, and afterward he shall come into the camp, and the priest shall be unclean until the evening. <verse number="8" style="v" />He who burns her shall wash his clothes in water, and bathe his flesh in water, and shall be unclean until the evening.</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="9" style="v" />“A man who is clean shall gather up the ashes of the heifer, and lay them up outside of the camp in a clean place; and it shall be kept for the congregation of the children of Israel for use in water for cleansing impurity. It is a sin offering. <verse number="10" style="v" />He who gathers the ashes of the heifer shall wash his clothes, and be unclean until the evening. It shall be to the children of Israel, and to the stranger who lives as a foreigner amongst them, for a statute forever.</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="11" style="v" />“He who touches the dead body of any man shall be unclean seven days. <verse number="12" style="v" />He shall purify himself with water on the third day, and on the seventh day he shall be clean; but if he doesn’t purify himself the third day, then the seventh day he shall not be clean. <verse number="13" style="v" />Whoever touches a dead person, the body of a man who has died, and doesn’t purify himself, defiles the LORD’s tabernacle; and that soul shall be cut off from Israel; because the water for impurity was not sprinkled on him, he shall be unclean. His uncleanness is yet on him.</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="14" style="v" />“This is the law when a man dies in a tent: everyone who comes into the tent, and everyone who is in the tent, shall be unclean seven days. <verse number="15" style="v" />Every open vessel, which has no covering bound on it, is unclean.</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="16" style="v" />“Whoever in the open field touches one who is slain with a sword, or a dead body, or a bone of a man, or a grave, shall be unclean seven days.</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="17" style="v" />“For the unclean, they shall take of the ashes of the burning of the sin offering; and running water shall be poured on them in a vessel. <verse number="18" style="v" />A clean person shall take hyssop, dip it in the water, and sprinkle it on the tent, on all the vessels, on the persons who were there, and on him who touched the bone, or the slain, or the dead, or the grave. <verse number="19" style="v" />The clean person shall sprinkle on the unclean on the third day, and on the seventh day. On the seventh day, he shall purify him. He shall wash his clothes and bathe himself in water, and shall be clean at evening. <verse number="20" style="v" />But the man who shall be unclean, and shall not purify himself, that soul shall be cut off from amongst the assembly, because he has defiled the sanctuary of the LORD. The water for impurity has not been sprinkled on him. He is unclean. <verse number="21" style="v" />It shall be a perpetual statute to them. He who sprinkles the water for impurity shall wash his clothes, and he who touches the water for impurity shall be unclean until evening.</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="22" style="v" />“Whatever the unclean person touches shall be unclean; and the soul that touches it shall be unclean until evening.”</para>
  <chapter number="20" style="c" />
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="1" style="v" />The children of Israel, even the whole congregation, came into the wilderness of Zin in the first month. The people stayed in Kadesh. Miriam died there, and was buried there. <verse number="2" style="v" />There was no water for the congregation; and they assembled themselves together against Moses and against Aaron. <verse number="3" style="v" />The people quarrelled with Moses, and spoke, saying, “We wish that we had died when our brothers died before the LORD! <verse number="4" style="v" />Why have you brought the LORD’s assembly into this wilderness, that we should die there, we and our animals? <verse number="5" style="v" />Why have you made us to come up out of Egypt, to bring us in to this evil place? It is no place of seed, or of figs, or of vines, or of pomegranates; neither is there any water to drink.”</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="6" style="v" />Moses and Aaron went from the presence of the assembly to the door of the Tent of Meeting, and fell on their faces. The LORD’s glory appeared to them. <verse number="7" style="v" />The LORD spoke to Moses, saying, <verse number="8" style="v" />“Take the rod, and assemble the congregation, you, and Aaron your brother, and speak to the rock before their eyes, that it pour out its water. You shall bring water to them out of the rock; so you shall give the congregation and their livestock drink.”</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="9" style="v" />Moses took the rod from before the LORD, as he commanded him. <verse number="10" style="v" />Moses and Aaron gathered the assembly together before the rock, and he said to them, “Hear now, you rebels! Shall we bring water out of this rock for you?” <verse number="11" style="v" />Moses lifted up his hand, and struck the rock with his rod twice, and water came out abundantly. The congregation and their livestock drank.</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="12" style="v" />The LORD said to Moses and Aaron, “Because you didn’t believe in me, to sanctify me in the eyes of the children of Israel, therefore you shall not bring this assembly into the land which I have given them.”</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="13" style="v" />These are the waters of Meribah;<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">20:13 </char><char style="ft" closed="false">“Meribah” means “quarrelling”.</char></note> because the children of Israel strove with the LORD, and he was sanctified in them.</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="14" style="v" />Moses sent messengers from Kadesh to the king of Edom, saying:</para>
  <para style="p">“Your brother Israel says: You know all the travail that has happened to us; <verse number="15" style="v" />how our fathers went down into Egypt, and we lived in Egypt a long time. The Egyptians mistreated us and our fathers. <verse number="16" style="v" />When we cried to the LORD, he heard our voice, sent an angel, and brought us out of Egypt. Behold, we are in Kadesh, a city in the edge of your border.</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="17" style="v" />“Please let us pass through your land. We will not pass through field or through vineyard, neither will we drink from the water of the wells. We will go along the king’s highway. We will not turn away to the right hand nor to the left, until we have passed your border.”</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="18" style="v" />Edom said to him, “You shall not pass through me, lest I come out with the sword against you.”</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="19" style="v" />The children of Israel said to him, “We will go up by the highway; and if we drink your water, I and my livestock, then I will give its price. Only let me, without doing anything else, pass through on my feet.”</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="20" style="v" />He said, “You shall not pass through.” Edom came out against him with many people, and with a strong hand. <verse number="21" style="v" />Thus Edom refused to give Israel passage through his border, so Israel turned away from him.</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="22" style="v" />They travelled from Kadesh, and the children of Israel, even the whole congregation, came to Mount Hor. <verse number="23" style="v" />The LORD spoke to Moses and Aaron in Mount Hor, by the border of the land of Edom, saying, <verse number="24" style="v" />“Aaron shall be gathered to his people; for he shall not enter into the land which I have given to the children of Israel, because you rebelled against my word at the waters of Meribah. <verse number="25" style="v" />Take Aaron and Eleazar his son, and bring them up to Mount Hor; <verse number="26" style="v" />and strip Aaron of his garments, and put them on Eleazar his son. Aaron shall be gathered, and shall die there.”</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="27" style="v" />Moses did as the LORD commanded. They went up onto Mount Hor in the sight of all the congregation. <verse number="28" style="v" />Moses stripped Aaron of his garments, and put them on Eleazar his son. Aaron died there on the top of the mountain, and Moses and Eleazar came down from the mountain. <verse number="29" style="v" />When all the congregation saw that Aaron was dead, they wept for Aaron thirty days, even all the house of Israel.</para>
  <chapter number="21" style="c" />
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="1" style="v" />The Canaanite, the king of Arad, who lived in the South, heard that Israel came by the way of Atharim. He fought against Israel, and took some of them captive. <verse number="2" style="v" />Israel vowed a vow to the LORD, and said, “If you will indeed deliver this people into my hand, then I will utterly destroy their cities.” <verse number="3" style="v" />The LORD listened to the voice of Israel, and delivered up the Canaanites; and they utterly destroyed them and their cities. The name of the place was called Hormah.<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">21:3 </char><char style="ft" closed="false">“Hormah” means “destruction”.</char></note></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="4" style="v" />They travelled from Mount Hor by the way to the Red Sea, to go around the land of Edom. The soul of the people was very discouraged because of the journey. <verse number="5" style="v" />The people spoke against God and against Moses: “Why have you brought us up out of Egypt to die in the wilderness? For there is no bread, there is no water, and our soul loathes this disgusting food!”</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="6" style="v" />The LORD sent venomous snakes amongst the people, and they bit the people. Many people of Israel died. <verse number="7" style="v" />The people came to Moses, and said, “We have sinned, because we have spoken against the LORD and against you. Pray to the LORD, that he take away the serpents from us.” Moses prayed for the people.</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="8" style="v" />The LORD said to Moses, “Make a venomous snake, and set it on a pole. It shall happen that everyone who is bitten, when he sees it, shall live.” <verse number="9" style="v" />Moses made a serpent of bronze, and set it on the pole. If a serpent had bitten any man, when he looked at the serpent of bronze, he lived.</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="10" style="v" />The children of Israel travelled, and encamped in Oboth. <verse number="11" style="v" />They travelled from Oboth, and encamped at Iyeabarim, in the wilderness which is before Moab, towards the sunrise. <verse number="12" style="v" />From there they travelled, and encamped in the valley of Zered. <verse number="13" style="v" />From there they travelled, and encamped on the other side of the Arnon, which is in the wilderness that comes out of the border of the Amorites; for the Arnon is the border of Moab, between Moab and the Amorites. <verse number="14" style="v" />Therefore it is said in <char style="bk">The Book of the Wars of the LORD</char>, “Vaheb in Suphah, the valleys of the Arnon, <verse number="15" style="v" />the slope of the valleys that incline towards the dwelling of Ar, leans on the border of Moab.”</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="16" style="v" />From there they travelled to Beer; that is the well of which the LORD said to Moses, “Gather the people together, and I will give them water.”</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="17" style="v" />Then Israel sang this song:</para>
  <para style="q1">“Spring up, well! Sing to it,</para>
  <para style="q2">
    <verse number="18" style="v" />the well, which the princes dug,</para>
  <para style="q2">which the nobles of the people dug,</para>
  <para style="q2">with the sceptre, and with their poles.”</para>
  <para style="p">From the wilderness they travelled to Mattanah; <verse number="19" style="v" />and from Mattanah to Nahaliel; and from Nahaliel to Bamoth; <verse number="20" style="v" />and from Bamoth to the valley that is in the field of Moab, to the top of Pisgah, which looks down on the desert. <verse number="21" style="v" />Israel sent messengers to Sihon king of the Amorites, saying, <verse number="22" style="v" />“Let me pass through your land. We will not turn away into field or vineyard. We will not drink of the water of the wells. We will go by the king’s highway, until we have passed your border.”</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="23" style="v" />Sihon would not allow Israel to pass through his border, but Sihon gathered all his people together, and went out against Israel into the wilderness, and came to Jahaz. He fought against Israel. <verse number="24" style="v" />Israel struck him with the edge of the sword, and possessed his land from the Arnon to the Jabbok, even to the children of Ammon; for the border of the children of Ammon was fortified. <verse number="25" style="v" />Israel took all these cities. Israel lived in all the cities of the Amorites, in Heshbon, and in all its villages. <verse number="26" style="v" />For Heshbon was the city of Sihon the king of the Amorites, who had fought against the former king of Moab, and taken all his land out of his hand, even to the Arnon. <verse number="27" style="v" />Therefore those who speak in proverbs say,</para>
  <para style="q1">“Come to Heshbon.</para>
  <para style="q2">Let the city of Sihon be built and established;</para>
  <para style="q1">
    <verse number="28" style="v" />for a fire has gone out of Heshbon,</para>
  <para style="q2">a flame from the city of Sihon.</para>
  <para style="q1">It has devoured Ar of Moab,</para>
  <para style="q2">The lords of the high places of the Arnon.</para>
  <para style="q1">
    <verse number="29" style="v" />Woe to you, Moab!</para>
  <para style="q2">You are undone, people of Chemosh!</para>
  <para style="q1">He has given his sons as fugitives,</para>
  <para style="q2">and his daughters into captivity,</para>
  <para style="q2">to Sihon king of the Amorites.</para>
  <para style="q1">
    <verse number="30" style="v" />We have shot at them.</para>
  <para style="q2">Heshbon has perished even to Dibon.</para>
  <para style="q1">We have laid waste even to Nophah,</para>
  <para style="q2">Which reaches to Medeba.”</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="31" style="v" />Thus Israel lived in the land of the Amorites. <verse number="32" style="v" />Moses sent to spy out Jazer. They took its villages, and drove out the Amorites who were there. <verse number="33" style="v" />They turned and went up by the way of Bashan. Og the king of Bashan went out against them, he and all his people, to battle at Edrei.</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="34" style="v" />The LORD said to Moses, “Don’t fear him, for I have delivered him into your hand, with all his people, and his land. You shall do to him as you did to Sihon king of the Amorites, who lived at Heshbon.”</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="35" style="v" />So they struck him, with his sons and all his people, until there were no survivors; and they possessed his land.</para>
  <chapter number="22" style="c" />
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="1" style="v" />The children of Israel travelled, and encamped in the plains of Moab beyond the Jordan at Jericho. <verse number="2" style="v" />Balak the son of Zippor saw all that Israel had done to the Amorites. <verse number="3" style="v" />Moab was very afraid of the people, because they were many. Moab was distressed because of the children of Israel. <verse number="4" style="v" />Moab said to the elders of Midian, “Now this multitude will lick up all that is around us, as the ox licks up the grass of the field.”</para>
  <para style="p">Balak the son of Zippor was king of Moab at that time. <verse number="5" style="v" />He sent messengers to Balaam the son of Beor, to Pethor, which is by the River, to the land of the children of his people, to call him, saying, “Behold, there is a people who came out of Egypt. Behold, they cover the surface of the earth, and they are staying opposite me. <verse number="6" style="v" />Please come now therefore, and curse this people for me; for they are too mighty for me. Perhaps I shall prevail, that we may strike them, and that I may drive them out of the land; for I know that he whom you bless is blessed, and he whom you curse is cursed.”</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="7" style="v" />The elders of Moab and the elders of Midian departed with the rewards of divination in their hand. They came to Balaam, and spoke to him the words of Balak.</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="8" style="v" />He said to them, “Lodge here this night, and I will bring you word again, as the LORD shall speak to me.” The princes of Moab stayed with Balaam.</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="9" style="v" />God came to Balaam, and said, “Who are these men with you?”</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="10" style="v" />Balaam said to God, “Balak the son of Zippor, king of Moab, has said to me, <verse number="11" style="v" />‘Behold, the people that has come out of Egypt covers the surface of the earth. Now, come curse them for me. Perhaps I shall be able to fight against them, and shall drive them out.’”</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="12" style="v" />God said to Balaam, “You shall not go with them. You shall not curse the people, for they are blessed.”</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="13" style="v" />Balaam rose up in the morning, and said to the princes of Balak, “Go to your land; for the LORD refuses to permit me to go with you.”</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="14" style="v" />The princes of Moab rose up, and they went to Balak, and said, “Balaam refuses to come with us.”</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="15" style="v" />Balak again sent princes, more, and more honourable than they. <verse number="16" style="v" />They came to Balaam, and said to him, “Balak the son of Zippor says, ‘Please let nothing hinder you from coming to me, <verse number="17" style="v" />for I will promote you to very great honour, and whatever you say to me I will do. Please come therefore, and curse this people for me.’”</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="18" style="v" />Balaam answered the servants of Balak, “If Balak would give me his house full of silver and gold, I can’t go beyond the word of the LORD my God, to do less or more. <verse number="19" style="v" />Now therefore please stay here tonight as well, that I may know what else the LORD will speak to me.”</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="20" style="v" />God came to Balaam at night, and said to him, “If the men have come to call you, rise up, go with them; but only the word which I speak to you, that you shall do.”</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="21" style="v" />Balaam rose up in the morning, and saddled his donkey, and went with the princes of Moab. <verse number="22" style="v" />God’s anger burnt because he went; and the LORD’s angel placed himself in the way as an adversary against him. Now he was riding on his donkey, and his two servants were with him. <verse number="23" style="v" />The donkey saw the LORD’s angel standing in the way, with his sword drawn in his hand; and the donkey turned out of the path, and went into the field. Balaam struck the donkey, to turn her into the path. <verse number="24" style="v" />Then the LORD’s angel stood in a narrow path between the vineyards, a wall being on this side, and a wall on that side. <verse number="25" style="v" />The donkey saw the LORD’s angel, and she thrust herself to the wall, and crushed Balaam’s foot against the wall. He struck her again.</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="26" style="v" />The LORD’s angel went further, and stood in a narrow place, where there was no way to turn either to the right hand or to the left. <verse number="27" style="v" />The donkey saw the LORD’s angel, and she lay down under Balaam. Balaam’s anger burnt, and he struck the donkey with his staff.</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="28" style="v" />The LORD opened the mouth of the donkey, and she said to Balaam, “What have I done to you, that you have struck me these three times?”</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="29" style="v" />Balaam said to the donkey, “Because you have mocked me, I wish there were a sword in my hand, for now I would have killed you.”</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="30" style="v" />The donkey said to Balaam, “Am I not your donkey, on which you have ridden all your life long until today? Was I ever in the habit of doing so to you?”</para>
  <para style="p">He said, “No.”</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="31" style="v" />Then the LORD opened the eyes of Balaam, and he saw the LORD’s angel standing in the way, with his sword drawn in his hand; and he bowed his head, and fell on his face. <verse number="32" style="v" />The LORD’s angel said to him, “Why have you struck your donkey these three times? Behold, I have come out as an adversary, because your way is perverse before me. <verse number="33" style="v" />The donkey saw me, and turned away before me these three times. Unless she had turned away from me, surely now I would have killed you, and saved her alive.”</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="34" style="v" />Balaam said to the LORD’s angel, “I have sinned; for I didn’t know that you stood in the way against me. Now therefore, if it displeases you, I will go back again.”</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="35" style="v" />The LORD’s angel said to Balaam, “Go with the men; but you shall only speak the word that I shall speak to you.”</para>
  <para style="p">So Balaam went with the princes of Balak. <verse number="36" style="v" />When Balak heard that Balaam had come, he went out to meet him to the City of Moab, which is on the border of the Arnon, which is in the utmost part of the border. <verse number="37" style="v" />Balak said to Balaam, “Didn’t I earnestly send for you to summon you? Why didn’t you come to me? Am I not able indeed to promote you to honour?”</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="38" style="v" />Balaam said to Balak, “Behold, I have come to you. Have I now any power at all to speak anything? I will speak the word that God puts in my mouth.”</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="39" style="v" />Balaam went with Balak, and they came to Kiriath Huzoth. <verse number="40" style="v" />Balak sacrificed cattle and sheep, and sent to Balaam, and to the princes who were with him. <verse number="41" style="v" />In the morning, Balak took Balaam, and brought him up into the high places of Baal; and he saw from there part of the people.</para>
  <chapter number="23" style="c" />
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="1" style="v" />Balaam said to Balak, “Build here seven altars for me, and prepare here seven bulls and seven rams for me.”</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="2" style="v" />Balak did as Balaam had spoken; and Balak and Balaam offered on every altar a bull and a ram. <verse number="3" style="v" />Balaam said to Balak, “Stand by your burnt offering, and I will go. Perhaps the LORD will come to meet me. Whatever he shows me I will tell you.”</para>
  <para style="p">He went to a bare height. <verse number="4" style="v" />God met Balaam, and he said to him, “I have prepared the seven altars, and I have offered up a bull and a ram on every altar.”</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="5" style="v" />The LORD put a word in Balaam’s mouth, and said, “Return to Balak, and thus you shall speak.”</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="6" style="v" />He returned to him, and behold, he was standing by his burnt offering, he, and all the princes of Moab. <verse number="7" style="v" />He took up his parable, and said,</para>
  <para style="q1">“From Aram has Balak brought me,</para>
  <para style="q2">the king of Moab from the mountains of the East.</para>
  <para style="q1">Come, curse Jacob for me.</para>
  <para style="q2">Come, defy Israel.</para>
  <para style="q1">
    <verse number="8" style="v" />How shall I curse whom God has not cursed?</para>
  <para style="q2">How shall I defy whom the LORD has not defied?</para>
  <para style="q1">
    <verse number="9" style="v" />For from the top of the rocks I see him.</para>
  <para style="q2">From the hills I see him.</para>
  <para style="q1">Behold, it is a people that dwells alone,</para>
  <para style="q2">and shall not be listed amongst the nations.</para>
  <para style="q1">
    <verse number="10" style="v" />Who can count the dust of Jacob,</para>
  <para style="q2">or count the fourth part of Israel?</para>
  <para style="q1">Let me die the death of the righteous!</para>
  <para style="q2">Let my last end be like his!”</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="11" style="v" />Balak said to Balaam, “What have you done to me? I took you to curse my enemies, and behold, you have blessed them altogether.”</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="12" style="v" />He answered and said, “Must I not take heed to speak that which the LORD puts in my mouth?”</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="13" style="v" />Balak said to him, “Please come with me to another place, where you may see them. You shall see just part of them, and shall not see them all. Curse them from there for me.”</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="14" style="v" />He took him into the field of Zophim, to the top of Pisgah, and built seven altars, and offered up a bull and a ram on every altar. <verse number="15" style="v" />He said to Balak, “Stand here by your burnt offering, while I meet God over there.”</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="16" style="v" />The LORD met Balaam, and put a word in his mouth, and said, “Return to Balak, and say this.”</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="17" style="v" />He came to him, and behold, he was standing by his burnt offering, and the princes of Moab with him. Balak said to him, “What has the LORD spoken?”</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="18" style="v" />He took up his parable, and said,</para>
  <para style="q1">“Rise up, Balak, and hear!</para>
  <para style="q2">Listen to me, you son of Zippor.</para>
  <para style="q1">
    <verse number="19" style="v" />God is not a man, that he should lie,</para>
  <para style="q2">nor a son of man, that he should repent.</para>
  <para style="q1">Has he said, and he won’t do it?</para>
  <para style="q2">Or has he spoken, and he won’t make it good?</para>
  <para style="q1">
    <verse number="20" style="v" />Behold, I have received a command to bless.</para>
  <para style="q2">He has blessed, and I can’t reverse it.</para>
  <para style="q1">
    <verse number="21" style="v" />He has not seen iniquity in Jacob.</para>
  <para style="q2">Neither has he seen perverseness in Israel.</para>
  <para style="q1">The LORD his God is with him.</para>
  <para style="q2">The shout of a king is amongst them.</para>
  <para style="q1">
    <verse number="22" style="v" />God brings them out of Egypt.</para>
  <para style="q2">He has as it were the strength of the wild ox.</para>
  <para style="q1">
    <verse number="23" style="v" />Surely there is no enchantment with Jacob;</para>
  <para style="q2">Neither is there any divination with Israel.</para>
  <para style="q1">Now it shall be said of Jacob and of Israel,</para>
  <para style="q2">‘What has God done!’</para>
  <para style="q1">
    <verse number="24" style="v" />Behold, a people rises up as a lioness.</para>
  <para style="q2">As a lion he lifts himself up.</para>
  <para style="q1">He shall not lie down until he eats of the prey,</para>
  <para style="q2">and drinks the blood of the slain.”</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="25" style="v" />Balak said to Balaam, “Neither curse them at all, nor bless them at all.”</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="26" style="v" />But Balaam answered Balak, “Didn’t I tell you, saying, ‘All that the LORD speaks, that I must do?’”</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="27" style="v" />Balak said to Balaam, “Come now, I will take you to another place; perhaps it will please God that you may curse them for me from there.”</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="28" style="v" />Balak took Balaam to the top of Peor, that looks down on the desert. <verse number="29" style="v" />Balaam said to Balak, “Build seven altars for me here, and prepare seven bulls and seven rams for me here.”</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="30" style="v" />Balak did as Balaam had said, and offered up a bull and a ram on every altar.</para>
  <chapter number="24" style="c" />
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="1" style="v" />When Balaam saw that it pleased the LORD to bless Israel, he didn’t go, as at the other times, to use divination, but he set his face towards the wilderness. <verse number="2" style="v" />Balaam lifted up his eyes, and he saw Israel dwelling according to their tribes; and the Spirit of God came on him. <verse number="3" style="v" />He took up his parable, and said,</para>
  <para style="q1">“Balaam the son of Beor says,</para>
  <para style="q2">the man whose eyes are open says;</para>
  <para style="q1">
    <verse number="4" style="v" />he says, who hears the words of God,</para>
  <para style="q2">who sees the vision of the Almighty,</para>
  <para style="q2">falling down, and having his eyes open:</para>
  <para style="q1">
    <verse number="5" style="v" />How goodly are your tents, Jacob,</para>
  <para style="q2">and your dwellings, Israel!</para>
  <para style="q1">
    <verse number="6" style="v" />As valleys they are spread out,</para>
  <para style="q2">as gardens by the riverside,</para>
  <para style="q2">as aloes which the LORD has planted,</para>
  <para style="q2">as cedar trees beside the waters.</para>
  <para style="q1">
    <verse number="7" style="v" />Water shall flow from his buckets.</para>
  <para style="q2">His seed shall be in many waters.</para>
  <para style="q1">His king shall be higher than Agag.</para>
  <para style="q2">His kingdom shall be exalted.</para>
  <para style="q1">
    <verse number="8" style="v" />God brings him out of Egypt.</para>
  <para style="q2">He has as it were the strength of the wild ox.</para>
  <para style="q1">He shall consume the nations his adversaries,</para>
  <para style="q2">shall break their bones in pieces,</para>
  <para style="q2">and pierce them with his arrows.</para>
  <para style="q1">
    <verse number="9" style="v" />He couched, he lay down as a lion,</para>
  <para style="q2">as a lioness;</para>
  <para style="q2">who shall rouse him up?</para>
  <para style="q1">Everyone who blesses you is blessed.</para>
  <para style="q2">Everyone who curses you is cursed.”</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="10" style="v" />Balak’s anger burnt against Balaam, and he struck his hands together. Balak said to Balaam, “I called you to curse my enemies, and, behold, you have altogether blessed them these three times. <verse number="11" style="v" />Therefore, flee to your place, now! I thought to promote you to great honour; but, behold, the LORD has kept you back from honour.”</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="12" style="v" />Balaam said to Balak, “Didn’t I also tell your messengers whom you sent to me, saying, <verse number="13" style="v" />‘If Balak would give me his house full of silver and gold, I can’t go beyond the LORD’s word, to do either good or bad from my own mind. I will say what the LORD says’? <verse number="14" style="v" />Now, behold, I go to my people. Come, I will inform you what this people shall do to your people in the latter days.”</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="15" style="v" />He took up his parable, and said,</para>
  <para style="q1">“Balaam the son of Beor says,</para>
  <para style="q2">the man whose eyes are open says;</para>
  <para style="q2">
    <verse number="16" style="v" />he says, who hears the words of God,</para>
  <para style="q2">knows the knowledge of the Most High,</para>
  <para style="q2">and who sees the vision of the Almighty,</para>
  <para style="q2">falling down, and having his eyes open:</para>
  <para style="q1">
    <verse number="17" style="v" />I see him, but not now.</para>
  <para style="q2">I see him, but not near.</para>
  <para style="q1">A star will come out of Jacob.</para>
  <para style="q2">A sceptre will rise out of Israel,</para>
  <para style="q1">and shall strike through the corners of Moab,</para>
  <para style="q2">and crush all the sons of Sheth.</para>
  <para style="q1">
    <verse number="18" style="v" />Edom shall be a possession.</para>
  <para style="q2">Seir, his enemy, also shall be a possession,</para>
  <para style="q2">while Israel does valiantly.</para>
  <para style="q1">
    <verse number="19" style="v" />Out of Jacob shall one have dominion,</para>
  <para style="q2">and shall destroy the remnant from the city.”</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="20" style="v" />He looked at Amalek, and took up his parable, and said,</para>
  <para style="q1">“Amalek was the first of the nations,</para>
  <para style="q2">But his latter end shall come to destruction.”</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="21" style="v" />He looked at the Kenite, and took up his parable, and said,</para>
  <para style="q1">“Your dwelling place is strong.</para>
  <para style="q2">Your nest is set in the rock.</para>
  <para style="q1">
    <verse number="22" style="v" />Nevertheless Kain shall be wasted,</para>
  <para style="q2">until Asshur carries you away captive.”</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="23" style="v" />He took up his parable, and said,</para>
  <para style="q1">“Alas, who shall live when God does this?</para>
  <para style="q2">
    <verse number="24" style="v" />But ships shall come from the coast of Kittim.</para>
  <para style="q1">They shall afflict Asshur, and shall afflict Eber.</para>
  <para style="q2">He also shall come to destruction.”</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="25" style="v" />Balaam rose up, and went and returned to his place; and Balak also went his way.</para>
  <chapter number="25" style="c" />
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="1" style="v" />Israel stayed in Shittim; and the people began to play the prostitute with the daughters of Moab; <verse number="2" style="v" />for they called the people to the sacrifices of their gods. The people ate and bowed down to their gods. <verse number="3" style="v" />Israel joined himself to Baal Peor, and the LORD’s anger burnt against Israel. <verse number="4" style="v" />The LORD said to Moses, “Take all the chiefs of the people, and hang them up to the LORD before the sun, that the fierce anger of the LORD may turn away from Israel.”</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="5" style="v" />Moses said to the judges of Israel, “Everyone kill his men who have joined themselves to Baal Peor.”</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="6" style="v" />Behold, one of the children of Israel came and brought to his brothers a Midianite woman in the sight of Moses, and in the sight of all the congregation of the children of Israel, while they were weeping at the door of the Tent of Meeting. <verse number="7" style="v" />When Phinehas, the son of Eleazar, the son of Aaron the priest, saw it, he rose up from the middle of the congregation, and took a spear in his hand. <verse number="8" style="v" />He went after the man of Israel into the pavilion, and thrust both of them through, the man of Israel, and the woman through her body. So the plague was stopped amongst the children of Israel. <verse number="9" style="v" />Those who died by the plague were twenty-four thousand.</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="10" style="v" />The LORD spoke to Moses, saying, <verse number="11" style="v" />“Phinehas, the son of Eleazar, the son of Aaron the priest, has turned my wrath away from the children of Israel, in that he was jealous with my jealousy amongst them, so that I didn’t consume the children of Israel in my jealousy. <verse number="12" style="v" />Therefore say, ‘Behold, I give to him my covenant of peace. <verse number="13" style="v" />It shall be to him, and to his offspring after him, the covenant of an everlasting priesthood, because he was jealous for his God, and made atonement for the children of Israel.’”</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="14" style="v" />Now the name of the man of Israel that was slain, who was slain with the Midianite woman, was Zimri, the son of Salu, a prince of a fathers’ house amongst the Simeonites. <verse number="15" style="v" />The name of the Midianite woman who was slain was Cozbi, the daughter of Zur. He was head of the people of a fathers’ house in Midian.</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="16" style="v" />The LORD spoke to Moses, saying, <verse number="17" style="v" />“Harass the Midianites, and strike them; <verse number="18" style="v" />for they harassed you with their wiles, wherein they have deceived you in the matter of Peor, and in the incident regarding Cozbi, the daughter of the prince of Midian, their sister, who was slain on the day of the plague in the matter of Peor.”</para>
  <chapter number="26" style="c" />
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="1" style="v" />After the plague, the LORD spoke to Moses and to Eleazar the son of Aaron the priest, saying, <verse number="2" style="v" />“Take a census of all the congregation of the children of Israel, from twenty years old and upward, by their fathers’ houses, all who are able to go out to war in Israel.” <verse number="3" style="v" />Moses and Eleazar the priest spoke with them in the plains of Moab by the Jordan at Jericho, saying, <verse number="4" style="v" />“Take a census, from twenty years old and upward, as the LORD commanded Moses and the children of Israel.”</para>
  <para style="p">These are those who came out of the land of Egypt. <verse number="5" style="v" />Reuben, the firstborn of Israel; the sons of Reuben: of Hanoch, the family of the Hanochites; of Pallu, the family of the Palluites; <verse number="6" style="v" />of Hezron, the family of the Hezronites; of Carmi, the family of the Carmites. <verse number="7" style="v" />These are the families of the Reubenites; and those who were counted of them were forty-three thousand and seven hundred and thirty. <verse number="8" style="v" />The son of Pallu: Eliab. <verse number="9" style="v" />The sons of Eliab: Nemuel, Dathan, and Abiram. These are that Dathan and Abiram who were called by the congregation, who rebelled against Moses and against Aaron in the company of Korah when they rebelled against the LORD; <verse number="10" style="v" />and the earth opened its mouth, and swallowed them up together with Korah when that company died; at the time the fire devoured two hundred and fifty men, and they became a sign. <verse number="11" style="v" />Notwithstanding, the sons of Korah didn’t die. <verse number="12" style="v" />The sons of Simeon after their families: of Nemuel, the family of the Nemuelites; of Jamin, the family of the Jaminites; of Jachin, the family of the Jachinites; <verse number="13" style="v" />of Zerah, the family of the Zerahites; of Shaul, the family of the Shaulites. <verse number="14" style="v" />These are the families of the Simeonites, twenty-two thousand and two hundred. <verse number="15" style="v" />The sons of Gad after their families: of Zephon, the family of the Zephonites; of Haggi, the family of the Haggites; of Shuni, the family of the Shunites; <verse number="16" style="v" />of Ozni, the family of the Oznites; of Eri, the family of the Erites; <verse number="17" style="v" />of Arod, the family of the Arodites; of Areli, the family of the Arelites. <verse number="18" style="v" />These are the families of the sons of Gad according to those who were counted of them, forty thousand and five hundred. <verse number="19" style="v" />The sons of Judah: Er and Onan. Er and Onan died in the land of Canaan. <verse number="20" style="v" />The sons of Judah after their families were: of Shelah, the family of the Shelanites; of Perez, the family of the Perezites; of Zerah, the family of the Zerahites. <verse number="21" style="v" />The sons of Perez were: of Hezron, the family of the Hezronites; of Hamul, the family of the Hamulites. <verse number="22" style="v" />These are the families of Judah according to those who were counted of them, seventy-six thousand and five hundred. <verse number="23" style="v" />The sons of Issachar after their families: of Tola, the family of the Tolaites; of Puvah, the family of the Punites; <verse number="24" style="v" />of Jashub, the family of the Jashubites; of Shimron, the family of the Shimronites. <verse number="25" style="v" />These are the families of Issachar according to those who were counted of them, sixty-four thousand and three hundred. <verse number="26" style="v" />The sons of Zebulun after their families: of Sered, the family of the Seredites; of Elon, the family of the Elonites; of Jahleel, the family of the Jahleelites. <verse number="27" style="v" />These are the families of the Zebulunites according to those who were counted of them, sixty thousand and five hundred. <verse number="28" style="v" />The sons of Joseph after their families: Manasseh and Ephraim. <verse number="29" style="v" />The sons of Manasseh: of Machir, the family of the Machirites; and Machir became the father of Gilead; of Gilead, the family of the Gileadites. <verse number="30" style="v" />These are the sons of Gilead: of Iezer, the family of the Iezerites; of Helek, the family of the Helekites; <verse number="31" style="v" />and Asriel, the family of the Asrielites; and Shechem, the family of the Shechemites; <verse number="32" style="v" />and Shemida, the family of the Shemidaites; and Hepher, the family of the Hepherites. <verse number="33" style="v" />Zelophehad the son of Hepher had no sons, but daughters: and the names of the daughters of Zelophehad were Mahlah, Noah, Hoglah, Milcah, and Tirzah. <verse number="34" style="v" />These are the families of Manasseh. Those who were counted of them were fifty-two thousand and seven hundred. <verse number="35" style="v" />These are the sons of Ephraim after their families: of Shuthelah, the family of the Shuthelahites; of Becher, the family of the Becherites; of Tahan, the family of the Tahanites. <verse number="36" style="v" />These are the sons of Shuthelah: of Eran, the family of the Eranites. <verse number="37" style="v" />These are the families of the sons of Ephraim according to those who were counted of them, thirty-two thousand and five hundred. These are the sons of Joseph after their families. <verse number="38" style="v" />The sons of Benjamin after their families: of Bela, the family of the Belaites; of Ashbel, the family of the Ashbelites; of Ahiram, the family of the Ahiramites; <verse number="39" style="v" />of Shephupham, the family of the Shuphamites; of Hupham, the family of the Huphamites. <verse number="40" style="v" />The sons of Bela were Ard and Naaman: the family of the Ardites; and of Naaman, the family of the Naamites. <verse number="41" style="v" />These are the sons of Benjamin after their families; and those who were counted of them were forty-five thousand and six hundred. <verse number="42" style="v" />These are the sons of Dan after their families: of Shuham, the family of the Shuhamites. These are the families of Dan after their families. <verse number="43" style="v" />All the families of the Shuhamites, according to those who were counted of them, were sixty-four thousand and four hundred. <verse number="44" style="v" />The sons of Asher after their families: of Imnah, the family of the Imnites; of Ishvi, the family of the Ishvites; of Beriah, the family of the Berites. <verse number="45" style="v" />Of the sons of Beriah: of Heber, the family of the Heberites; of Malchiel, the family of the Malchielites. <verse number="46" style="v" />The name of the daughter of Asher was Serah. <verse number="47" style="v" />These are the families of the sons of Asher according to those who were counted of them, fifty-three thousand and four hundred. <verse number="48" style="v" />The sons of Naphtali after their families: of Jahzeel, the family of the Jahzeelites; of Guni, the family of the Gunites; <verse number="49" style="v" />of Jezer, the family of the Jezerites; of Shillem, the family of the Shillemites. <verse number="50" style="v" />These are the families of Naphtali according to their families; and those who were counted of them were forty-five thousand and four hundred. <verse number="51" style="v" />These are those who were counted of the children of Israel, six hundred and one thousand and seven hundred and thirty.</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="52" style="v" />The LORD spoke to Moses, saying, <verse number="53" style="v" />“To these the land shall be divided for an inheritance according to the number of names. <verse number="54" style="v" />To the more you shall give the more inheritance, and to the fewer you shall give the less inheritance. To everyone according to those who were counted of him shall his inheritance be given. <verse number="55" style="v" />Notwithstanding, the land shall be divided by lot. According to the names of the tribes of their fathers they shall inherit. <verse number="56" style="v" />According to the lot shall their inheritance be divided between the more and the fewer.”</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="57" style="v" />These are those who were counted of the Levites after their families: of Gershon, the family of the Gershonites; of Kohath, the family of the Kohathites; of Merari, the family of the Merarites. <verse number="58" style="v" />These are the families of Levi: the family of the Libnites, the family of the Hebronites, the family of the Mahlites, the family of the Mushites, and the family of the Korahites. Kohath became the father of Amram. <verse number="59" style="v" />The name of Amram’s wife was Jochebed, the daughter of Levi, who was born to Levi in Egypt. She bore to Amram Aaron and Moses, and Miriam their sister. <verse number="60" style="v" />To Aaron were born Nadab and Abihu, Eleazar and Ithamar. <verse number="61" style="v" />Nadab and Abihu died when they offered strange fire before the LORD. <verse number="62" style="v" />Those who were counted of them were twenty-three thousand, every male from a month old and upward; for they were not counted amongst the children of Israel, because there was no inheritance given them amongst the children of Israel. <verse number="63" style="v" />These are those who were counted by Moses and Eleazar the priest, who counted the children of Israel in the plains of Moab by the Jordan at Jericho. <verse number="64" style="v" />But amongst these there was not a man of them who were counted by Moses and Aaron the priest, who counted the children of Israel in the wilderness of Sinai. <verse number="65" style="v" />For the LORD had said of them, “They shall surely die in the wilderness.” There was not a man left of them, except Caleb the son of Jephunneh, and Joshua the son of Nun.</para>
  <chapter number="27" style="c" />
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="1" style="v" />Then the daughters of Zelophehad, the son of Hepher, the son of Gilead, the son of Machir, the son of Manasseh, of the families of Manasseh the son of Joseph came near. These are the names of his daughters: Mahlah, Noah, Hoglah, Milcah, and Tirzah. <verse number="2" style="v" />They stood before Moses, before Eleazar the priest, and before the princes and all the congregation, at the door of the Tent of Meeting, saying, <verse number="3" style="v" />“Our father died in the wilderness. He was not amongst the company of those who gathered themselves together against the LORD in the company of Korah, but he died in his own sin. He had no sons. <verse number="4" style="v" />Why should the name of our father be taken away from amongst his family, because he had no son? Give to us a possession amongst the brothers of our father.”</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="5" style="v" />Moses brought their cause before the LORD. <verse number="6" style="v" />The LORD spoke to Moses, saying, <verse number="7" style="v" />“The daughters of Zelophehad speak right. You shall surely give them a possession of an inheritance amongst their father’s brothers. You shall cause the inheritance of their father to pass to them. <verse number="8" style="v" />You shall speak to the children of Israel, saying, ‘If a man dies, and has no son, then you shall cause his inheritance to pass to his daughter. <verse number="9" style="v" />If he has no daughter, then you shall give his inheritance to his brothers. <verse number="10" style="v" />If he has no brothers, then you shall give his inheritance to his father’s brothers. <verse number="11" style="v" />If his father has no brothers, then you shall give his inheritance to his kinsman who is next to him of his family, and he shall possess it. This shall be a statute and ordinance for the children of Israel, as the LORD commanded Moses.’”</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="12" style="v" />The LORD said to Moses, “Go up into this mountain of Abarim, and see the land which I have given to the children of Israel. <verse number="13" style="v" />When you have seen it, you also shall be gathered to your people, as Aaron your brother was gathered; <verse number="14" style="v" />because in the strife of the congregation, you rebelled against my word in the wilderness of Zin, to honour me as holy at the waters before their eyes.” (These are the waters of Meribah of Kadesh in the wilderness of Zin.)</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="15" style="v" />Moses spoke to the LORD, saying, <verse number="16" style="v" />“Let the LORD, the God of the spirits of all flesh, appoint a man over the congregation, <verse number="17" style="v" />who may go out before them, and who may come in before them, and who may lead them out, and who may bring them in, that the congregation of the LORD may not be as sheep which have no shepherd.”</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="18" style="v" />The LORD said to Moses, “Take Joshua the son of Nun, a man in whom is the Spirit, and lay your hand on him. <verse number="19" style="v" />Set him before Eleazar the priest, and before all the congregation; and commission him in their sight. <verse number="20" style="v" />You shall give authority to him, that all the congregation of the children of Israel may obey. <verse number="21" style="v" />He shall stand before Eleazar the priest, who shall enquire for him by the judgement of the Urim before the LORD. At his word they shall go out, and at his word they shall come in, both he and all the children of Israel with him, even all the congregation.”</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="22" style="v" />Moses did as the LORD commanded him. He took Joshua, and set him before Eleazar the priest and before all the congregation. <verse number="23" style="v" />He laid his hands on him and commissioned him, as the LORD spoke by Moses.</para>
  <chapter number="28" style="c" />
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="1" style="v" />The LORD spoke to Moses, saying, <verse number="2" style="v" />“Command the children of Israel, and tell them, ‘See that you present my offering, my food for my offerings made by fire, as a pleasant aroma to me, in their due season.’ <verse number="3" style="v" />You shall tell them, ‘This is the offering made by fire which you shall offer to the LORD: male lambs a year old without defect, two day by day, for a continual burnt offering. <verse number="4" style="v" />You shall offer the one lamb in the morning, and you shall offer the other lamb at evening, <verse number="5" style="v" />with one tenth of an ephah<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">28:5 </char><char style="ft" closed="false">1 ephah is about 22 litres or about 2/3 of a bushel</char></note> of fine flour for a meal offering, mixed with the fourth part of a hin<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">28:5 </char><char style="ft" closed="false">A hin is about 6.5 litres or 1.7 gallons.</char></note> of beaten oil. <verse number="6" style="v" />It is a continual burnt offering which was ordained in Mount Sinai for a pleasant aroma, an offering made by fire to the LORD. <verse number="7" style="v" />Its drink offering shall be the fourth part of a hin<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">28:7 </char><char style="ft" closed="false">One hin is about 6.5 litres, so 1/4 hin is about 1.6 litres or 1.7 quarts.</char></note> for each lamb. You shall pour out a drink offering of strong drink to the LORD in the holy place. <verse number="8" style="v" />The other lamb you shall offer at evening. As the meal offering of the morning, and as its drink offering, you shall offer it, an offering made by fire, for a pleasant aroma to the LORD.</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="9" style="v" />“‘On the Sabbath day, you shall offer two male lambs a year old without defect, and two tenths of an ephah<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">28:9 </char><char style="ft" closed="false">1 ephah is about 22 litres or about 2/3 of a bushel</char></note> of fine flour for a meal offering mixed with oil, and its drink offering: <verse number="10" style="v" />this is the burnt offering of every Sabbath, in addition to the continual burnt offering and its drink offering.</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="11" style="v" />“‘In the beginnings of your months, you shall offer a burnt offering to the LORD: two young bulls, one ram, seven male lambs a year old without defect, <verse number="12" style="v" />and three tenths of an ephah<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">28:12 </char><char style="ft" closed="false">1 ephah is about 22 litres or about 2/3 of a bushel</char></note> of fine flour for a meal offering mixed with oil, for each bull; and two tenth parts of fine flour for a meal offering mixed with oil, for the one ram; <verse number="13" style="v" />and one tenth part of fine flour mixed with oil for a meal offering to every lamb, as a burnt offering of a pleasant aroma, an offering made by fire to the LORD. <verse number="14" style="v" />Their drink offerings shall be half a hin of wine for a bull, the third part of a hin for the ram, and the fourth part of a hin for a lamb. This is the burnt offering of every month throughout the months of the year. <verse number="15" style="v" />Also, one male goat for a sin offering to the LORD shall be offered in addition to the continual burnt offering and its drink offering.</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="16" style="v" />“‘In the first month, on the fourteenth day of the month, is the LORD’s Passover. <verse number="17" style="v" />On the fifteenth day of this month shall be a feast. Unleavened bread shall be eaten for seven days. <verse number="18" style="v" />In the first day shall be a holy convocation. You shall do no regular work, <verse number="19" style="v" />but you shall offer an offering made by fire, a burnt offering to the LORD: two young bulls, one ram, and seven male lambs a year old. They shall be without defect, <verse number="20" style="v" />with their meal offering, fine flour mixed with oil. You shall offer three tenths for a bull, and two tenths for the ram. <verse number="21" style="v" />You shall offer one tenth for every lamb of the seven lambs; <verse number="22" style="v" />and one male goat for a sin offering, to make atonement for you. <verse number="23" style="v" />You shall offer these in addition to the burnt offering of the morning, which is for a continual burnt offering. <verse number="24" style="v" />In this way you shall offer daily, for seven days, the food of the offering made by fire, of a pleasant aroma to the LORD. It shall be offered in addition to the continual burnt offering and its drink offering. <verse number="25" style="v" />On the seventh day you shall have a holy convocation. You shall do no regular work.</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="26" style="v" />“‘Also in the day of the first fruits, when you offer a new meal offering to the LORD in your feast of weeks, you shall have a holy convocation. You shall do no regular work; <verse number="27" style="v" />but you shall offer a burnt offering for a pleasant aroma to the LORD: two young bulls, one ram, seven male lambs a year old; <verse number="28" style="v" />and their meal offering, fine flour mixed with oil, three tenths for each bull, two tenths for the one ram, <verse number="29" style="v" />one tenth for every lamb of the seven lambs; <verse number="30" style="v" />and one male goat, to make atonement for you. <verse number="31" style="v" />Besides the continual burnt offering and its meal offering, you shall offer them and their drink offerings. See that they are without defect.</para>
  <chapter number="29" style="c" />
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="1" style="v" />“‘In the seventh month, on the first day of the month, you shall have a holy convocation; you shall do no regular work. It is a day of blowing of trumpets to you. <verse number="2" style="v" />You shall offer a burnt offering for a pleasant aroma to the LORD: one young bull, one ram, seven male lambs a year old without defect; <verse number="3" style="v" />and their meal offering, fine flour mixed with oil: three tenths for the bull, two tenths for the ram, <verse number="4" style="v" />and one tenth for every lamb of the seven lambs; <verse number="5" style="v" />and one male goat for a sin offering, to make atonement for you; <verse number="6" style="v" />in addition to the burnt offering of the new moon with its meal offering, and the continual burnt offering with its meal offering, and their drink offerings, according to their ordinance, for a pleasant aroma, an offering made by fire to the LORD.</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="7" style="v" />“‘On the tenth day of this seventh month you shall have a holy convocation. You shall afflict your souls. You shall do no kind of work; <verse number="8" style="v" />but you shall offer a burnt offering to the LORD for a pleasant aroma: one young bull, one ram, seven male lambs a year old, all without defect; <verse number="9" style="v" />and their meal offering, fine flour mixed with oil: three tenths for the bull, two tenths for the one ram, <verse number="10" style="v" />one tenth for every lamb of the seven lambs; <verse number="11" style="v" />one male goat for a sin offering, in addition to the sin offering of atonement, and the continual burnt offering, and its meal offering, and their drink offerings.</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="12" style="v" />“‘On the fifteenth day of the seventh month you shall have a holy convocation. You shall do no regular work. You shall keep a feast to the LORD seven days. <verse number="13" style="v" />You shall offer a burnt offering, an offering made by fire, of a pleasant aroma to the LORD: thirteen young bulls, two rams, fourteen male lambs a year old, all without defect; <verse number="14" style="v" />and their meal offering, fine flour mixed with oil: three tenths for every bull of the thirteen bulls, two tenths for each ram of the two rams, <verse number="15" style="v" />and one tenth for every lamb of the fourteen lambs; <verse number="16" style="v" />and one male goat for a sin offering, in addition to the continual burnt offering, its meal offering, and its drink offering.</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="17" style="v" />“‘On the second day you shall offer twelve young bulls, two rams, and fourteen male lambs a year old without defect; <verse number="18" style="v" />and their meal offering and their drink offerings for the bulls, for the rams, and for the lambs, according to their number, after the ordinance; <verse number="19" style="v" />and one male goat for a sin offering, in addition to the continual burnt offering, with its meal offering and their drink offerings.</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="20" style="v" />“‘On the third day: eleven bulls, two rams, fourteen male lambs a year old without defect; <verse number="21" style="v" />and their meal offering and their drink offerings for the bulls, for the rams, and for the lambs, according to their number, after the ordinance; <verse number="22" style="v" />and one male goat for a sin offering, in addition to the continual burnt offering, and its meal offering, and its drink offering.</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="23" style="v" />“‘On the fourth day ten bulls, two rams, fourteen male lambs a year old without defect; <verse number="24" style="v" />their meal offering and their drink offerings for the bulls, for the rams, and for the lambs, according to their number, after the ordinance; <verse number="25" style="v" />and one male goat for a sin offering; in addition to the continual burnt offering, its meal offering, and its drink offering.</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="26" style="v" />“‘On the fifth day: nine bulls, two rams, fourteen male lambs a year old without defect; <verse number="27" style="v" />and their meal offering and their drink offerings for the bulls, for the rams, and for the lambs, according to their number, after the ordinance, <verse number="28" style="v" />and one male goat for a sin offering, in addition to the continual burnt offering, and its meal offering, and its drink offering.</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="29" style="v" />“‘On the sixth day: eight bulls, two rams, fourteen male lambs a year old without defect; <verse number="30" style="v" />and their meal offering and their drink offerings for the bulls, for the rams, and for the lambs, according to their number, after the ordinance, <verse number="31" style="v" />and one male goat for a sin offering; in addition to the continual burnt offering, its meal offering, and the drink offerings of it.</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="32" style="v" />“‘On the seventh day: seven bulls, two rams, fourteen male lambs a year old without defect; <verse number="33" style="v" />and their meal offering and their drink offerings for the bulls, for the rams, and for the lambs, according to their number, after the ordinance, <verse number="34" style="v" />and one male goat for a sin offering; in addition to the continual burnt offering, its meal offering, and its drink offering.</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="35" style="v" />“‘On the eighth day you shall have a solemn assembly. You shall do no regular work; <verse number="36" style="v" />but you shall offer a burnt offering, an offering made by fire, a pleasant aroma to the LORD: one bull, one ram, seven male lambs a year old without defect; <verse number="37" style="v" />their meal offering and their drink offerings for the bull, for the ram, and for the lambs, shall be according to their number, after the ordinance, <verse number="38" style="v" />and one male goat for a sin offering, in addition to the continual burnt offering, with its meal offering, and its drink offering.</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="39" style="v" />“‘You shall offer these to the LORD in your set feasts—in addition to your vows and your free will offerings—for your burnt offerings, your meal offerings, your drink offerings, and your peace offerings.’”</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="40" style="v" />Moses told the children of Israel according to all that the LORD commanded Moses.</para>
  <chapter number="30" style="c" />
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="1" style="v" />Moses spoke to the heads of the tribes of the children of Israel, saying, “This is the thing which the LORD has commanded. <verse number="2" style="v" />When a man vows a vow to the LORD, or swears an oath to bind his soul with a bond, he shall not break his word. He shall do according to all that proceeds out of his mouth.</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="3" style="v" />“Also, when a woman vows a vow to the LORD and binds herself by a pledge, being in her father’s house, in her youth, <verse number="4" style="v" />and her father hears her vow and her pledge with which she has bound her soul, and her father says nothing to her, then all her vows shall stand, and every pledge with which she has bound her soul shall stand. <verse number="5" style="v" />But if her father forbids her in the day that he hears, none of her vows or of her pledges with which she has bound her soul, shall stand. The LORD will forgive her, because her father has forbidden her.</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="6" style="v" />“If she has a husband, while her vows are on her, or the rash utterance of her lips with which she has bound her soul, <verse number="7" style="v" />and her husband hears it, and says nothing to her in the day that he hears it; then her vows shall stand, and her pledges with which she has bound her soul shall stand. <verse number="8" style="v" />But if her husband forbids her in the day that he hears it, then he makes void her vow which is on her and the rash utterance of her lips, with which she has bound her soul. The LORD will forgive her.</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="9" style="v" />“But the vow of a widow, or of her who is divorced, everything with which she has bound her soul shall stand against her.</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="10" style="v" />“If she vowed in her husband’s house or bound her soul by a bond with an oath, <verse number="11" style="v" />and her husband heard it, and held his peace at her and didn’t disallow her, then all her vows shall stand, and every pledge with which she bound her soul shall stand. <verse number="12" style="v" />But if her husband made them null and void in the day that he heard them, then whatever proceeded out of her lips concerning her vows, or concerning the bond of her soul, shall not stand. Her husband has made them void. The LORD will forgive her. <verse number="13" style="v" />Every vow, and every binding oath to afflict the soul, her husband may establish it, or her husband may make it void. <verse number="14" style="v" />But if her husband says nothing to her from day to day, then he establishes all her vows or all her pledges which are on her. He has established them, because he said nothing to her in the day that he heard them. <verse number="15" style="v" />But if he makes them null and void after he has heard them, then he shall bear her iniquity.”</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="16" style="v" />These are the statutes which the LORD commanded Moses, between a man and his wife, between a father and his daughter, being in her youth, in her father’s house.</para>
  <chapter number="31" style="c" />
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="1" style="v" />The LORD spoke to Moses, saying, <verse number="2" style="v" />“Avenge the children of Israel on the Midianites. Afterward you shall be gathered to your people.”</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="3" style="v" />Moses spoke to the people, saying, “Arm men from amongst you for war, that they may go against Midian, to execute the LORD’s vengeance on Midian. <verse number="4" style="v" />You shall send one thousand out of every tribe, throughout all the tribes of Israel, to the war.” <verse number="5" style="v" />So there were delivered, out of the thousands of Israel, a thousand from every tribe, twelve thousand armed for war. <verse number="6" style="v" />Moses sent them, one thousand of every tribe, to the war with Phinehas the son of Eleazar the priest, to the war, with the vessels of the sanctuary and the trumpets for the alarm in his hand. <verse number="7" style="v" />They fought against Midian, as the LORD commanded Moses. They killed every male. <verse number="8" style="v" />They killed the kings of Midian with the rest of their slain: Evi, Rekem, Zur, Hur, and Reba, the five kings of Midian. They also killed Balaam the son of Beor with the sword. <verse number="9" style="v" />The children of Israel took the women of Midian captive with their little ones; and all their livestock, all their flocks, and all their goods, they took as plunder. <verse number="10" style="v" />All their cities in the places in which they lived, and all their encampments, they burnt with fire. <verse number="11" style="v" />They took all the captives, and all the plunder, both of man and of animal. <verse number="12" style="v" />They brought the captives with the prey and the plunder, to Moses, and to Eleazar the priest, and to the congregation of the children of Israel, to the camp at the plains of Moab, which are by the Jordan at Jericho. <verse number="13" style="v" />Moses and Eleazar the priest, with all the princes of the congregation, went out to meet them outside of the camp. <verse number="14" style="v" />Moses was angry with the officers of the army, the captains of thousands and the captains of hundreds, who came from the service of the war. <verse number="15" style="v" />Moses said to them, “Have you saved all the women alive? <verse number="16" style="v" />Behold, these caused the children of Israel, through the counsel of Balaam, to commit trespass against the LORD in the matter of Peor, and so the plague was amongst the congregation of the LORD. <verse number="17" style="v" />Now therefore kill every male amongst the little ones, and kill every woman who has known man by lying with him. <verse number="18" style="v" />But all the girls, who have not known man by lying with him, keep alive for yourselves.</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="19" style="v" />“Encamp outside of the camp for seven days. Whoever has killed any person, and whoever has touched any slain, purify yourselves on the third day and on the seventh day, you and your captives. <verse number="20" style="v" />You shall purify every garment, and all that is made of skin, and all work of goats’ hair, and all things made of wood.”</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="21" style="v" />Eleazar the priest said to the men of war who went to the battle, “This is the statute of the law which the LORD has commanded Moses. <verse number="22" style="v" />However the gold, and the silver, the bronze, the iron, the tin, and the lead, <verse number="23" style="v" />everything that may withstand the fire, you shall make to go through the fire, and it shall be clean; nevertheless it shall be purified with the water for impurity. All that doesn’t withstand the fire you shall make to go through the water. <verse number="24" style="v" />You shall wash your clothes on the seventh day, and you shall be clean. Afterward you shall come into the camp.”</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="25" style="v" />The LORD spoke to Moses, saying, <verse number="26" style="v" />“Count the plunder that was taken, both of man and of animal, you, and Eleazar the priest, and the heads of the fathers’ households of the congregation; <verse number="27" style="v" />and divide the plunder into two parts: between the men skilled in war, who went out to battle, and all the congregation. <verse number="28" style="v" />Levy a tribute to the LORD of the men of war who went out to battle: one soul of five hundred; of the persons, of the cattle, of the donkeys, and of the flocks. <verse number="29" style="v" />Take it from their half, and give it to Eleazar the priest, for the LORD’s wave offering. <verse number="30" style="v" />Of the children of Israel’s half, you shall take one drawn out of every fifty, of the persons, of the cattle, of the donkeys, and of the flocks, of all the livestock, and give them to the Levites, who perform the duty of the LORD’s tabernacle.”</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="31" style="v" />Moses and Eleazar the priest did as the LORD commanded Moses.</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="32" style="v" />Now the plunder, over and above the booty which the men of war took, was six hundred and seventy-five thousand sheep, <verse number="33" style="v" />seventy-two thousand head of cattle, <verse number="34" style="v" />sixty-one thousand donkeys, <verse number="35" style="v" />and thirty-two thousand persons in all, of the women who had not known man by lying with him. <verse number="36" style="v" />The half, which was the portion of those who went out to war, was in number three hundred and thirty-seven thousand and five hundred sheep; <verse number="37" style="v" />and the LORD’s tribute of the sheep was six hundred and seventy-five. <verse number="38" style="v" />The cattle were thirty-six thousand, of which the LORD’s tribute was seventy-two. <verse number="39" style="v" />The donkeys were thirty thousand and five hundred, of which the LORD’s tribute was sixty-one. <verse number="40" style="v" />The persons were sixteen thousand, of whom the LORD’s tribute was thirty-two persons. <verse number="41" style="v" />Moses gave the tribute, which was the LORD’s wave offering, to Eleazar the priest, as the LORD commanded Moses. <verse number="42" style="v" />Of the children of Israel’s half, which Moses divided off from the men who fought <verse number="43" style="v" />(now the congregation’s half was three hundred and thirty-seven thousand and five hundred sheep, <verse number="44" style="v" />thirty-six thousand head of cattle, <verse number="45" style="v" />thirty thousand and five hundred donkeys, <verse number="46" style="v" />and sixteen thousand persons), <verse number="47" style="v" />even of the children of Israel’s half, Moses took one drawn out of every fifty, both of man and of animal, and gave them to the Levites, who performed the duty of the LORD’s tabernacle, as the LORD commanded Moses.</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="48" style="v" />The officers who were over the thousands of the army, the captains of thousands, and the captains of hundreds, came near to Moses. <verse number="49" style="v" />They said to Moses, “Your servants have taken the sum of the men of war who are under our command, and there lacks not one man of us. <verse number="50" style="v" />We have brought the LORD’s offering, what every man found: gold ornaments, armlets, bracelets, signet rings, earrings, and necklaces, to make atonement for our souls before the LORD.”</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="51" style="v" />Moses and Eleazar the priest took their gold, even all worked jewels. <verse number="52" style="v" />All the gold of the wave offering that they offered up to the LORD, of the captains of thousands, and of the captains of hundreds, was sixteen thousand and seven hundred and fifty shekels.<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">31:52 </char><char style="ft" closed="false">A shekel is about 10 grams or about 0.35 ounces, so 16,750 shekels is about 167.5 kilograms or about 368.5 pounds.</char></note> <verse number="53" style="v" />The men of war had taken booty, every man for himself. <verse number="54" style="v" />Moses and Eleazar the priest took the gold of the captains of thousands and of hundreds, and brought it into the Tent of Meeting for a memorial for the children of Israel before the LORD.</para>
  <chapter number="32" style="c" />
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="1" style="v" />Now the children of Reuben and the children of Gad had a very great multitude of livestock. They saw the land of Jazer, and the land of Gilead. Behold, the place was a place for livestock. <verse number="2" style="v" />Then the children of Gad and the children of Reuben came and spoke to Moses, and to Eleazar the priest, and to the princes of the congregation, saying, <verse number="3" style="v" />“Ataroth, Dibon, Jazer, Nimrah, Heshbon, Elealeh, Sebam, Nebo, and Beon, <verse number="4" style="v" />the land which The LORD struck before the congregation of Israel, is a land for livestock; and your servants have livestock.” <verse number="5" style="v" />They said, “If we have found favour in your sight, let this land be given to your servants for a possession. Don’t bring us over the Jordan.”</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="6" style="v" />Moses said to the children of Gad, and to the children of Reuben, “Shall your brothers go to war while you sit here? <verse number="7" style="v" />Why do you discourage the heart of the children of Israel from going over into the land which the LORD has given them? <verse number="8" style="v" />Your fathers did so when I sent them from Kadesh Barnea to see the land. <verse number="9" style="v" />For when they went up to the valley of Eshcol, and saw the land, they discouraged the heart of the children of Israel, that they should not go into the land which the LORD had given them. <verse number="10" style="v" />The LORD’s anger burnt in that day, and he swore, saying, <verse number="11" style="v" />‘Surely none of the men who came up out of Egypt, from twenty years old and upward, shall see the land which I swore to Abraham, to Isaac, and to Jacob; because they have not wholly followed me, <verse number="12" style="v" />except Caleb the son of Jephunneh the Kenizzite, and Joshua the son of Nun, because they have followed the LORD completely.’ <verse number="13" style="v" />The LORD’s anger burnt against Israel, and he made them wander back and forth in the wilderness forty years, until all the generation who had done evil in the LORD’s sight was consumed.</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="14" style="v" />“Behold, you have risen up in your fathers’ place, an increase of sinful men, to increase the fierce anger of the LORD towards Israel. <verse number="15" style="v" />For if you turn away from after him, he will yet again leave them in the wilderness; and you will destroy all these people.”</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="16" style="v" />They came near to him, and said, “We will build sheepfolds here for our livestock, and cities for our little ones; <verse number="17" style="v" />but we ourselves will be ready armed to go before the children of Israel, until we have brought them to their place. Our little ones shall dwell in the fortified cities because of the inhabitants of the land. <verse number="18" style="v" />We will not return to our houses until the children of Israel have all received their inheritance. <verse number="19" style="v" />For we will not inherit with them on the other side of the Jordan and beyond, because our inheritance has come to us on this side of the Jordan eastward.”</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="20" style="v" />Moses said to them: “If you will do this thing, if you will arm yourselves to go before the LORD to the war, <verse number="21" style="v" />and every one of your armed men will pass over the Jordan before the LORD until he has driven out his enemies from before him, <verse number="22" style="v" />and the land is subdued before the LORD; then afterward you shall return, and be clear of obligation to the LORD and to Israel. Then this land shall be your possession before the LORD.</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="23" style="v" />“But if you will not do so, behold, you have sinned against the LORD; and be sure your sin will find you out. <verse number="24" style="v" />Build cities for your little ones, and folds for your sheep; and do that which has proceeded out of your mouth.”</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="25" style="v" />The children of Gad and the children of Reuben spoke to Moses, saying, “Your servants will do as my lord commands. <verse number="26" style="v" />Our little ones, our wives, our flocks, and all our livestock shall be there in the cities of Gilead; <verse number="27" style="v" />but your servants will pass over, every man who is armed for war, before the LORD to battle, as my lord says.”</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="28" style="v" />So Moses commanded concerning them to Eleazar the priest, and to Joshua the son of Nun, and to the heads of the fathers’ households of the tribes of the children of Israel. <verse number="29" style="v" />Moses said to them, “If the children of Gad and the children of Reuben will pass with you over the Jordan, every man who is armed to battle before the LORD, and the land is subdued before you, then you shall give them the land of Gilead for a possession; <verse number="30" style="v" />but if they will not pass over with you armed, they shall have possessions amongst you in the land of Canaan.”</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="31" style="v" />The children of Gad and the children of Reuben answered, saying, “As the LORD has said to your servants, so will we do. <verse number="32" style="v" />We will pass over armed before the LORD into the land of Canaan, and the possession of our inheritance shall remain with us beyond the Jordan.”</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="33" style="v" />Moses gave to them, even to the children of Gad, and to the children of Reuben, and to the half-tribe of Manasseh the son of Joseph, the kingdom of Sihon king of the Amorites, and the kingdom of Og king of Bashan; the land, according to its cities and borders, even the cities of the surrounding land. <verse number="34" style="v" />The children of Gad built Dibon, Ataroth, Aroer, <verse number="35" style="v" />Atroth-shophan, Jazer, Jogbehah, <verse number="36" style="v" />Beth Nimrah, and Beth Haran: fortified cities and folds for sheep. <verse number="37" style="v" />The children of Reuben built Heshbon, Elealeh, Kiriathaim, <verse number="38" style="v" />Nebo, and Baal Meon, (their names being changed), and Sibmah. They gave other names to the cities which they built. <verse number="39" style="v" />The children of Machir the son of Manasseh went to Gilead, took it, and dispossessed the Amorites who were therein. <verse number="40" style="v" />Moses gave Gilead to Machir the son of Manasseh; and he lived therein. <verse number="41" style="v" />Jair the son of Manasseh went and took its villages, and called them Havvoth Jair. <verse number="42" style="v" />Nobah went and took Kenath and its villages, and called it Nobah, after his own name.</para>
  <chapter number="33" style="c" />
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="1" style="v" />These are the journeys of the children of Israel, when they went out of the land of Egypt by their armies under the hand of Moses and Aaron. <verse number="2" style="v" />Moses wrote the starting points of their journeys by the commandment of the LORD. These are their journeys according to their starting points. <verse number="3" style="v" />They travelled from Rameses in the first month, on the fifteenth day of the first month; on the next day after the Passover, the children of Israel went out with a high hand in the sight of all the Egyptians, <verse number="4" style="v" />while the Egyptians were burying all their firstborn, whom the LORD had struck amongst them. The LORD also executed judgements on their gods. <verse number="5" style="v" />The children of Israel travelled from Rameses, and encamped in Succoth. <verse number="6" style="v" />They travelled from Succoth, and encamped in Etham, which is in the edge of the wilderness. <verse number="7" style="v" />They travelled from Etham, and turned back to Pihahiroth, which is before Baal Zephon, and they encamped before Migdol. <verse number="8" style="v" />They travelled from before Hahiroth, and crossed through the middle of the sea into the wilderness. They went three days’ journey in the wilderness of Etham, and encamped in Marah. <verse number="9" style="v" />They travelled from Marah, and came to Elim. In Elim, there were twelve springs of water and seventy palm trees, and they encamped there. <verse number="10" style="v" />They travelled from Elim, and encamped by the Red Sea. <verse number="11" style="v" />They travelled from the Red Sea, and encamped in the wilderness of Sin. <verse number="12" style="v" />They travelled from the wilderness of Sin, and encamped in Dophkah. <verse number="13" style="v" />They travelled from Dophkah, and encamped in Alush. <verse number="14" style="v" />They travelled from Alush, and encamped in Rephidim, where there was no water for the people to drink. <verse number="15" style="v" />They travelled from Rephidim, and encamped in the wilderness of Sinai. <verse number="16" style="v" />They travelled from the wilderness of Sinai, and encamped in Kibroth Hattaavah. <verse number="17" style="v" />They travelled from Kibroth Hattaavah, and encamped in Hazeroth. <verse number="18" style="v" />They travelled from Hazeroth, and encamped in Rithmah. <verse number="19" style="v" />They travelled from Rithmah, and encamped in Rimmon Perez. <verse number="20" style="v" />They travelled from Rimmon Perez, and encamped in Libnah. <verse number="21" style="v" />They travelled from Libnah, and encamped in Rissah. <verse number="22" style="v" />They travelled from Rissah, and encamped in Kehelathah. <verse number="23" style="v" />They travelled from Kehelathah, and encamped in Mount Shepher. <verse number="24" style="v" />They travelled from Mount Shepher, and encamped in Haradah. <verse number="25" style="v" />They travelled from Haradah, and encamped in Makheloth. <verse number="26" style="v" />They travelled from Makheloth, and encamped in Tahath. <verse number="27" style="v" />They travelled from Tahath, and encamped in Terah. <verse number="28" style="v" />They travelled from Terah, and encamped in Mithkah. <verse number="29" style="v" />They travelled from Mithkah, and encamped in Hashmonah. <verse number="30" style="v" />They travelled from Hashmonah, and encamped in Moseroth. <verse number="31" style="v" />They travelled from Moseroth, and encamped in Bene Jaakan. <verse number="32" style="v" />They travelled from Bene Jaakan, and encamped in Hor Haggidgad. <verse number="33" style="v" />They travelled from Hor Haggidgad, and encamped in Jotbathah. <verse number="34" style="v" />They travelled from Jotbathah, and encamped in Abronah. <verse number="35" style="v" />They travelled from Abronah, and encamped in Ezion Geber. <verse number="36" style="v" />They travelled from Ezion Geber, and encamped at Kadesh in the wilderness of Zin. <verse number="37" style="v" />They travelled from Kadesh, and encamped in Mount Hor, in the edge of the land of Edom. <verse number="38" style="v" />Aaron the priest went up into Mount Hor at the commandment of the LORD and died there, in the fortieth year after the children of Israel had come out of the land of Egypt, in the fifth month, on the first day of the month. <verse number="39" style="v" />Aaron was one hundred and twenty-three years old when he died in Mount Hor. <verse number="40" style="v" />The Canaanite king of Arad, who lived in the South in the land of Canaan, heard of the coming of the children of Israel. <verse number="41" style="v" />They travelled from Mount Hor, and encamped in Zalmonah. <verse number="42" style="v" />They travelled from Zalmonah, and encamped in Punon. <verse number="43" style="v" />They travelled from Punon, and encamped in Oboth. <verse number="44" style="v" />They travelled from Oboth, and encamped in Iye Abarim, in the border of Moab. <verse number="45" style="v" />They travelled from Iyim, and encamped in Dibon Gad. <verse number="46" style="v" />They travelled from Dibon Gad, and encamped in Almon Diblathaim. <verse number="47" style="v" />They travelled from Almon Diblathaim, and encamped in the mountains of Abarim, before Nebo. <verse number="48" style="v" />They travelled from the mountains of Abarim, and encamped in the plains of Moab by the Jordan at Jericho. <verse number="49" style="v" />They encamped by the Jordan, from Beth Jeshimoth even to Abel Shittim in the plains of Moab. <verse number="50" style="v" />The LORD spoke to Moses in the plains of Moab by the Jordan at Jericho, saying, <verse number="51" style="v" />Speak to the children of Israel, and tell them, “When you pass over the Jordan into the land of Canaan, <verse number="52" style="v" />then you shall drive out all the inhabitants of the land from before you, destroy all their stone idols, destroy all their molten images, and demolish all their high places. <verse number="53" style="v" />You shall take possession of the land, and dwell therein; for I have given the land to you to possess it. <verse number="54" style="v" />You shall inherit the land by lot according to your families; to the larger groups you shall give a larger inheritance, and to the smaller you shall give a smaller inheritance. Wherever the lot falls to any man, that shall be his. You shall inherit according to the tribes of your fathers.</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="55" style="v" />“But if you do not drive out the inhabitants of the land from before you, then those you let remain of them will be like pricks in your eyes and thorns in your sides. They will harass you in the land in which you dwell. <verse number="56" style="v" />It shall happen that as I thought to do to them, so I will do to you.”</para>
  <chapter number="34" style="c" />
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="1" style="v" />The LORD spoke to Moses, saying, <verse number="2" style="v" />“Command the children of Israel, and tell them, ‘When you come into the land of Canaan (this is the land that shall fall to you for an inheritance, even the land of Canaan according to its borders), <verse number="3" style="v" />then your south quarter shall be from the wilderness of Zin along by the side of Edom, and your south border shall be from the end of the Salt Sea eastward. <verse number="4" style="v" />Your border shall turn about southward of the ascent of Akrabbim, and pass along to Zin; and it shall pass southward of Kadesh Barnea; and it shall go from there to Hazar Addar, and pass along to Azmon. <verse number="5" style="v" />The border shall turn about from Azmon to the brook of Egypt, and it shall end at the sea.</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="6" style="v" />“‘For the western border, you shall have the great sea and its border. This shall be your west border.</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="7" style="v" />“‘This shall be your north border: from the great sea you shall mark out for yourselves Mount Hor. <verse number="8" style="v" />From Mount Hor you shall mark out to the entrance of Hamath; and the border shall pass by Zedad. <verse number="9" style="v" />Then the border shall go to Ziphron, and it shall end at Hazar Enan. This shall be your north border.</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="10" style="v" />“‘You shall mark out your east border from Hazar Enan to Shepham. <verse number="11" style="v" />The border shall go down from Shepham to Riblah, on the east side of Ain. The border shall go down, and shall reach to the side of the sea of Chinnereth eastward. <verse number="12" style="v" />The border shall go down to the Jordan, and end at the Salt Sea. This shall be your land according to its borders around it.’”</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="13" style="v" />Moses commanded the children of Israel, saying, “This is the land which you shall inherit by lot, which the LORD has commanded to give to the nine tribes, and to the half-tribe; <verse number="14" style="v" />for the tribe of the children of Reuben according to their fathers’ houses, the tribe of the children of Gad according to their fathers’ houses, and the half-tribe of Manasseh have received their inheritance. <verse number="15" style="v" />The two tribes and the half-tribe have received their inheritance beyond the Jordan at Jericho eastward, towards the sunrise.”</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="16" style="v" />The LORD spoke to Moses, saying, <verse number="17" style="v" />“These are the names of the men who shall divide the land to you for inheritance: Eleazar the priest, and Joshua the son of Nun. <verse number="18" style="v" />You shall take one prince of every tribe, to divide the land for inheritance. <verse number="19" style="v" />These are the names of the men: Of the tribe of Judah, Caleb the son of Jephunneh. <verse number="20" style="v" />Of the tribe of the children of Simeon, Shemuel the son of Ammihud. <verse number="21" style="v" />Of the tribe of Benjamin, Elidad the son of Chislon. <verse number="22" style="v" />Of the tribe of the children of Dan a prince, Bukki the son of Jogli. <verse number="23" style="v" />Of the children of Joseph: of the tribe of the children of Manasseh a prince, Hanniel the son of Ephod. <verse number="24" style="v" />Of the tribe of the children of Ephraim a prince, Kemuel the son of Shiphtan. <verse number="25" style="v" />Of the tribe of the children of Zebulun a prince, Elizaphan the son of Parnach. <verse number="26" style="v" />Of the tribe of the children of Issachar a prince, Paltiel the son of Azzan. <verse number="27" style="v" />Of the tribe of the children of Asher a prince, Ahihud the son of Shelomi. <verse number="28" style="v" />Of the tribe of the children of Naphtali a prince, Pedahel the son of Ammihud.” <verse number="29" style="v" />These are they whom the LORD commanded to divide the inheritance to the children of Israel in the land of Canaan.</para>
  <chapter number="35" style="c" />
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="1" style="v" />The LORD spoke to Moses in the plains of Moab by the Jordan at Jericho, saying, <verse number="2" style="v" />“Command the children of Israel to give to the Levites cities to dwell in out of their inheritance. You shall give pasture lands for the cities around them to the Levites. <verse number="3" style="v" />They shall have the cities to dwell in. Their pasture lands shall be for their livestock, and for their possessions, and for all their animals.</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="4" style="v" />“The pasture lands of the cities, which you shall give to the Levites, shall be from the wall of the city and outward one thousand cubits<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">35:4 </char><char style="ft" closed="false">A cubit is the length from the tip of the middle finger to the elbow on a man’s arm, or about 18 inches or 46 centimetres.</char></note> around it. <verse number="5" style="v" />You shall measure outside of the city for the east side two thousand cubits, and for the south side two thousand cubits, and for the west side two thousand cubits, and for the north side two thousand cubits, the city being in the middle. This shall be the pasture lands of their cities.</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="6" style="v" />“The cities which you shall give to the Levites, they shall be the six cities of refuge, which you shall give for the man slayer to flee to. Besides them you shall give forty-two cities. <verse number="7" style="v" />All the cities which you shall give to the Levites shall be forty-eight cities together with their pasture lands. <verse number="8" style="v" />Concerning the cities which you shall give of the possession of the children of Israel, from the many you shall take many, and from the few you shall take few. Everyone according to his inheritance which he inherits shall give some of his cities to the Levites.” <verse number="9" style="v" />The LORD spoke to Moses, saying, <verse number="10" style="v" />“Speak to the children of Israel, and tell them, ‘When you pass over the Jordan into the land of Canaan, <verse number="11" style="v" />then you shall appoint for yourselves cities to be cities of refuge for you, that the man slayer who kills any person unwittingly may flee there. <verse number="12" style="v" />The cities shall be for your refuge from the avenger, that the man slayer not die until he stands before the congregation for judgement. <verse number="13" style="v" />The cities which you shall give shall be for you six cities of refuge. <verse number="14" style="v" />You shall give three cities beyond the Jordan, and you shall give three cities in the land of Canaan. They shall be cities of refuge. <verse number="15" style="v" />These six cities shall be refuge for the children of Israel, for the stranger, and for the foreigner living amongst them, that everyone who kills any person unwittingly may flee there.</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="16" style="v" />“‘But if he struck him with an instrument of iron, so that he died, he is a murderer. The murderer shall surely be put to death. <verse number="17" style="v" />If he struck him with a stone in the hand, by which a man may die, and he died, he is a murderer. The murderer shall surely be put to death. <verse number="18" style="v" />Or if he struck him with a weapon of wood in the hand, by which a man may die, and he died, he is a murderer. The murderer shall surely be put to death. <verse number="19" style="v" />The avenger of blood shall himself put the murderer to death. When he meets him, he shall put him to death. <verse number="20" style="v" />If he shoved him out of hatred, or hurled something at him while lying in wait, so that he died, <verse number="21" style="v" />or in hostility struck him with his hand, so that he died, he who struck him shall surely be put to death. He is a murderer. The avenger of blood shall put the murderer to death when he meets him.</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="22" style="v" />“‘But if he shoved him suddenly without hostility, or hurled on him anything without lying in wait, <verse number="23" style="v" />or with any stone, by which a man may die, not seeing him, and cast it on him so that he died, and he was not his enemy and not seeking his harm, <verse number="24" style="v" />then the congregation shall judge between the striker and the avenger of blood according to these ordinances. <verse number="25" style="v" />The congregation shall deliver the man slayer out of the hand of the avenger of blood, and the congregation shall restore him to his city of refuge, where he had fled. He shall dwell therein until the death of the high priest, who was anointed with the holy oil.</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="26" style="v" />“‘But if the man slayer shall at any time go beyond the border of his city of refuge where he flees, <verse number="27" style="v" />and the avenger of blood finds him outside of the border of his city of refuge, and the avenger of blood kills the man slayer, he shall not be guilty of blood, <verse number="28" style="v" />because he should have remained in his city of refuge until the death of the high priest. But after the death of the high priest, the man slayer shall return into the land of his possession.</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="29" style="v" />“‘These things shall be for a statute and ordinance to you throughout your generations in all your dwellings.</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="30" style="v" />“‘Whoever kills any person, the murderer shall be slain based on the testimony of witnesses; but one witness shall not testify alone against any person so that he dies.</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="31" style="v" />“‘Moreover you shall take no ransom for the life of a murderer who is guilty of death. He shall surely be put to death.</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="32" style="v" />“‘You shall take no ransom for him who has fled to his city of refuge, that he may come again to dwell in the land before the death of the priest.</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="33" style="v" />“‘So you shall not pollute the land where you live; for blood pollutes the land. No atonement can be made for the land, for the blood that is shed in it, but by the blood of him who shed it. <verse number="34" style="v" />You shall not defile the land which you inhabit, where I dwell; for I, the LORD, dwell amongst the children of Israel.’”</para>
  <chapter number="36" style="c" />
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="1" style="v" />The heads of the fathers’ households of the family of the children of Gilead, the son of Machir, the son of Manasseh, of the families of the sons of Joseph, came near, and spoke before Moses and before the princes, the heads of the fathers’ households of the children of Israel. <verse number="2" style="v" />They said, “The LORD commanded my lord to give the land for inheritance by lot to the children of Israel. My lord was commanded by the LORD to give the inheritance of Zelophehad our brother to his daughters. <verse number="3" style="v" />If they are married to any of the sons of the other tribes of the children of Israel, then their inheritance will be taken away from the inheritance of our fathers, and will be added to the inheritance of the tribe to which they shall belong. So it will be taken away from the lot of our inheritance. <verse number="4" style="v" />When the jubilee of the children of Israel comes, then their inheritance will be added to the inheritance of the tribe to which they shall belong. So their inheritance will be taken away from the inheritance of the tribe of our fathers.”</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="5" style="v" />Moses commanded the children of Israel according to the LORD’s word, saying, “The tribe of the sons of Joseph speak what is right. <verse number="6" style="v" />This is the thing which the LORD commands concerning the daughters of Zelophehad, saying, ‘Let them be married to whom they think best, only they shall marry into the family of the tribe of their father. <verse number="7" style="v" />So shall no inheritance of the children of Israel move from tribe to tribe; for the children of Israel shall all keep the inheritance of the tribe of his fathers. <verse number="8" style="v" />Every daughter who possesses an inheritance in any tribe of the children of Israel shall be wife to one of the family of the tribe of her father, that the children of Israel may each possess the inheritance of his fathers. <verse number="9" style="v" />So shall no inheritance move from one tribe to another tribe; for the tribes of the children of Israel shall each keep his own inheritance.’”</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="10" style="v" />The daughters of Zelophehad did as the LORD commanded Moses: <verse number="11" style="v" />for Mahlah, Tirzah, Hoglah, Milcah, and Noah, the daughters of Zelophehad, were married to their father’s brothers’ sons. <verse number="12" style="v" />They were married into the families of the sons of Manasseh the son of Joseph. Their inheritance remained in the tribe of the family of their father.</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="13" style="v" />These are the commandments and the ordinances which the LORD commanded by Moses to the children of Israel in the plains of Moab by the Jordan at Jericho.</para>
</usx>