<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<usx version="2.6">
  <book code="1ES" style="id">- 1 Esdras</book>
  <para style="h">1 Esdras</para>
  <para style="toc1">1 Esdras</para>
  <para style="toc2">1 Esdras</para>
  <para style="toc3">1Es</para>
  <para style="mt1">THE FIRST BOOK OF ESDRAS</para>
  <para style="ip">
    <char style="bk">The First Book of Esdras</char> is recognised as Deuterocanonical Scripture by the Greek Orthodox and Russian Orthodox Churches. It is not recognised by the Roman Catholic Church, but 1 Esdras is placed as an appendix to the Latin Vulgate Bible.</para>
  <chapter number="1" style="c" />
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="1" style="v" />
    <note caller="+" style="x">
      <char style="xo" closed="false">1:1 </char>
      <char style="xt" closed="false">
        <ref loc="2KI 23:21">2 Kings 23:21</ref>; <ref loc="2CH 35:1">2 Chronicles 35:1</ref></char>
    </note> Josias held the Passover in Jerusalem to his Lord, and offered the Passover the fourteenth day of the first month; <verse number="2" style="v" />having set the priests according to their daily courses, being arrayed in their vestments, in the temple of the Lord. <verse number="3" style="v" />And he spoke to the Levites,<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">1:3 </char><char style="ft" closed="false">That is, </char><char style="fqa" closed="false">the temple servants. </char><char style="ft" closed="false">See Num. 3:9.</char></note> the temple-servants of Israel, that they should make themselves holy to the Lord, to set the holy ark of the Lord in the house that King Solomon the son of David had built: <verse number="4" style="v" /><char style="add">and said,</char> You° shall no more have need to bear it upon your shoulders: now therefore serve the Lord your God, and minister to his people Israel, and prepare you after your fathers’ houses and kindred, <verse number="5" style="v" />according to the writing of David king of Israel, and according to the magnificence of Solomon his son: and standing in the holy place according to the several divisions of the families of you the Levites, who <char style="add">minister</char> in the presence of your kindred the children of Israel, <verse number="6" style="v" />offer the Passover in order, and make ready the sacrifices for your kindred, and keep the Passover according to the commandment of the Lord, which was given to Moses. <verse number="7" style="v" />And to the people which were present Josias gave thirty thousand lambs and kids, <char style="add">and</char> three thousand calves: these things were given of the king’s substance, according as he promised, to the people, and to the priests and Levites. <verse number="8" style="v" />And Helkias, and Zacharias, and<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">1:8 </char><char style="fq" closed="false">Jehiel, </char><char style="ft" closed="false">2 Chronicles 35:8.</char></note> Esyelus, the rulers of the temple, gave to the priests for the Passover two thousand <char style="add">and</char> six hundred sheep, <char style="add">and</char> three hundred calves. <verse number="9" style="v" />And Jeconias, and Samaias and Nathanael his brother, and Sabias, and Ochielus, and Joram, captains over thousands, gave to the Levites for the Passover five thousand sheep, <char style="add">and</char> seven hundred calves. <verse number="10" style="v" />And when these things were done, the priests and Levites, having the unleavened bread, stood in comely order according to the kindred, <verse number="11" style="v" />and according to the several divisions by fathers’ houses, before the people, to offer to the Lord, as it is written in the book of Moses: and thus <char style="add">did they</char> in the morning. <verse number="12" style="v" />And they roasted the Passover with fire, as appertains: and the sacrifices they sod in the brazen vessels and cauldrons with a good savour, <verse number="13" style="v" />and set them before all the people: and afterward they prepared for themselves, and for the priests their kindred, the sons of Aaron. <verse number="14" style="v" />For the priests offered the fat until night: and the Levites prepared for themselves, and for the priests their kindred, the sons of Aaron. <verse number="15" style="v" />The holy singers also, the sons of Asaph, were in their order, according to the appointment of David, <char style="add">to wit,</char> Asaph, Zacharias, and Eddinus, who<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">1:15 </char><char style="ft" closed="false">Another reading is, </char><char style="fqa" closed="false">were.</char></note> was of the king’s retinue. <verse number="16" style="v" />Moreover the gatekeepers were at every gate; none had need to depart from his daily course: for their kindred the Levites prepared for them. <verse number="17" style="v" />Thus were the things that belonged to the sacrifices of the Lord accomplished in that day, in holding the Passover, <verse number="18" style="v" />and offering sacrifices upon the altar of the Lord, according to the commandment of King Josias. <verse number="19" style="v" />So the children of Israel which were present at that time held the Passover, and the feast of unleavened bread seven days. <verse number="20" style="v" />And such a Passover was not held in Israel since the time of the prophet Samuel. <verse number="21" style="v" />Yes, all the kings of Israel held not such a Passover as Josias, and the priests, and the Levites, and the Jews, held with all Israel that were present in their dwelling place at Jerusalem. <verse number="22" style="v" />In the eighteenth year of the reign of Josias was this Passover held. <verse number="23" style="v" />And the works of Josias were upright before his Lord with a heart full of godliness. <verse number="24" style="v" />Moreover the things that came to pass in his days have been written in times past, concerning those that sinned, and did wickedly against the Lord above every people and kingdom, and how they grieved him<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">1:24 </char><char style="ft" closed="false">Or, </char><char style="fqa" closed="false">sensibly </char><char style="ft" closed="false">Judges 16:17.</char></note> exceedingly, so that the words of the Lord were confirmed against Israel.</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="25" style="v" />
    <note caller="+" style="x">
      <char style="xo" closed="false">1:25 </char>
      <char style="xt" closed="false">
        <ref loc="2CH 35:20">2 Chronicles 35:20</ref>
      </char>
    </note> Now after all these acts of Josias it came to pass, that Pharaoh the king of Egypt came to raise war at Carchemish upon Euphrates: and Josias went out against him. <verse number="26" style="v" />But the king of Egypt sent to him, saying, What have I to do with you, O king of Judea? <verse number="27" style="v" />I am not sent out from the Lord God against you; for my war is upon Euphrates: and now the Lord is with me, yes, the Lord is with me hastening me forward: depart from me, and be not against the Lord. <verse number="28" style="v" />However Josias didn’t turn back<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">1:28 </char><char style="ft" closed="false">Another reading is, </char><char style="fqa" closed="false">his chariot from him.</char></note> to his chariot, but undertook to fight with him, not regarding the words of the prophet Jeremy <char style="add">spoken</char> by the mouth of the Lord: <verse number="29" style="v" />but joined battle with him in the plain of Megiddo, and the princes came down against King Josias. <verse number="30" style="v" />Then said the king to his servants, Carry me away out of the battle; for I am very weak. And immediately his servants carried him away out of the army. <verse number="31" style="v" />Then got he up upon his second chariot; and being brought back to Jerusalem he died, and was buried in the sepulchre of his fathers. <verse number="32" style="v" />And in all Jewry they mourned for Josias; and Jeremy the prophet lamented for Josias, and the chief men with the women made lamentation for him, to this day: and this was given out for an ordinance to be done continually in all the nation of Israel. <verse number="33" style="v" />These things are written in the book of the histories of the kings of Judea, and every one of the acts that Josias did, and his glory, and his understanding in the law of the Lord, and the things that he had done before, and the things now <char style="add">recited</char>, are reported in the book of the kings of Israel and Judah.</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="34" style="v" />
    <note caller="+" style="x">
      <char style="xo" closed="false">1:34 </char>
      <char style="xt" closed="false">
        <ref loc="2KI 23:30">2 Kings 23:30</ref>; <ref loc="2CH 36:1">2 Chronicles 36:1</ref></char>
    </note> And the people took<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">1:34 </char><char style="ft" closed="false">Another reading is, </char><char style="fqa" closed="false">Jeconias.</char></note> Joachaz the son of Josias, and made him king instead of Josias his father, when he was twenty and three years old. <verse number="35" style="v" />And he reigned in<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">1:35 </char><char style="ft" closed="false">Another reading is, </char><char style="fqa" closed="false">Israel.</char></note> Judah and in Jerusalem three months: and then the king of Egypt deposed him from reigning in Jerusalem. <verse number="36" style="v" />And he set a tax upon the people of a hundred talents of silver and one talent of gold. <verse number="37" style="v" />The king of Egypt also made King Joakim his brother king of Judea and Jerusalem. <verse number="38" style="v" />And Joakim bound the nobles: but Zarakes his brother he apprehended, and brought him up out of Egypt. <verse number="39" style="v" />Five and twenty years old was <note caller="+" style="x"><char style="xo" closed="false">1:39 </char><char style="xt" closed="false"><ref loc="2CH 36:4-5">2 Chronicles 36:4-5</ref></char></note> Joakim when he began to reign in Judea and Jerusalem; and he did that which was evil in the sight of the Lord. <verse number="40" style="v" />And against him Nabuchodonosor the king of Babylon came up, and bound him with a chain of brass, and carried him to Babylon. <verse number="41" style="v" />Nabuchodonosor also took of the holy vessels of the Lord, and carried them away, and set them up in his own temple at Babylon. <verse number="42" style="v" />But those things that are reported of him, and of his uncleanness and impiety, are written in the chronicles of the kings. <verse number="43" style="v" />And Joakim his son reigned in his stead: for when he was made king he was<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">1:43 </char><char style="ft" closed="false">Another reading is, </char><char style="fqa" closed="false">eight.</char></note> eighteen years old; <verse number="44" style="v" />and he reigned three months and ten days in Jerusalem; and did that which was evil before the Lord.</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="45" style="v" />So after a year Nabuchodonosor sent and caused him to be brought to Babylon with the holy vessels of the Lord; <verse number="46" style="v" />and made Sedekias king of Judea and Jerusalem, when he was one and twenty years old; and he reigned eleven years: <verse number="47" style="v" />and he also did that which was evil in the sight of the Lord, and cared not for the words that were spoken by Jeremy the prophet from the mouth of the Lord. <verse number="48" style="v" />And after king Nabuchodonosor had made him to swear by the name of the Lord, he forswore himself, and rebelled; and hardening his neck, and his heart, he transgressed the laws of the Lord, the God of Israel. <verse number="49" style="v" />Moreover the governors of the people and of the priests did many things wickedly,<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">1:49 </char><char style="ft" closed="false">Another reading is, </char><char style="fqa" closed="false">even above all.</char></note> and passed all the pollutions of all nations, and defiled the temple of the Lord, which was sanctified in Jerusalem. <verse number="50" style="v" />And the God of their fathers sent by his messenger to call them back, because he had compassion on them and on his dwelling place. <verse number="51" style="v" />But they mocked his messengers; and in the day when the Lord spoke <char style="add">to them,</char> they scoffed at his prophets: <verse number="52" style="v" />so far forth, that he, being angry with his people for their great ungodliness, commanded to bring up the kings of the Chaldeans against them; <verse number="53" style="v" />who killed their young men with the sword, round about their holy temple, and spared neither young man nor maid, old man nor child; but he delivered all into their hands. <verse number="54" style="v" />And they took all the holy vessels of the Lord, both great and small, with<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">1:54 </char><char style="ft" closed="false">Another reading is, </char><char style="fqa" closed="false">the arks of the Lord.</char></note> the vessels of the ark of the Lord, and the king’s treasures, and carried them away to Babylon. <verse number="55" style="v" />And they burnt the house of the Lord, and brake down the walls of Jerusalem, and burnt the towers thereof with fire: <verse number="56" style="v" />and as for her glorious things, they never ceased till they had brought them all to nothing: and the people that were not slain with the sword he carried to Babylon: <verse number="57" style="v" />and they were servants to him and to his children, till the Persians reigned, to fulfil the word of the Lord by the mouth of Jeremy: <verse number="58" style="v" />Until the land has enjoyed her Sabbaths, the whole time of her desolation shall she keep Sabbath, to fulfil threescore and ten years.</para>
  <chapter number="2" style="c" />
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="1" style="v" />In the <note caller="+" style="x"><char style="xo" closed="false">2:1 </char><char style="xt" closed="false"><ref loc="2CH 36:22">2 Chronicles 36:22</ref>,<ref loc="2CH 36:23">23</ref>; <ref loc="EZR 1:1">Ezra 1:1</ref></char></note> first year of Cyrus king of the Persians, that the word of the Lord by the mouth of Jeremy might be accomplished, <verse number="2" style="v" />the Lord stirred up the spirit of Cyrus king of the Persians, and he made proclamation through all his kingdom, and also by writing, <verse number="3" style="v" />saying, Cyrus king of the Persians says: The Lord of Israel, the Most High Lord, has made me king of the whole world, <verse number="4" style="v" />and commanded me to build him a house at Jerusalem that is in Judea. <verse number="5" style="v" />If therefore there be any of you that are of his people,<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">2:5 </char><char style="ft" closed="false">Another reading is, </char><char style="fqa" closed="false">Let his Lord be etc.</char></note> let the Lord, even his Lord, be with him, and let him go up to Jerusalem that is in Judea, and build the house of the Lord of Israel: he is the Lord that dwells in Jerusalem. <verse number="6" style="v" />Of such therefore as dwell in various places, let those who are in his own place help each one with gold, and with silver, <verse number="7" style="v" />with gifts, with horses also and cattle, beside the other things which have been added by vow for the temple of the Lord which is in Jerusalem.</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="8" style="v" />Then the chief of the families of Judah and of the tribe of Benjamin stood up; the priests also, and the Levites, and all they whose spirit the Lord had stirred to go up, to build the house for the Lord which is in Jerusalem. <verse number="9" style="v" />And those who lived round about them helped them in all things with silver and gold, with horses and cattle, and with very many gifts that were vowed of a great number whose minds were stirred up <char style="add">thereto. </char> <verse number="10" style="v" />King Cyrus also brought forth the holy vessels of the Lord, which Nabuchodonosor had carried away from Jerusalem, and had set up in his temple of idols. <verse number="11" style="v" />Now when Cyrus king of the Persians had brought them forth, he delivered them to Mithradates his treasurer, <verse number="12" style="v" />and by him they were delivered to<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">2:12 </char><char style="ft" closed="false">Another reading is, </char><char style="fqa" closed="false">Simanassar.</char></note> Sanabassar the governor of Judea. <verse number="13" style="v" />And this was the number of them: A thousand golden cups, a thousand cups of silver, censers of silver twenty nine, vials of gold thirty, and of silver two thousand and four hundred and ten, and other vessels a thousand. <verse number="14" style="v" />So all the vessels of gold and of silver were brought up, even five thousand and four hundred threescore and nine, <verse number="15" style="v" />and were carried back by Sanabassar, together with them of the captivity, from Babylon to Jerusalem.</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="16" style="v" />
    <note caller="+" style="x">
      <char style="xo" closed="false">2:16 </char>
      <char style="xt" closed="false">
        <ref loc="EZR 4:7">Ezra 4:7</ref>
      </char>
    </note> But in the time of Artaxerxes king of the Persians Belemus, and Mithradates, and Tabellius, and<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">2:16 </char><char style="fqa" closed="false">Rehum,</char></note> Rathumus, and Beeltethmus, and<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">2:16 </char><char style="fqa" closed="false">Shimshai.</char></note> Samellius the scribe, with the others that were in commission with them, dwelling in Samaria and other places, wrote to him against those who lived in Judea and Jerusalem the letter following: <verse number="17" style="v" />To king Artaxerxes our Lord, Your servants, Rathumus the recorder, and Samellius the scribe, and the rest of their council, and the judges that are in Coelesyria and Phoenicia. <verse number="18" style="v" />Be it now known to our lord the king, that the Jews that have come up from you to us, having come to Jerusalem, are building that rebellious and wicked city, and are repairing its marketplaces and walls, and are laying the foundation of a temple. <verse number="19" style="v" />Now if this city is built and the walls <char style="add">thereof</char> are finished, they will not only refuse to give tribute, but will even stand up against kings. <verse number="20" style="v" />And forasmuch as the things pertaining to the temple are now in hand, we think it meet not to neglect such a matter, <verse number="21" style="v" />but to speak to our lord the king, to the intent that, if it be your pleasure, search may be made in the books of your fathers: <verse number="22" style="v" />and you shall find in the chronicles what is written concerning these things, and shall understand that that city was rebellious, troubling both kings and cities: <verse number="23" style="v" />and that the Jews were rebellious, and raised always wars therein of old time; for the which cause even this city was laid waste. <verse number="24" style="v" />Wherefore now we do declare to you, O lord the king, that if this city be built again, and the walls thereof set up anew, you shall from henceforth have no passage into Coelesyria and Phoenicia. <verse number="25" style="v" />Then the king wrote back again to Rathumus the recorder, and Beeltethmus, and Samellius the scribe, and to the rest that were in commission, and lived in Samaria and Syria and Phoenicia, after this manner: <verse number="26" style="v" />I have read the letter which you° have sent to me: therefore I commanded to make search, and it has been found that that city of old time has made insurrection against kings; <verse number="27" style="v" />and the men were given to rebellion and war therein: and that mighty kings and fierce were in Jerusalem, who reigned and exacted tribute in Coelesyria and Phoenicia. <verse number="28" style="v" />Now therefore I have commanded to hinder those men from building the city, and heed to be taken that there be nothing done contrary to this <char style="add">order; </char> <verse number="29" style="v" />and that those wicked doings proceed no further to the annoyance of kings. <verse number="30" style="v" />Then king Artaxerxes, his letters being read, Rathumus, and Samellius the scribe, and the rest that were in commission with them, removing in haste to Jerusalem with horsemen and a multitude of people in battle array, began to hinder the builders; and the building of the temple in Jerusalem ceased until the second year of the reign of Darius king of the Persians.</para>
  <chapter number="3" style="c" />
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="1" style="v" />Now king Darius made a great feast to all his subjects, and to all that were born in his house, and to all the princes of Media and of Persia, <verse number="2" style="v" />and to all the local governors and captains and governors that were under him, from India to Ethiopia, in the hundred and twenty and seven provinces. <verse number="3" style="v" />And when they had eaten and drunken, and being satisfied were gone home, then Darius the king went into his bedchamber, and slept, and awaked out of his sleep.</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="4" style="v" />Then the three young men of the body-guard, that kept the king’s person, spoke one to another: <verse number="5" style="v" />Let every one of us say one thing which shall be strongest: and he whose sentence shall seem wiser than the others, to him shall Darius the king give great gifts, and great honours in token of victory: <verse number="6" style="v" />as, to be clothed in purple, to drink in gold, and to sleep upon gold, and a chariot with bridles of gold, and a turban of fine linen, and a chain about his neck: <verse number="7" style="v" />and he shall sit next to Darius because of his wisdom, and shall be called Darius his cousin. <verse number="8" style="v" />And then they wrote every one his sentence, and set to their seals, and laid <char style="add">the writing</char> under king Darius his pillow, <verse number="9" style="v" />and said, When the king is risen, some shall give him the writing; and of whose side the king and the three princes of Persia shall judge that his sentence is the wisest, to him shall the victory be given, as it is written. <verse number="10" style="v" />The first wrote, Wine is the strongest. <verse number="11" style="v" />The second wrote, The king is strongest. <verse number="12" style="v" />The third wrote, Women are strongest: but above all things Truth bears away the victory.</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="13" style="v" />Now when the king was risen up, they took the writing, and gave it to him, and so he read it: <verse number="14" style="v" />and sending forth he called all the princes of Persia and of Media, and the local governors, and the captains, and the governors, and the chief officers; <verse number="15" style="v" />and sat him down in the royal seat of judgement; and the writing was read before them. <verse number="16" style="v" />And he said, Call the young men, and they shall explain their own sentences. So they were called, and came in. <verse number="17" style="v" />And they said to them, Declare to us your mind concerning the things you° have written.</para>
  <para style="p">Then began the first, who had spoken of the strength of wine, <verse number="18" style="v" />and said thus, O sirs, how exceedingly strong is wine! it causes all men to err that drink it: <verse number="19" style="v" />it makes the mind of the king and of the fatherless child to be all one; of the bondman and of the freeman, of the poor man and of the rich: <verse number="20" style="v" />it turns also every thought into cheer and mirth, so that a man remembers neither sorrow nor debt: <verse number="21" style="v" />and it makes every heart rich, so that a man remembers neither king nor local governor; and it makes to speak all things by talents: <verse number="22" style="v" />and when they are in their cups, they forget their love both to friends and kindred, and a little after draw their swords: <verse number="23" style="v" />but when they awake from their wine, they remember not what they have done. <verse number="24" style="v" />O sirs, is not wine the strongest, seeing that it enforces to do thus? And when he had so spoken, he held his peace.</para>
  <chapter number="4" style="c" />
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="1" style="v" />Then the second, that had spoken of the strength of the king, began to say, <verse number="2" style="v" />O sirs, do not men excel in strength, that bear rule over the sea and land, and all things in them? <verse number="3" style="v" />But yet is the king stronger: and he is their lord, and has dominion over them; and in whatever he commands them they obey him. <verse number="4" style="v" />If he bid them make war the one against the other, they do it: and if he send them out against the enemies, they go, and overcome mountains, walls, and towers. <verse number="5" style="v" />They kill and are slain, and transgress not the king’s commandment: if they get the victory, they bring all to the king, as well the plunder, as all things else. <verse number="6" style="v" />Likewise for those that are no soldiers, and have not to do with wars, but use husbandry, when they have reaped again that which they had sown, they bring it to the king, and compel one another to pay tribute to the king. <verse number="7" style="v" />And he is<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">4:7 </char><char style="ft" closed="false">Or, </char><char style="fqa" closed="false">one and alone</char></note> but one man: if he command to kill, they kill; if he command to spare, they spare; <verse number="8" style="v" />if he command to strike, they strike; if he command to make desolate, they make desolate; if he command to build, they build; <verse number="9" style="v" />if he command to cut down, they cut down; if he command to plant, they plant. <verse number="10" style="v" />So all his people and his armies obey him: furthermore he lies down, he eats and drinks, and takes his rest: <verse number="11" style="v" />and these keep watch round about him, neither may any one depart, and do his own business, neither disobey they him <char style="add">in anything. </char> <verse number="12" style="v" />O sirs, how should not the king be strongest, seeing that in such sort he is obeyed? And he held his peace.</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="13" style="v" />Then the third, who had spoken of women, and of truth, (this was Zorobabel) began to speak. <verse number="14" style="v" />O sirs, is not the king great, and men are many, and wine is strong? who is it then that rules them, or has the lordship over them? are they not women? <verse number="15" style="v" />Women have borne the king and all the people that bear rule by sea and land. <verse number="16" style="v" />Even of them came they: and they nourished them up that planted the vineyards, from whence the wine comes. <verse number="17" style="v" />These also make garments for men; these bring glory to men; and without women can’t men be. <verse number="18" style="v" />Yes, and if men have gathered together gold and silver and any other goodly thing,<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">4:18 </char><char style="ft" closed="false">Another reading is, </char><char style="fqa" closed="false">do they not love etc.</char></note> and see a woman which is comely in favour and beauty, <verse number="19" style="v" />they let all those things go, and gape after her, and even with open mouth fix their eyes fast on her; and have all more desire to her than to gold or silver, or any goodly thing whatever. <verse number="20" style="v" />A man leaves his own father that brought him up, and his own country, and joins with his wife. <verse number="21" style="v" />And with his wife he ends his days, and remembers neither father, nor mother, nor country. <verse number="22" style="v" />By this also you° must know that women have dominion over you: do you° not labour and toil, and give and bring all to women? <verse number="23" style="v" />Yes, a man takes his sword, and goes forth to make outroads, and to rob and to steal, and to sail upon the sea and upon rivers; <verse number="24" style="v" />and looks upon a lion, and walks in the darkness; and when he has stolen, plundered, and robbed, he brings it to his love. <verse number="25" style="v" />Wherefore a man loves his wife better than father or mother. <verse number="26" style="v" />Yes, many there be that have run out of their wits for women, and become bondmen for their sakes. <verse number="27" style="v" />Many also have perished, have stumbled, and sinned, for women. <verse number="28" style="v" />And now do you° not believe me? is not the king great in his power? do not all regions fear to touch him? <verse number="29" style="v" />Yet did I see him and Apame the king’s concubine, the daughter of the illustrious Barticus, sitting at the right hand of the king, <verse number="30" style="v" />and taking the crown from the king’s head, and setting it upon her own head; yes, she struck the king with her left hand: <verse number="31" style="v" />and therewithal the king gaped and gazed upon her with open mouth: if she laughed upon him, he laughed also: but if she took any displeasure at him, he was fain to flatter, that she might be reconciled to him again. <verse number="32" style="v" />O sirs, how can it be but women should be strong, seeing they do thus?</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="33" style="v" />Then the king and the nobles looked one upon another: so he began to speak concerning truth. <verse number="34" style="v" />O sirs, are not women strong? great is the earth, high is the heaven, swift is the sun in his course, for he encircles the heavens round about, and fetches his course again to his own place in one day. <verse number="35" style="v" />Is he not great that makes these things? therefore great is truth, and stronger than all things. <verse number="36" style="v" />All the earth calls upon truth, and the heaven blesses her: all works shake and tremble, but with<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">4:36 </char><char style="ft" closed="false">Another reading is, him.</char></note> her is no unrighteous thing. <verse number="37" style="v" />Wine is unrighteous, the king is unrighteous, women are unrighteous, all the children of men are unrighteous, and unrighteous are all such their works; and there is no truth in them; in their unrighteousness also they shall perish. <verse number="38" style="v" />But truth remains, and is strong forever; she lives and conquers forevermore. <verse number="39" style="v" />With her there is no accepting of persons or rewards; but she does the things that are just, <char style="add">and refrains</char> from all unrighteous and wicked things; and all men do well like of her works. <verse number="40" style="v" />Neither in her judgement is any unrighteousness; and she is the strength, and the kingdom, and the power, and the majesty, of all ages. Blessed be the God of truth. <verse number="41" style="v" />And with that he held his tongue. And all the people then shouted, and said, Great is truth, and strong above all things.</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="42" style="v" />Then said the king to him, Ask what you will more than is appointed in writing, and we will give it you, inasmuch as you are found wisest; and you shall sit next me, and shall be called my cousin. <verse number="43" style="v" />Then said he to the king, Remember your vow, which you did vow to build Jerusalem, in the day when you came to your kingdom, <verse number="44" style="v" />and to send away all the vessels that were taken out of Jerusalem, which Cyrus set apart, when he vowed to destroy Babylon, and vowed to send them again there. <verse number="45" style="v" />You did also vow to build up the temple, which the Edomites burnt when Judea was made desolate by the Chaldeans. <verse number="46" style="v" />And now, O lord the king, this is that which I require, and which I desire of you, and this is the princely generosity that shall proceed from you: I pray therefore that you make good the vow, the performance whereof you have vowed to the King of heaven with your own mouth.</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="47" style="v" />Then Darius the king stood up, and kissed him, and wrote letters for him to all the treasurers and governors and captains and local governors, that they should safely bring on their way both him, and all those that should go up with him to build Jerusalem. <verse number="48" style="v" />He wrote letters also to all the governors that were in Coelesyria and Phoenicia, and to them in Libanus, that they should bring cedar wood from Libanus to Jerusalem, and that they should build the city with him. <verse number="49" style="v" />Moreover he wrote for all the Jews that should go out of his realm up into Jewry, concerning their freedom, that no officer, no governor, no local governor, nor treasurer, should forcibly enter into their doors; <verse number="50" style="v" />and that all the country which they occupied should be free to them without tribute; and that the Edomites should give over the villages of the Jews which then they held: <verse number="51" style="v" />and that there should be yearly given twenty talents to the building of the temple, until the time that it were built; <verse number="52" style="v" />and other ten talents yearly, for burnt offerings to be presented upon the altar every day, as they had a commandment to offer seventeen: <verse number="53" style="v" />and that all those who should come from Babylonia to build the city should have their freedom, as well they as their posterity, and all the priests that came. <verse number="54" style="v" />He wrote also <char style="add">to give them</char> their charges, and the priests’ vestments wherein they minister; <verse number="55" style="v" />and for the Levites he wrote that their charges should be given them until the day that the house were finished, and Jerusalem built up. <verse number="56" style="v" />And he commanded to give to all that kept the city lands and wages. <verse number="57" style="v" />He sent away also all the vessels from Babylon, that Cyrus had set apart; and all that Cyrus had given in commandment, he charged also to be done, and sent to Jerusalem.</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="58" style="v" />Now when this young man was gone forth, he lifted up his face to heaven towards Jerusalem, and praised the King of heaven, <verse number="59" style="v" />and said, From you comes victory, from you comes wisdom, and your is the glory, and I am your servant. <verse number="60" style="v" />Blessed are you, who have given me wisdom: and to you I give thanks, O Lord of our fathers. <verse number="61" style="v" />And so he took the letters, and went out, and came to Babylon, and told it all his kindred. <verse number="62" style="v" />And they praised the God of their fathers, because he had given them freedom and liberty <verse number="63" style="v" />to go up, and to build Jerusalem, and the temple which is called by his name: and they feasted with instruments of music and gladness seven days.</para>
  <chapter number="5" style="c" />
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="1" style="v" />After this were the chiefs of fathers’ houses chosen to go up according to their tribes, with their wives and sons and daughters, with their menservants and maidservants, and their cattle. <verse number="2" style="v" />And Darius sent with them a thousand horsemen, till they had brought them back to Jerusalem<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">5:2 </char><char style="ft" closed="false">Gr. </char><char style="fqa" closed="false">with peace.</char></note> safely, and with musical instruments, tabrets and flutes. <verse number="3" style="v" />And all their kindred played, and he made them go up together with them.</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="4" style="v" />And these are the names of the men which went up, according to their families amongst their tribes, after their several divisions. <verse number="5" style="v" />The priests, the sons of Phinees, the sons of Aaron: Jesus the son of Josedek, the son of Saraias, and Joakim the son of Zorobabel, the son of Salathiel, of the house of David, of the lineage of Phares, of the tribe of Judah; <verse number="6" style="v" />who spoke wise sentences before Darius the king of Persia in the second year of his reign, in the month Nisan, which is the first month. <verse number="7" style="v" /><note caller="+" style="x"><char style="xo" closed="false">5:7 </char><char style="xt" closed="false"><ref loc="EZR 2:1">Ezra 2:1</ref></char></note> And these are they of Jewry that came up from the captivity, where they lived as strangers, whom Nabuchodonosor the king of Babylon had carried away to Babylon. <verse number="8" style="v" />And they returned to Jerusalem, and to the other parts of Jewry, every man to his own city, who came with Zorobabel, with Jesus, Nehemias, <char style="add">and</char><note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">5:8 </char><char style="fqa" closed="false">Seralah.</char></note> Zaraias, Resaias,<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">5:8 </char><char style="ft" closed="false">Or, </char><char style="fqa" closed="false">Enenis.</char></note> Eneneus, Mardocheus, Beelsarus,<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">5:8 </char><char style="fqa" closed="false">Mispar.</char></note> Aspharsus,<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">5:8 </char><char style="fqa" closed="false">Reclaiah</char></note> Reelias, Roimus, <char style="add">and</char> Baana, their leaders. <verse number="9" style="v" />The number of them of the nation, and their leaders: the sons of<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">5:9 </char><char style="fqa" closed="false">Parosh.</char></note> Phoros, two thousand a hundred and seventy and two: the sons of<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">5:9 </char><char style="fqa" closed="false">Shephatiah.</char></note> Saphat, four hundred and seventy and two: <verse number="10" style="v" />the sons of<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">5:10 </char><char style="fqa" closed="false">Arah.</char></note> Ares, seven hundred and fifty and six: <verse number="11" style="v" />the sons of<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">5:11 </char><char style="fqa" closed="false">Pahath-moab.</char></note> Phaath Moab, of the sons of Jesus and Joab, two thousand and eight hundred and twelve: <verse number="12" style="v" />the sons of Elam, a thousand and two hundred and fifty and four: the sons of<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">5:12 </char><char style="fqa" closed="false">Zattu.</char></note> Zathui, nine hundred and forty and five: the sons of<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">5:12 </char><char style="fqa" closed="false">Zaccai.</char></note> Chorbe, seven hundred and five: the sons of Bani, six hundred and forty and eight: <verse number="13" style="v" />the sons of Bebai, six hundred and twenty and three: the sons of<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">5:13 </char><char style="fqa" closed="false">Asgad.</char></note> Astad,<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">5:13 </char><char style="ft" closed="false">According to other readings, 3622, or 3222.</char></note> a thousand and three hundred and twenty and two: <verse number="14" style="v" />the sons of Adonikam, six hundred and sixty and seven: the sons of<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">5:14 </char><char style="fqa" closed="false">Bigvai.</char></note> Bagoi, two thousand and sixty and six: the sons of<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">5:14 </char><char style="fqa" closed="false">Adin.</char></note> Adinu, four hundred and fifty and four: <verse number="15" style="v" />the sons of<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">5:15 </char><char style="fqa" closed="false">Ater of Hezekiah.</char></note> Ater, of Ezekias, ninety and two: the sons of Kilan and Azetas, three score and seven: the sons of<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">5:15 </char><char style="ft" closed="false">Another reading is, </char><char style="fqa" closed="false">Azuru.</char></note> Azaru, four hundred and thirty and two: <verse number="16" style="v" />the sons of<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">5:16 </char><char style="ft" closed="false">Another reading is, </char><char style="fqa" closed="false">Annias.</char></note> Annis, a hundred and one: the sons of Arom: the sons of<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">5:16 </char><char style="fqa" closed="false">Bezai.</char></note> Bassai, three hundred and twenty and three: the sons of Arsiphurith, a hundred and twelve: <verse number="17" style="v" />the sons of Baiterus, three thousand and five: the sons of<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">5:17 </char><char style="fqa" closed="false">Bethlehem.</char></note> Bethlomon, a hundred and twenty and three: <verse number="18" style="v" />they of Netophas, fifty and five: they of Anathoth, a hundred and fifty and eight: they of<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">5:18 </char><char style="fqa" closed="false">Azmaveth.</char></note> Bethasmoth, forty and two: <verse number="19" style="v" />they of<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">5:19 </char><char style="fqa" closed="false">Kiriath-arim</char></note> or<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">5:19 </char><char style="fqa" closed="false">Kiriath-jearim.</char></note> Kariathiarius, twenty and five: they of Caphira and Beroth, seven hundred and forty and three: <verse number="20" style="v" />the Chadiasai and Ammidioi, four hundred and twenty and two: they of<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">5:20 </char><char style="fqa" closed="false">Rumah.</char></note> Kirama and<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">5:20 </char><char style="fqa" closed="false">Geba.</char></note> Gabbe, six hundred and twenty and one: <verse number="21" style="v" />they of<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">5:21 </char><char style="fqa" closed="false">Michmas.</char></note> Macalon, a hundred and twenty and two: they of<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">5:21 </char><char style="fqa" closed="false">Bethel.</char></note> Betolion, fifty and two: the sons of<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">5:21 </char><char style="fqa" closed="false">Magbish</char></note> Niphis, a hundred and fifty and six: <verse number="22" style="v" />the sons of<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">5:22 </char><char style="fqa" closed="false">Lod, Hadid.</char></note> Calamolalus and<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">5:22 </char><char style="fqa" closed="false">Ono.</char></note> Onus, seven hundred and twenty and five: the sons of<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">5:22 </char><char style="fqa" closed="false">Jericho.</char></note> Jerechu,<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">5:22 </char><char style="ft" closed="false">Another reading is, </char><char style="fqa" closed="false">two</char></note> three hundred and forty and five: <verse number="23" style="v" />the sons of<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">5:23 </char><char style="fqa" closed="false">Senaah.</char></note> Sanaas, three thousand and three hundred and<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">5:23 </char><char style="ft" closed="false">Another reading is, </char><char style="fqa" closed="false">one.</char></note> thirty. <verse number="24" style="v" />The priests: the sons of<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">5:24 </char><char style="fqa" closed="false">Jedaiah.</char></note> Jeddu, the son of Jesus, amongst the sons of Sanasib,<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">5:24 </char><char style="ft" closed="false">Another reading is, </char><char style="fqa" closed="false">eight</char></note> nine hundred and seventy and two: the sons of<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">5:24 </char><char style="fqa" closed="false">Immer.</char></note> Emmeruth,<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">5:24 </char><char style="ft" closed="false">Another reading is, </char><char style="fqa" closed="false">two hundred.</char></note> a thousand and fifty and two: <verse number="25" style="v" />the sons of<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">5:25 </char><char style="fqa" closed="false">Pashhur.</char></note> Phassurus, a thousand and two hundred and forty and seven: the sons of<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">5:25 </char><char style="fqa" closed="false">Harim.</char></note> Charme,<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">5:25 </char><char style="ft" closed="false">Another reading is, </char><char style="fqa" closed="false">two hundred</char></note> a thousand and seventeen. <verse number="26" style="v" />The Levites: the sons of Jesus, and Kadmiel, and Bannas, and Sudias, seventy and four. <verse number="27" style="v" />The holy singers: the sons of Asaph, a hundred<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">5:27 </char><char style="ft" closed="false">Another reading is, </char><char style="fqa" closed="false">forty</char></note> twenty and eight. <verse number="28" style="v" />The gatekeepers: the sons of<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">5:28 </char><char style="fqa" closed="false">Shallum.</char></note> Salum, the sons of<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">5:28 </char><char style="fqa" closed="false">Ater.</char></note> Atar, the sons of Tolman, the sons of<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">5:28 </char><char style="fqa" closed="false">Akkub.</char></note> Dacubi, the sons of<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">5:28 </char><char style="fqa" closed="false">Hatita.</char></note> Ateta, the sons of<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">5:28 </char><char style="fqa" closed="false">Shobai.</char></note> Sabi, in all a hundred and thirty and nine. <verse number="29" style="v" />The temple servants: the sons of<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">5:29 </char><char style="fqa" closed="false">Ziha.</char></note> Esau, the sons of<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">5:29 </char><char style="fqa" closed="false">Hasupha.</char></note> Asipha, the sons of Tabaoth, the sons of<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">5:29 </char><char style="fqa" closed="false">Keros.</char></note> Keras, the sons of<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">5:29 </char><char style="fqa" closed="false">Siaha.</char></note> Sua, the sons of<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">5:29 </char><char style="fqa" closed="false">Padon.</char></note> Phaleas, the sons of Labana, the sons of<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">5:29 </char><char style="fqa" closed="false">Hagaba.</char></note> Aggaba. <verse number="30" style="v" />the sons of<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">5:30 </char><char style="fqa" closed="false">Akkub.</char></note> Acud, the sons of Uta, the sons of Ketab, the sons of<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">5:30 </char><char style="fqa" closed="false">Hagab.</char></note> Accaba, the sons of<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">5:30 </char><char style="fqa" closed="false">Shamlai.</char></note> Subai, the sons of<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">5:30 </char><char style="fqa" closed="false">Hanan.</char></note> Anan, the sons of<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">5:30 </char><char style="fqa" closed="false">Giddel.</char></note> Cathua, the sons of<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">5:30 </char><char style="fqa" closed="false">Gahar</char></note> Geddur, <verse number="31" style="v" />the sons of<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">5:31 </char><char style="fqa" closed="false">Reaiah.</char></note> Jairus, the sons of<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">5:31 </char><char style="fqa" closed="false">Rezin.</char></note> Daisan, the sons of<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">5:31 </char><char style="fqa" closed="false">Nekoda.</char></note> Noeba, the sons of Chaseba, the sons of<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">5:31 </char><char style="fqa" closed="false">Gazzam.</char></note> Gazera, the sons of<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">5:31 </char><char style="fqa" closed="false">Uzza.</char></note> Ozias, the sons of<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">5:31 </char><char style="fqa" closed="false">Paseah.</char></note> Phinoe, the sons of Asara, the sons of<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">5:31 </char><char style="fqa" closed="false">Besai.</char></note> Basthai, the sons of<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">5:31 </char><char style="fqa" closed="false">Asnah.</char></note> Asana, the sons of<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">5:31 </char><char style="fqa" closed="false">Meunim.</char></note> Maani, the sons of<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">5:31 </char><char style="fqa" closed="false">Nephisim.</char></note> Naphisi, the sons of<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">5:31 </char><char style="fqa" closed="false">Bakbuk. </char><char style="ft" closed="false">According to other readings, </char><char style="fqa" closed="false">Acum, </char><char style="ft" closed="false">or </char><char style="fqa" closed="false">Acuph.</char></note> Acub, the sons of<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">5:31 </char><char style="fqa" closed="false">Hakupha.</char></note> Achipha, the sons of<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">5:31 </char><char style="fqa" closed="false">Harhur.</char></note> Asur, the sons of Pharakim, the sons of<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">5:31 </char><char style="fqa" closed="false">Bazluth.</char></note> Basaloth, <verse number="32" style="v" />the sons of<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">5:32 </char><char style="fqa" closed="false">Mehida.</char></note> Meedda, the sons of Cutha, the sons of<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">5:32 </char><char style="fqa" closed="false">Harsha</char></note> Charea, the sons of<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">5:32 </char><char style="fqa" closed="false">Barkos.</char></note> Barchus, the sons of<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">5:32 </char><char style="fqa" closed="false">Sisera.</char></note> Serar, the sons of<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">5:32 </char><char style="fqa" closed="false">Temah</char></note> Thomei, the sons of<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">5:32 </char><char style="fqa" closed="false">Neziah. </char><char style="ft" closed="false">Another reading is, </char><char style="fqa" closed="false">Nasith.</char></note> Nasi, the sons of Atipha. <verse number="33" style="v" />The sons of the servants of Solomon: the sons of<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">5:33 </char><char style="fqa" closed="false">Hussophereth.</char></note> Assaphioth, the sons of<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">5:33 </char><char style="fqa" closed="false">Peruda.</char></note> Pharida, the sons of<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">5:33 </char><char style="fqa" closed="false">Jaalah.</char></note> Jeeli, the sons of<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">5:33 </char><char style="fqa" closed="false">Darkon.</char></note> Lozon, the sons of<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">5:33 </char><char style="fqa" closed="false">Giddel.</char></note> Isdael, the sons of<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">5:33 </char><char style="fqa" closed="false">Shephatia.</char></note> Saphuthi, <verse number="34" style="v" />the sons of<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">5:34 </char><char style="fqa" closed="false">Hattil.</char></note> Agia, the sons of<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">5:34 </char><char style="fqa" closed="false">Pochereth-haz-zebaim, </char><char style="ft" closed="false">Ezra 2:57.</char></note> Phacareth, the sons of Sabie, the sons of Sarothie, the sons of<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">5:34 </char><char style="ft" closed="false">Another reading is, </char><char style="fqa" closed="false">Misaias.</char></note> Masias, the sons of Gas, the sons of Addus, the sons of Subas, the sons of Apherra, the sons of Barodis, the sons of Saphat, the sons of Allon. <verse number="35" style="v" />All the temple-servants, and the sons of the servants of Solomon, were three hundred and seventy and two. <verse number="36" style="v" />These came up from<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">5:36 </char><char style="fqa" closed="false">Telmelah.</char></note> Thermeleth, and<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">5:36 </char><char style="fqa" closed="false">Telharsha.</char></note> Thelersas,<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">5:36 </char><char style="fqa" closed="false">Cherub. Addan.</char></note> Charaathalan leading them, and Allar; <verse number="37" style="v" />and they could not show their families, nor their stock, how they were of Israel: the sons of<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">5:37 </char><char style="fqa" closed="false">Delaiah. </char><char style="ft" closed="false">Another reading is, </char><char style="fqa" closed="false">Asan.</char></note> Dalan the son of<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">5:37 </char><char style="fqa" closed="false">Tobiah </char><char style="ft" closed="false">Another reading is, </char><char style="fqa" closed="false">Baenan.</char></note> Ban, the sons of<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">5:37 </char><char style="fqa" closed="false">Nekoda.</char></note> Nekodan, six hundred and fifty and two. <verse number="38" style="v" />And of the priests, those who usurped the office of the priesthood and were not found: the sons of<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">5:38 </char><char style="fqa" closed="false">Habaiah, </char><char style="ft" closed="false">or </char><char style="fqa" closed="false">Hobaiah.</char></note> Obdia, the sons of<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">5:38 </char><char style="fqa" closed="false">Hakkoz.</char></note> Akkos, the sons of Jaddus, who married Augia one of the daughters of<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">5:38 </char><char style="fqa" closed="false">Barzillai. </char><char style="ft" closed="false">Another reading is, </char><char style="fqa" closed="false">Phaezeldaeus.</char></note> Zorzelleus, and was called after his name. <verse number="39" style="v" />And when the description of the kindred of these men was sought in the register, and was not found, they were removed from executing the office of the priesthood: <verse number="40" style="v" />for to them said Nehemias and Attharias, that they should not be partakers of the holy things, till there arose up a high priest wearing<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">5:40 </char><char style="ft" closed="false">Gr. </char><char style="fqa" closed="false">the manifestation and truth.</char></note> Urim and Thummim. <verse number="41" style="v" />So all they of Israel, from twelve years old <char style="add">and upward,</char> beside menservants and women servants, were <char style="add">in number</char> forty and two thousand and three hundred and sixty. <verse number="42" style="v" />Their menservants and handmaids were seven thousand and three hundred and thirty and seven: the minstrels and singers, two hundred and forty and five: <verse number="43" style="v" />four hundred and thirty and five camels, seven<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">5:43 </char><char style="ft" closed="false">Another reading is, </char><char style="fqa" closed="false">hundred.</char></note> thousand and thirty and six horses, two hundred and forty and five mules, five thousand and five hundred and twenty and five beasts of burden. <verse number="44" style="v" />And certain of the chief men of their families, when they came to the temple of God that is in Jerusalem, vowed to set up the house again in its own place according to their ability, <verse number="45" style="v" />and to give into the holy treasury of the works a thousand pounds of gold, five thousand of silver, and a hundred priestly vestments. <verse number="46" style="v" />And the priests and the Levites and those who were of the people lived in Jerusalem and the country; the holy singers also and the gatekeepers and all Israel in their villages.</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="47" style="v" />But when the seventh month was at hand, and when the children of Israel were every man in his own place, they came all together with one consent into the broad place before the first porch which is towards the east. <verse number="48" style="v" />Then stood up Jesus the son of Josedek, and his kindred the priests, and Zorobabel the son of Salathiel, and his kindred, and made ready the altar of the God of Israel, <verse number="49" style="v" />to offer burnt sacrifices upon it, according as it is expressly commanded in the book of Moses the man of God. <verse number="50" style="v" />And certain were gathered to them out of the other nations of the land, and they erected the altar upon its own place, because all the nations of the land were at enmity with them, and oppressed them; and they offered sacrifices according to the time, and burnt offerings to the Lord both morning and evening. <verse number="51" style="v" />Also they held the feast of tabernacles, as it is commanded in the law, and <char style="add">offered</char> sacrifices daily, as was meet: <verse number="52" style="v" />and after that, the continual oblations, and the sacrifices of the Sabbaths, and of the new moons, and of all the consecrated feasts. <verse number="53" style="v" />And all those who had made any vow to God began to offer sacrifices to God from the new moon of the<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">5:53 </char><char style="ft" closed="false">Another reading is, </char><char style="fqa" closed="false">first.</char></note> seventh month, although the temple of God was not yet built. <verse number="54" style="v" />And they gave money to the masons and carpenters; and meat and drink, <verse number="55" style="v" />and cars to them of Sidon and Tyre, that they should bring cedar trees from Libanus, <char style="add">and</char> convey them in floats to the haven of Joppa, according to the commandment which was written for them by Cyrus king of the Persians. <verse number="56" style="v" />And in the second year after his coming to the temple of God at Jerusalem, in the second month, began Zorobabel the son of Salathiel, and Jesus the son of Josedek, and their kindred, and the Levitical priests, and all those who were come to Jerusalem out of the captivity: <verse number="57" style="v" />and they laid the foundation of the temple of God on the new moon of the second month, in the second year after they were come to Jewry and Jerusalem. <verse number="58" style="v" /><note caller="+" style="x"><char style="xo" closed="false">5:58 </char><char style="xt" closed="false"><ref loc="EZR 3:8-9">Ezra 3:8-9</ref></char></note> And they appointed the Levites from twenty years old over the works of the Lord. Then stood up Jesus, and his sons and kindred, and Kadmiel his brother, and the sons of Jesus, Emadabun, and the sons of Joda the son of Iliadun, and their sons and kindred, all the Levites, with one accord started the business, labouring to advance the works in the house of God. So the builders built the temple of the Lord. <verse number="59" style="v" />And the priests stood arrayed in their vestments with musical instruments and trumpets, and the Levites the sons of Asaph with their cymbals, <verse number="60" style="v" />singing songs of thanksgiving, and praising the Lord, after the order of David king of Israel. <verse number="61" style="v" />And they sang aloud, praising the Lord in songs of thanksgiving, because his goodness and his glory are forever in all Israel. <verse number="62" style="v" />And all the people sounded trumpets, and shouted with a loud voice, singing songs of thanksgiving to the Lord for the rearing up of the house of the Lord. <verse number="63" style="v" /><note caller="+" style="x"><char style="xo" closed="false">5:63 </char><char style="xt" closed="false"><ref loc="EZR 3:12-13">Ezra 3:12-13</ref></char></note> Also of the Levitical priests, and of the heads of their families, the ancients who had seen the former house came to the building of this with lamentation and great weeping. <verse number="64" style="v" />But many with trumpets and joy <char style="add">shouted</char> with loud voice, <verse number="65" style="v" />insomuch that the people heard not the trumpets for the weeping of the people: for the multitude sounded marvellously, so that it was heard afar off.</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="66" style="v" />
    <note caller="+" style="x">
      <char style="xo" closed="false">5:66 </char>
      <char style="xt" closed="false">
        <ref loc="EZR 4:1">Ezra 4:1</ref>
      </char>
    </note> Wherefore when the enemies of the tribe of Judah and Benjamin heard it, they came to know what that noise of trumpets should mean. <verse number="67" style="v" />And they perceived that those who were of the captivity did build the temple to the Lord, the God of Israel. <verse number="68" style="v" />So they went to Zorobabel and Jesus, and to the chief men of the families, and said to them, we will build together with you. <verse number="69" style="v" />For we likewise, as you°, do obey your Lord, and do sacrifice to him from the days of<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">5:69 </char><char style="ft" closed="false">Another reading is, </char><char style="fqa" closed="false">Asbacaphath.</char></note> Asbasareth the king of the Assyrians, who brought us here. <verse number="70" style="v" />Then Zorobabel and Jesus and the chief men of the families of Israel said to them, It is not<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">5:70 </char><char style="ft" closed="false">Another reading is, </char><char style="fqa" closed="false">for us and you.</char></note> for you to build the house to the Lord our God. <verse number="71" style="v" />We ourselves alone will build to the Lord of Israel, according as Cyrus the king of the Persians has commanded us. <verse number="72" style="v" />But the heathen of the land lying heavy upon the inhabitants of Judea, and<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">5:72 </char><char style="ft" closed="false">Or, </char><char style="fqa" closed="false">besieging them</char></note> holding them strait, hindered their building; <verse number="73" style="v" />and<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">5:73 </char><char style="ft" closed="false">Another reading is, </char><char style="fqa" closed="false">leading the people astray in counsel, and raising commotions.</char></note> by their secret plots, and popular persuasions and commotions, they hindered the finishing of the building all the time that King Cyrus lived: so they were hindered from building for the space of two years, until the reign of Darius.</para>
  <chapter number="6" style="c" />
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="1" style="v" />Now <note caller="+" style="x"><char style="xo" closed="false">6:1 </char><char style="xt" closed="false"><ref loc="EZR 4:24">Ezra 4:24</ref>; <ref loc="EZR 5:1">5:1</ref></char></note> in the second year of the reign of Darius, Aggaeus and Zacharius the son of<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">6:1 </char><char style="fqa" closed="false">Iddo. </char><char style="ft" closed="false">Another reading is, </char><char style="fqa" closed="false">Eddin</char></note> Addo, the prophets, prophesied to the Jews in Jewry and Jerusalem; in the name of the Lord, the God of Israel, <char style="add">prophesied they</char> to them. <verse number="2" style="v" />Then stood up Zorobabel the son of Salathiel, and Jesus the son of Josedek, and began to build the house of the Lord at Jerusalem, the prophets of the Lord being with them, <char style="add">and</char> helping them. <verse number="3" style="v" /><note caller="+" style="x"><char style="xo" closed="false">6:3 </char><char style="xt" closed="false"><ref loc="EZR 5:3">Ezra 5:3</ref></char></note> At the same time came to them<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">6:3 </char><char style="fqa" closed="false">Tattenai.</char></note> Sisinnes the governor of Syria and Phoenicia, with<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">6:3 </char><char style="fqa" closed="false">Shetharbozenai</char></note> Sathrabuzanes and his companions, and said to them, <verse number="4" style="v" />By whose appointment do you° build this house and this roof, and perform all the other things? and who are the builders that perform these things? <verse number="5" style="v" />Nevertheless the elders of the Jews obtained favour, because the Lord had visited the captivity; <verse number="6" style="v" />and they were not hindered from building, until such time as communication was made to Darius concerning them, and his answer signified.</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="7" style="v" />The copy of the letter which Sisinnes, governor of Syria and Phoenicia, and Sathrabuzanes, with their companions, the rulers in Syria and Phoenicia, wrote and sent to Darius; <verse number="8" style="v" />To king Darius, greeting: Let all things be known to our lord the king, that being come into the country of Judea, and entered into the city of Jerusalem, we found in the city of Jerusalem the elders of the Jews that were of the captivity <verse number="9" style="v" />building a house to the Lord, great <char style="add">and</char> new, of hewn and costly stones, with timber laid in the walls. <verse number="10" style="v" />And those works are done with great speed, and the work goes on prosperously in their hands, and with all glory and diligence it is accomplished. <verse number="11" style="v" />Then asked we these elders, saying, By whose commandment build you° this house, and lay the foundations of these works? <verse number="12" style="v" />Therefore, to the intent that we might give knowledge to you by writing who were the chief doers, we questioned them, and we required of them the names in writing of their principal men. <verse number="13" style="v" />So they gave us this answer, We are the servants of the Lord which made heaven and earth. <verse number="14" style="v" />And as for this house, it was built many years ago by a king of Israel great and strong, and was finished. <verse number="15" style="v" />But when our fathers sinned against the Lord of Israel which is in heaven, and provoked him to wrath, he gave them over into the hands of Nabuchodonosor king of Babylon, king of the Chaldeans; <verse number="16" style="v" />and they pulled down the house, and burnt it, and carried away the people captives to Babylon. <verse number="17" style="v" />But in the first year that Cyrus reigned over the country of Babylon, king Cyrus wrote to build up this house. <verse number="18" style="v" />And the holy vessels of gold and of silver, that Nabuchodonosor had carried away out of the house at Jerusalem, and had set up in his own temple, those Cyrus the king brought forth again out of the temple in Babylonia, and they were delivered to Zorobabel and to<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">6:18 </char><char style="ft" closed="false">Another reading is, </char><char style="fqa" closed="false">Sabunassarus.</char></note> Sanabassarus the governor, <verse number="19" style="v" />with commandment that he should carry away<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">6:19 </char><char style="ft" closed="false">Another reading is, </char><char style="fqa" closed="false">the same.</char></note> all these vessels, and put them in the temple at Jerusalem; and that the temple of the Lord should be built in its place. <verse number="20" style="v" />Then Sanabassarus, being come here, laid the foundations of the house of the Lord which is in Jerusalem; and from that time to this being still a building, it is not yet fully ended. <verse number="21" style="v" />Now therefore, if it seem good, O king, let search be made amongst the royal archives of our lord the king that are in Babylon: <verse number="22" style="v" />and if it be found that the building of the house of the Lord which is in Jerusalem has been done with the consent of king Cyrus, and it seem good to our lord the king, let him signify to us thereof.</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="23" style="v" />
    <note caller="+" style="x">
      <char style="xo" closed="false">6:23 </char>
      <char style="xt" closed="false">
        <ref loc="EZR 6:1">Ezra 6:1</ref>
      </char>
    </note> Then commanded King Darius to seek amongst the archives that were laid up at Babylon: and so at Ekbatana the palace, which is in the country of Media, there was found a<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">6:23 </char><char style="ft" closed="false">Another reading is, </char><char style="fqa" closed="false">place.</char></note> scroll where these things were recorded. <verse number="24" style="v" />In the first year of the reign of Cyrus king Cyrus commanded to build up the house of the Lord which is in Jerusalem, where they do sacrifice with continual fire: <verse number="25" style="v" />whose height shall be sixty cubits, and the breadth sixty cubits, with three rows of hewn stones, and one row of new wood of that country; and the expenses thereof to be given out of the house of king Cyrus: <verse number="26" style="v" />and that the holy vessels of the house of the Lord, both gold and silver, that Nabuchodonosor took out of the house at Jerusalem, and carried away to Babylon, should be restored to the house at Jerusalem, and be set in the place where they were before. <verse number="27" style="v" />And also he commanded that Sisinnes the governor of Syria and Phoenicia, and Sathrabuzanes, and their companions, and those which were appointed rulers in Syria and Phoenicia, should be careful not to meddle with the place, but suffer Zorobabel, the servant of the Lord, and governor of Judea, and the elders of the Jews, to build that house of the Lord in its place. <verse number="28" style="v" />And I also do command to have it built up whole again; and that they look diligently to help those that be of the captivity of Judea, till the house of the Lord be finished: <verse number="29" style="v" />and that out of the tribute of Coelesyria and Phoenicia a portion be carefully given these men for the sacrifices of the Lord, <char style="add">that is,</char> to Zorobabel the governor, for bullocks, and rams, and lambs; <verse number="30" style="v" />and also corn, salt, wine and oil, and that continually every year without further question, according as the priests that be in Jerusalem shall signify to be daily spent: <verse number="31" style="v" />that drink offerings may be made to the Most High God for the king and for his children, and that they may pray for their lives. <verse number="32" style="v" />And that commandment be given that whoever shall transgress, yes, or neglect anything<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">6:32 </char><char style="ft" closed="false">ft Another reading is, </char><char style="fqa" closed="false">before spoken or written.</char></note> written here, out of his own <char style="add">house</char> shall a tree be taken, and he be hanged on it, and all his goods seized for the king. <verse number="33" style="v" />The Lord therefore, whose name is there called upon, utterly destroy every king and nation, that shall stretch out his hand to hinder or endamage that house of the Lord in Jerusalem. <verse number="34" style="v" />I Darius the king have ordained that according to these things it be done with diligence.</para>
  <chapter number="7" style="c" />
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="1" style="v" />Then <note caller="+" style="x"><char style="xo" closed="false">7:1 </char><char style="xt" closed="false"><ref loc="EZR 6:13">Ezra 6:13</ref></char></note> Sisinnes the governor of Coelesyria and Phoenicia, and Sathrabuzanes, with their companions, following the commandments of king Darius, <verse number="2" style="v" />did very carefully oversee the holy works, assisting the elders of the Jews and rulers of the temple. <verse number="3" style="v" />And so the holy works prospered, while Aggaeus and Zacharias the prophets prophesied. <verse number="4" style="v" />And they finished these things by the commandment of the Lord, the God of Israel, and with the consent of Cyrus, Darius, and Artaxerxes, kings of the Persians. <verse number="5" style="v" /><char style="add">And thus</char> was<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">7:5 </char><char style="ft" closed="false">Another reading is, </char><char style="fqa" closed="false">the holy house.</char></note> the house finished by the three and twentieth day of the month Adar, in the sixth year of king Darius. <verse number="6" style="v" />And the children of Israel, the priests, and the Levites, and the other that were of the captivity, that were added <char style="add">to them,</char> did according to the things <char style="add">written</char> in the book of Moses. <verse number="7" style="v" />And to the dedication of the temple of the Lord they offered a hundred bullocks, two hundred rams, four hundred lambs; <verse number="8" style="v" /><char style="add">and</char> twelve he-goats for the sin of all Israel, according to the number of the twelve<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">7:8 </char><char style="ft" closed="false">Another reading is, </char><char style="fqa" closed="false">tribes of Israel.</char></note> princes of the tribes of Israel. <verse number="9" style="v" />The priests also and the Levites stood arrayed in their vestments, according to their kindred, for the services of the Lord, the God of Israel, according to the book of Moses: and the gatekeepers at every gate.</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="10" style="v" />And the children of Israel that came out of the captivity held the Passover the fourteenth day of the first month, when the priests and the Levites were sanctified together, <verse number="11" style="v" /><note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">7:11 </char><char style="ft" closed="false">Another reading is, </char><char style="fqa" closed="false">And those who were of the captivity were not all sanctified together: but the Levites were all sanctified together. And etc.</char></note> and all those who were of the captivity; for they were sanctified. For the Levites were all sanctified together, <verse number="12" style="v" />and they offered the Passover for all them of the captivity, and for their kindred the priests, and for themselves. <verse number="13" style="v" />And the children of Israel that came out of the captivity did eat, even all those who had separated themselves from the abominations of the heathen of the land, and sought the Lord. <verse number="14" style="v" />And they kept the feast of unleavened bread seven days, making merry before the Lord, <verse number="15" style="v" />for that he had turned the counsel of the king of Assyria towards them, to strengthen their hands in the works of the Lord, the God of Israel.</para>
  <chapter number="8" style="c" />
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="1" style="v" />
    <note caller="+" style="x">
      <char style="xo" closed="false">8:1 </char>
      <char style="xt" closed="false">
        <ref loc="EZR 7:1">Ezra 7:1</ref>
      </char>
    </note> And after these things, when Artaxerxes the king of the Persians reigned, came Esdras the son of Azaraias, the son of Zechrias, the son of Helkias, the son of Salem, <verse number="2" style="v" />the son of Sadduk, the son of Ahitob, the son of Amarias, the son of Ozias,<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">8:2 </char><char style="ft" closed="false">The Vatican MS. omits </char><char style="fq" closed="false">the son of Memeroth, the son of Zaraias, the son of Savias.</char></note> the son of Memeroth, the son of Zaraias, the son of Savias, the son of Boccas, the son of Abisne, the son of Phinees, the son of Eleazar, the son of Aaron, the chief priest. <verse number="3" style="v" />This Esdras went up from Babylon, as being a ready scribe in the law of Moses, that was given by the God of Israel. <verse number="4" style="v" />And the king did him honour: for he found grace in his sight in all his requests. <verse number="5" style="v" />There went up with him also certain of the children of Israel, and of the priests, and Levites, and holy singers, and gatekeepers, and<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">8:5 </char><char style="ft" closed="false">That is, </char><char style="fqa" closed="false">the temple servants.</char></note> temple servants, to Jerusalem, <verse number="6" style="v" />in the seventh year of the reign of Artaxerxes, in the fifth month, this was the king’s seventh year; for they went from Babylon on the new moon of the first month, and came to Jerusalem, according to the prosperous journey which the Lord gave them<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">8:6 </char><char style="ft" closed="false">Some MSS. omit </char><char style="fq" closed="false">for his sake.</char></note> for his sake. <verse number="7" style="v" />For Esdras had very great skill, so that he omitted nothing of the law and commandments of the Lord, <char style="add">but</char> taught all Israel the ordinances and judgements.</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="8" style="v" />Now the commission, which was written from Artaxerxes the king, came to Esdras the priest and reader of the law of the Lord, whereof this that follows is a copy; <verse number="9" style="v" />King Artaxerxes to Esdras the priest and reader of the law of the Lord, greeting: <verse number="10" style="v" />Having determined to deal graciously, I have given order, that such of the nation of the Jews, and of the priests and Levites,<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">8:10 </char><char style="ft" closed="false">Another reading is, </char><char style="fqa" closed="false">being within.</char></note> and of those within our realm, as are willing and desirous, should go with you to Jerusalem. <verse number="11" style="v" />As many therefore as have a mind <char style="add">thereto,</char> let them depart with you, as it has seemed good both to me and my seven friends the counsellors; <verse number="12" style="v" />that they may look to the affairs of Judea and Jerusalem, agreeably to that which is in the law of the Lord, <verse number="13" style="v" />and carry the gifts to the Lord of Israel to Jerusalem, which I and my friends have vowed; and that all the gold and silver that can be found in the country of Babylonia for the Lord in Jerusalem, <verse number="14" style="v" />with that also which is given of the people for the temple of the Lord their God that is at Jerusalem, be collected: even the gold and silver for bullocks, rams, and lambs, and things thereto appertaining; <verse number="15" style="v" />to the end that they may offer sacrifices to the Lord upon the altar of the Lord their God, which is in Jerusalem. <verse number="16" style="v" />And whatever you and your kindred are minded to do with gold and silver, that perform, according to the will of your God. <verse number="17" style="v" />And the holy vessels of the Lord, which are given you for the use of the temple of your God, which is in Jerusalem: <verse number="18" style="v" />and whatever thing else you shall remember for the use of the temple of your God, you shall give it out of the king’s treasury. <verse number="19" style="v" />And I king Artaxerxes have also commanded the keepers of the treasures in Syria and Phoenicia, that whatever Esdras the priest and reader of the law of the Most High God shall send for, they should give it him with all diligence, <verse number="20" style="v" />to the sum of a hundred talents of silver, likewise also of wheat even to a hundred<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">8:20 </char><char style="ft" closed="false">Gr. </char><char style="fqa" closed="false">cors.</char></note> measures, and a hundred firkins<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">8:20 </char><char style="ft" closed="false">a firkin is about 41 litres or 11 gallons.</char></note> of wine, and<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">8:20 </char><char style="ft" closed="false">So some authorities. See Ezra 7:22. The common reading is, </char><char style="fqa" closed="false">other things.</char></note> salt in abundance. <verse number="21" style="v" />Let all things be performed after the law of God diligently to the most high God, that wrath come not upon the kingdom of the king and his sons. <verse number="22" style="v" />I command you also, that no tax, nor any other imposition, be laid upon any of the priests, or Levites, or holy singers, or gatekeepers, or temple servants, or any that have employment in this temple, and that no man have authority to impose anything upon them. <verse number="23" style="v" />And you, Esdras, according to the wisdom of God ordain judges and justices, that they may judge in all Syria and Phoenicia all those that know the law of your God; and those that know it not you shall teach. <verse number="24" style="v" />And whoever shall transgress the law of your God, and of the king, shall be punished diligently, whether it be by death, or other punishment, by penalty of money, or by<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">8:24 </char><char style="ft" closed="false">Or. </char><char style="fqa" closed="false">captivity</char></note> imprisonment.</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="25" style="v" />Then said Esdras the scribe, Blessed be the only Lord, the God of my fathers, who has put these things into the heart of the king, to glorify his house that is in Jerusalem: <verse number="26" style="v" />and has honoured me in the sight of the king, and his counsellors, and all his friends and nobles. <verse number="27" style="v" />Therefore was I encouraged by the help of the Lord my God, and gathered together out of Israel men to go up with me. <verse number="28" style="v" />And these are the chief according to their families and the several divisions thereof, that went up with me from Babylon in the reign of king Artaxerxes: <verse number="29" style="v" />of the sons of Phinees, Gerson: of the sons of Ithamar, Gamael: of the sons of David,<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">8:29 </char><char style="fqa" closed="false">Hattush.</char></note> Attus<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">8:29 </char><char style="ft" closed="false">Ezra 8:3, </char><char style="fqa" closed="false">of the sons of Shecaniah; of the sons of Parosh.</char></note> the son of Sechenias: <verse number="30" style="v" />of the sons of Phoros, Zacharais; and with him were counted a hundred and fifty men: <verse number="31" style="v" />of the sons of Phaath Moab, Eliaonias the son of<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">8:31 </char><char style="fqa" closed="false">Zerehiah.</char></note> Zaraias, and with him two hundred men: <verse number="32" style="v" /><note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">8:32 </char><char style="ft" closed="false">Ezra 8:5, </char><char style="fqa" closed="false">of the sons of Shecaniah, the son of Jahaziel.</char></note> of the sons of Zathoes, Sechenias the son of Jezelus, and with him<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">8:32 </char><char style="ft" closed="false">Another reading is, </char><char style="fqa" closed="false">two</char></note> three hundred men: of the sons ofAdin, Obeth the son of Jonathan, and with him two hundred and fifty men: <verse number="33" style="v" />of the sons of Elam, Jesias son of <char style="add">Athaliah.</char> Gotholias, and with him seventy men: <verse number="34" style="v" />of the sons of Saphatias, <char style="add">Zebadiah.</char> Zaraias son of Michael, and with him threescore and ten men: <verse number="35" style="v" />of the sons of Joab, <char style="add">Obadiah.</char> Abadias son of <char style="add">Jehiel.</char> Jezelus, and with him two hundred and twelve men: <verse number="36" style="v" /><note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">8:36 </char><char style="ft" closed="false">Ezra 8:10, </char><char style="fqa" closed="false">of the sons of Shelomith, the son of Josiphiah.</char></note> of the sons of Banias, Salimoth son of Josaphias, and with him a hundred and threescore men: <verse number="37" style="v" />of the sons of Babi, Zacharias son of Bebai, and with him twenty and eight men: <verse number="38" style="v" />of the sons of <char style="add">Azgad.</char> Astath, Joannes son of <char style="add">Hakkatan</char> Akatan, and with him a hundred and ten men: <verse number="39" style="v" />of the sons of Adonikam, the last, and these are the names of them, Eliphalat, Jeuel, and <char style="add">Shemaiah.</char> Samaias, and with them seventy men: <verse number="40" style="v" />of the sons of <char style="add">Bigvai.</char> Bago, Uthi the son of Istalcurus, and with him seventy men.</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="41" style="v" />And I gathered them together to the river called Theras; and there we pitched our tents three days, and I surveyed them. <verse number="42" style="v" />But when I had found there none of the priests and Levites, <verse number="43" style="v" />then sent I to Eleazar, and <char style="add">Ariel</char> Iduel, and Maasmas, <verse number="44" style="v" />and Elnathan, and Samaias, and <char style="add">Jarib</char> Joribus, Nathan, Ennatan, Zacharias, and Mosollamus, principal men and men of understanding. <verse number="45" style="v" />And I bade those who they should go to <char style="add">Iddo</char> Loddeus the captain, who was in the place of <char style="add">Casiphia,</char> the treasury: <verse number="46" style="v" />and commanded them that they should speak to Loddeus, and to his kindred, and to the treasurers in that place, to send us such men as might execute the priests’ office in the house of our Lord. <verse number="47" style="v" />And by the mighty hand of our Lord they brought to us<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">8:47 </char><char style="ft" closed="false">Another reading is, </char><char style="fqa" closed="false">a man.</char></note> men of understanding of the sons of<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">8:47 </char><char style="fqa" closed="false">Mahli.</char></note> Mooli the son of Levi, the son of Israel,<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">8:47 </char><char style="fqa" closed="false">Sherebiah.</char></note> Asebebias, and his sons, and his kindred, who were eighteen, <verse number="48" style="v" />and<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">8:48 </char><char style="fqa" closed="false">Hashabiah.</char></note> Asebias, and Annuus, and Osaias his brother, of the sons of Chanuneus, and their sons were twenty men; <verse number="49" style="v" />and of the temple-servants whom David and the principal men had appointed for the servants of the Levites, two hundred and twenty temple-servants, the catalogue of all their names was showed. <verse number="50" style="v" />And there I vowed a fast for the young men before our Lord, to desire of him a prosperous journey both for us and for our children and cattle that were with us: <verse number="51" style="v" />for I was ashamed to ask of the king footmen, and horsemen, and conduct for protection against our adversaries. <verse number="52" style="v" />For we had said to the king, that the power of our Lord would be with those who seek him, to support them in all ways. <verse number="53" style="v" />And again we implored our lord as touching these things, and found him favourable <char style="add">to us. </char> <verse number="54" style="v" />Then I separated twelve men of the chiefs of the priests,<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">8:54 </char><char style="fqa" closed="false">Sherebiah, Hashabiah.</char></note> Eserebias, and Assamias, and ten men of their kindred with them: <verse number="55" style="v" />and I weighed them the silver, and the gold, and the holy vessels of the house of our Lord, which the king, and his counsellors, and the nobles, and all Israel, had given. <verse number="56" style="v" />And when I had weighed it, I delivered to them six hundred and fifty talents of silver, and silver vessels of a hundred talents, and a hundred talents of gold, <verse number="57" style="v" />and twenty golden vessels, and twelve vessels of brass, even of fine brass, glittering like gold. <verse number="58" style="v" />And I said to them, Both you° are holy to the Lord,<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">8:58 </char><char style="ft" closed="false">Another reading is, </char><char style="fqa" closed="false">and the holy vessels and the silver and the gold etc.</char></note> and the vessels are holy, and the gold and the silver are a vow to the Lord, the Lord of our fathers. <verse number="59" style="v" />Watch you°, and keep them till you° deliver them to the chiefs of the priests and Levites, and to the principal men of the families of Israel, in Jerusalem, in the chambers of the house of our Lord. <verse number="60" style="v" />So the priests and the Levites, who received the silver and the gold and the vessels which were in Jerusalem, brought them into the temple of the Lord.</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="61" style="v" />And from the river Theras we departed the twelfth day of the first month, until we came to Jerusalem, by the mighty hand of our Lord which was upon us: and the Lord delivered us from <char style="add">assault by</char> the way, from every enemy, and so we came to Jerusalem. <verse number="62" style="v" />And when we had been there three days, the silver and gold was weighed and delivered in the house of our Lord on the fourth day to<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">8:62 </char><char style="fqa" closed="false">Meremoth.</char></note> Marmoth the priest the son of<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">8:62 </char><char style="fqa" closed="false">Uriah.</char></note> Urias. <verse number="63" style="v" />And with him was Eleazar the son of Phinees, and with them were Josabdus the son of Jesus and<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">8:63 </char><char style="fqa" closed="false">Noadiah the son of Binnui.</char></note> Moeth the son of Sabannus, the Levites: all <char style="add">was delivered them</char> by number and weight. <verse number="64" style="v" />And all the weight of them was written up the same hour. <verse number="65" style="v" />Moreover those who were come out of the captivity offered sacrifices to the Lord, the God of Israel, even twelve bullocks for all Israel, fourscore and sixteen rams, <verse number="66" style="v" />threescore and twelve lambs, goats for a peace offering, twelve; all of them a sacrifice to the Lord. <verse number="67" style="v" />And they delivered the king’s commandments to the king’s stewards, and to the governors of Coelesyria and Phoenicia; and they honoured the people and the temple of the Lord.</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="68" style="v" />Now when these things were done, the principal men came to me, and said, <verse number="69" style="v" />The nation of Israel, and the princes, and the priests and the Levites, have not put away <char style="add">from them</char> the strange people of the land,<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">8:69 </char><char style="ft" closed="false">Another reading is, </char><char style="fqa" closed="false">nor their uncleannesses, </char><char style="ft" closed="false">to wit, </char><char style="fqa" closed="false">of the Gentiles, etc.</char></note> nor the uncleannesses of the Gentiles, <char style="add">to wit,</char> of the Canaanites, Hittites, Pherezites, Jebusites, and the Moabites, Egyptians, and Edomites. <verse number="70" style="v" />For both they and their sons have married with their daughters, and the holy seed is mixed with the strange people of the land; and from the beginning of this matter the rulers and the nobles have been partakers of this iniquity. <verse number="71" style="v" />And as soon as I had heard these things, I tore my clothes, and my holy garment, and plucked the hair from off my head and beard, and sat me down sad and full of heaviness. <verse number="72" style="v" />So all those who were moved at the word of the Lord, the God of Israel, assembled to me, while I mourned for the iniquity: but I sat still full of heaviness until the evening sacrifice. <verse number="73" style="v" />Then rising up from the fast with my clothes and my holy garment tore, and bowing my knees, and stretching forth my hands to the Lord, <verse number="74" style="v" />I said, O Lord, I am ashamed and confounded before your face; <verse number="75" style="v" />for our sins are multiplied above our heads, and our errors have reached up to heaven, <verse number="76" style="v" />ever since the time of our fathers; and we are in great sin, even to this day. <verse number="77" style="v" />And for our sins and our fathers’ we with our kindred and our kings and our priests were given up to the kings of the earth, to the sword, and to captivity, and for a prey with shame, to this day. <verse number="78" style="v" />And now in some measure has mercy been showed to us from you, O Lord, that there should be left us a root and a name in the place of your sanctuary; <verse number="79" style="v" />and to discover to us a light in the house of the Lord our God, <char style="add">and</char> to give us food in the time of our servitude. <verse number="80" style="v" />Yes, when we were in bondage, we were not forsaken of our Lord; but he made us gracious before the kings of Persia, so that they gave us food, <verse number="81" style="v" />and glorified the temple of our Lord, and raised up the desolate Sion, to give us a sure dwelling in Jewry and Jerusalem. <verse number="82" style="v" />And now, O Lord, what shall we say, having these things? For we have transgressed your commandments, which you gave by the hand of your servants the prophets, saying, <verse number="83" style="v" />That the land, which you° enter into to possess as a heritage, is a land polluted with the pollutions of the strangers of the land, and they have filled it with their uncleanness. <verse number="84" style="v" />Therefore now shall you° not join your daughters to their sons, neither shall you° take their daughters to your sons. <verse number="85" style="v" />Neither shall you° seek to have peace with them forever, that you° may be strong, and eat the good things of the land, and that you° may leave it for an inheritance to your children for evermore. <verse number="86" style="v" />And all that is befallen is done to us for our wicked works and great sins: for you, O Lord, did make our sins light, <verse number="87" style="v" />and did give to us such a root: <char style="add">but</char> we have turned back again to transgress your law, in mingling ourselves with the uncleanness of the heathen of the land. <verse number="88" style="v" /><note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">8:88 </char><char style="ft" closed="false">Or, </char><char style="fqa" closed="false">Was you not etc.</char></note> You was not angry with us to destroy us, till you had left us neither root, seed, nor name. <verse number="89" style="v" />O Lord of Israel, you are true: for we are left a root this day. <verse number="90" style="v" />Behold, now are we before you in our iniquities, for we can’t stand any longer before you by reason of these things.</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="91" style="v" />
    <note caller="+" style="x">
      <char style="xo" closed="false">8:91 </char>
      <char style="xt" closed="false">
        <ref loc="EZR 10:1">Ezra 10:1</ref>
      </char>
    </note> And as Esdras in his prayer made his confession, weeping, and lying flat upon the ground before the temple, there gathered to him from Jerusalem a very great throng of men and women and children: for there was great weeping amongst the multitude. <verse number="92" style="v" />Then Jechonias the son of Jeelus, one of the sons of Israel, called out, and said, O Esdras, we have sinned against the Lord God, we have married strange women of the heathen of the land, and now is all Israel<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">8:92 </char><char style="ft" closed="false">Or, </char><char style="fqa" closed="false">exalted </char><char style="ft" closed="false">Deuteronomy 28:13.</char></note> aloft. <verse number="93" style="v" />Let’s make an oath to the Lord herein, that we will put away all our wives, which <char style="add">we have taken</char> of the strangers, with their children, <verse number="94" style="v" />like as seems good to you, and to as many as do obey the Law of the Lord. <verse number="95" style="v" />Arise, and put in execution: for to you does this matter appertain, and we will be with you to do valiantly. <verse number="96" style="v" />So Esdras arose, and took an oath of the chief of the priests and Levites of all Israel to do after these things; and <char style="add">so</char> they sware.</para>
  <chapter number="9" style="c" />
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="1" style="v" />
    <note caller="+" style="x">
      <char style="xo" closed="false">9:1 </char>
      <char style="xt" closed="false">
        <ref loc="EZR 10:6">Ezra 10:6</ref>
      </char>
    </note> Then Esdras rising from the court of the temple went to the chamber of Jonas the son of Eliasib, <verse number="2" style="v" />and lodged there, and did eat no bread nor drink water, mourning for the great iniquities of the multitude. <verse number="3" style="v" />And there was made proclamation in all Jewry and Jerusalem to all those who were of the captivity, that they should be gathered together at Jerusalem: <verse number="4" style="v" />and that whoever met not there within two or three days, according as the elders that bare rule appointed, their cattle should be seized to the use of the temple, and himself cast out from the multitude of those who were of the captivity.</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="5" style="v" />And in three days were all they of the tribe of Judah and Benjamin gathered together at Jerusalem: this was the ninth month, on the twentieth day of the month. <verse number="6" style="v" />And all the multitude sat together trembling in the broad place before the temple because of the present foul weather. <verse number="7" style="v" />So Esdras arose up and said to them, you° have transgressed the law and married strange wives to increase the sins of Israel. <verse number="8" style="v" />And now make confession and give glory to the Lord, the God of our fathers, <verse number="9" style="v" />and do his will, and separate yourselves from the heathen of the land, and from the strange women. <verse number="10" style="v" />Then cried the whole multitude, and said with a loud voice, Just as you have spoken, so will we do. <verse number="11" style="v" />But forasmuch as the multitude is great, and it is foul weather, so that we can’t stand without, and this is not a work of one day or two, seeing our sin in these things is spread far: <verse number="12" style="v" />therefore let the rulers of the multitude stay, and let all them of our habitations that have strange wives come at the time appointed, <verse number="13" style="v" />and with them the rulers and judges of every place, till we turn away the wrath of the Lord from us for this matter. <verse number="14" style="v" /><char style="add">Then</char> Jonathan the son of Azael and<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">9:14 </char><char style="ft" closed="false">Another reading is, </char><char style="fqa" closed="false">Ezias.</char></note> Ezekias the son of Thocanus accordingly took the matter upon them: and Mosollamus and Levis and Sabbateus were assessors to them. <verse number="15" style="v" />And those who were of the captivity did according to all these things.</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="16" style="v" />And Esdras the priest chose to him principal men of their families, all by name: and on the new moon of the tenth month they were shut in together to examine the matter. <verse number="17" style="v" />So their cause that held strange wives was brought to an end by the new moon of the first month. <verse number="18" style="v" />And of the priests that were come together, and had strange wives, there were found; <verse number="19" style="v" />of the sons of Jesus the son of Josedek, and his kindred;<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">9:19 </char><char style="fqa" closed="false">Maaseiah.</char></note> Mathelas, and Eleazar, and<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">9:19 </char><char style="fqa" closed="false">Jarib.</char></note> Joribus, and<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">9:19 </char><char style="fqa" closed="false">Gedaliah</char></note> Joadanus. <verse number="20" style="v" />And they gave their hands to put away their wives, and <char style="add">to offer</char> rams to make reconciliation for their error. <verse number="21" style="v" />And of the sons of Emmer; Ananias, and Zabdeus, and<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">9:21 </char><char style="fqa" closed="false">Harim</char></note> Manes, and<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">9:21 </char><char style="fqa" closed="false">Maaseiah.</char></note> Sameus, and<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">9:21 </char><char style="fqa" closed="false">Jehiel.</char></note> Hiereel, and<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">9:21 </char><char style="fqa" closed="false">Uzziah.</char></note> Azarias. <verse number="22" style="v" />And of the sons of<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">9:22 </char><char style="fqa" closed="false">Pashhur.</char></note> Phaisur; Elionas, Massias, Ishmael, and Nathanael, and<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">9:22 </char><char style="fqa" closed="false">Jozabad.</char></note> Ocidelus, and<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">9:22 </char><char style="fqa" closed="false">Elasah.</char></note> Saloas. <verse number="23" style="v" />And of the Levites; Jozabdus, and Semeis, and<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">9:23 </char><char style="fqa" closed="false">Kelaiah.</char></note> Colius, who was called<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">9:23 </char><char style="fqa" closed="false">Kelita.</char></note> Calitas, and<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">9:23 </char><char style="fqa" closed="false">Pethahiah.</char></note> Patheus, and Judas, and Jonas. <verse number="24" style="v" />Of the holy singers;<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">9:24 </char><char style="fqa" closed="false">Eliashib.</char></note> Eliasibus, Bacchurus. <verse number="25" style="v" />Of the gatekeepers: Sallumus, and<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">9:25 </char><char style="fqa" closed="false">Telem.</char></note> Tolbanes. <verse number="26" style="v" />Of Israel, of the sons of<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">9:26 </char><char style="fqa" closed="false">Parosh.</char></note> Phoros;<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">9:26 </char><char style="fqa" closed="false">Ramiah</char></note> Hiermas, and<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">9:26 </char><char style="fqa" closed="false">Izziah. </char><char style="ft" closed="false">Another reading is, </char><char style="fqa" closed="false">Iezias</char></note> Ieddias, and Melchias, and<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">9:26 </char><char style="fqa" closed="false">Mijamin.</char></note> Maelus, and Eleazar, and<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">9:26 </char><char style="fqa" closed="false">Malchijah.</char></note> Asibas, and Banneas. <verse number="27" style="v" />Of the sons of Ela; Matthanias, Zacharias, and<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">9:27 </char><char style="fqa" closed="false">Jehiel.</char></note> Jezrielus, and Oabdius, and Hieremoth, and<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">9:27 </char><char style="fqa" closed="false">Abdi.</char></note> Aedias. <verse number="28" style="v" />And of the sons of<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">9:28 </char><char style="fqa" closed="false">Zattu.</char></note> Zamoth;<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">9:28 </char><char style="fqa" closed="false">Elioenai.</char></note> Eliadas,<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">9:28 </char><char style="fqa" closed="false">Eliashib.</char></note> Eliasimus,<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">9:28 </char><char style="fqa" closed="false">Mattaniah.</char></note> Othonias, Jarimoth, and<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">9:28 </char><char style="fqa" closed="false">Zabad.</char></note> Sabathus, and<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">9:28 </char><char style="fqa" closed="false">Aziza.</char></note> Zardeus. <verse number="29" style="v" />Of the sons of Bebai; Joannes, and Ananias, and<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">9:29 </char><char style="fqa" closed="false">Zabbai.</char></note> Jozabdus, and<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">9:29 </char><char style="fqa" closed="false">Athlai.</char></note> Ematheis. <verse number="30" style="v" />Of the sons of<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">9:30 </char><char style="fqa" closed="false">Bani.</char></note> Mani;<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">9:30 </char><char style="fqa" closed="false">Meshullam.</char></note> Olamus,<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">9:30 </char><char style="fqa" closed="false">Malluch.</char></note> Mamuchus,<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">9:30 </char><char style="fqa" closed="false">Adaiah.</char></note> Jedeus, Jasubas, and<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">9:30 </char><char style="fqa" closed="false">Sheal.</char></note> Jasaelus, and Hieremoth. <verse number="31" style="v" />And of the sons of Addi; Naathus, and Moossias, Laccunus, and Naidus, and Matthanias, and Sesthel, Balnuus, and Manasseas. <verse number="32" style="v" />And of the sons of Annas; Elionas, and Aseas, and Melchias, and Sabbeus, and Simon Chosameus. <verse number="33" style="v" />And of the sons of Asom;<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">9:33 </char><char style="fqa" closed="false">Mattenai.</char></note> Maltanneus, and<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">9:33 </char><char style="fqa" closed="false">Mattattah.</char></note> Mattathias, and<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">9:33 </char><char style="fqa" closed="false">Zabad.</char></note> Sabanneus, Eliphalat, and Manasses, and Semei. <verse number="34" style="v" />And of the sons of Baani; Jeremias, Momdis, Ismaerus, Juel, Mamdai, and Pedias, and Anos, Carabasion, and Enasibus, and Mamnitamenus, Eliasis, Bannus, Eliali, Someis, Selemias, Nathanias: and of the sons of Ezora; Sesis, Ezril, Azaelus, Samatus, Zambri, Josephus. <verse number="35" style="v" />And of the sons of Nooma; Mazitias, Zabadeas, Edos, Juel, Banaias. <verse number="36" style="v" />All these had taken strange wives, and they put them away with their children. <verse number="37" style="v" />And the priests and Levites, and those who were of Israel, lived in Jerusalem, and in the country, on the new moon of the seventh month, and the children of Israel in their habitations.</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="38" style="v" />
    <note caller="+" style="x">
      <char style="xo" closed="false">9:38 </char>
      <char style="xt" closed="false">
        <ref loc="NEH 8:1">Nehemiah 8:1</ref>
      </char>
    </note> And the whole multitude were gathered together with one accord into the broad place before the porch of the temple towards the east: <verse number="39" style="v" />and they said to Esdras the priest and reader, Bring the law of Moses, that was given of the Lord, the God of Israel. <verse number="40" style="v" />So Esdras the chief priest brought the law to the whole multitude both of men and women, and to all the priests, to hear the law on the new moon of the seventh month. <verse number="41" style="v" />And he read in the broad place before the porch of the temple from morning to mid-day, before both men and women; and<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">9:41 </char><char style="ft" closed="false">Another reading is, </char><char style="fqa" closed="false">they gave all heed.</char></note> all the multitude gave heed to the law. <verse number="42" style="v" />And Esdras the priest and reader of the law stood up upon the pulpit of wood, which was made <char style="add">for that purpose. </char> <verse number="43" style="v" />And there stood up by him Mattathias, Sammus, Ananias, Azarias, Urias,<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">9:43 </char><char style="fqa" closed="false">Hilkiah.</char></note> Ezekias, Baalsamus, upon the right hand: <verse number="44" style="v" />and upon his left hand,<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">9:44 </char><char style="fqa" closed="false">Pedaiah.</char></note> Phaldeus, Misael, Melchias,<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">9:44 </char><char style="fqa" closed="false">Hashuin.</char></note> Lothasubus, Nabarias, Zacharias. <verse number="45" style="v" />Then took Esdras the book of the law before the multitude, and sat honourably in the first place before all. <verse number="46" style="v" />And when he opened the law, they stood all straight up. So Esdras blessed the Lord God Most High, the God of armies, Almighty. <verse number="47" style="v" />And all the people answered, Amen; and lifting up their hands they fell to the ground, and worshipped the Lord. <verse number="48" style="v" />Also Jesus, Annus, Sarabias, Iadinus, Jacubus, Sabateus,<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">9:48 </char><char style="fqa" closed="false">Hodiah.</char></note> Auteas, Maiannas, and Calitas, Azarias, and Jozabdus, and Ananias, Phalias, the Levites, taught the law of the Lord,<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">9:48 </char><char style="ft" closed="false">Some authorities omit </char><char style="fq" closed="false">and read...Lord.</char></note> and read to the multitude the law of the Lord, making them withal to understand it. <verse number="49" style="v" />Then said Attharates to Esdras the chief priest and reader, and to the Levites that taught the multitude, even to all, <verse number="50" style="v" />This day is holy to the Lord; (now they all wept when they heard the law:) <verse number="51" style="v" />go then, and eat the fat, and drink the sweet, and send portions to those who have nothing; <verse number="52" style="v" />for the day is holy to the Lord: and be not sorrowful; for the Lord will bring you to honour. <verse number="53" style="v" />So the Levites published all things to the people, saying, This day is holy; be not sorrowful. <verse number="54" style="v" />Then they went their way, every one to eat and drink, and make merry, and to give portions to those who had nothing, and to make great cheer; <verse number="55" style="v" />because they<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">9:55 </char><char style="ft" closed="false">Or, </char><char style="fqa" closed="false">were inspired by</char></note> understood the words wherein they were instructed, and for the which they had been assembled.</para>
</usx>