<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<usx version="2.6">
  <book code="DEU" style="id">1World English Bible British Edition (WEBBE)</book>
  <para style="ide">UTF-8</para>
  <para style="h">Deuteronomy</para>
  <para style="toc1">The Fifth Book of Moses, Commonly Called Deuteronomy</para>
  <para style="toc2">Deuteronomy</para>
  <para style="toc3">Deuteronomy</para>
  <para style="mt2">The Fifth Book of Moses,</para>
  <para style="mt3">Commonly Called</para>
  <para style="mt1">Deuteronomy</para>
  <chapter number="1" style="c" />
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="1" style="v" />These are the words which Moses spoke to all Israel beyond the Jordan in the wilderness, in the Arabah opposite Suf, between Paran, Tophel, Laban, Hazeroth, and Dizahab. <verse number="2" style="v" />It is eleven days’ journey from Horeb by the way of Mount Seir to Kadesh Barnea. <verse number="3" style="v" />In the fortieth year, in the eleventh month, on the first day of the month, Moses spoke to the children of Israel according to all that the LORD<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">1:3 </char><char style="ft" closed="false">When rendered in ALL CAPITAL LETTERS, “LORD” or “GOD” is the translation of God’s Proper Name.</char></note> had given him in commandment to them, <verse number="4" style="v" />after he had struck Sihon the king of the Amorites who lived in Heshbon, and Og the king of Bashan who lived in Ashtaroth, at Edrei. <verse number="5" style="v" />Beyond the Jordan, in the land of Moab, Moses began to declare this law, saying, <verse number="6" style="v" />“The LORD our God<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">1:6 </char><char style="ft" closed="false">The Hebrew word rendered “God” is “אֱלֹהִ֑ים” (Elohim).</char></note> spoke to us in Horeb, saying, ‘You have lived long enough at this mountain. <verse number="7" style="v" />Turn, and take your journey, and go to the hill country of the Amorites and to all the places near there: in the Arabah, in the hill country, in the lowland, in the South, by the seashore, in the land of the Canaanites, and in Lebanon as far as the great river, the river Euphrates. <verse number="8" style="v" />Behold,<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">1:8 </char><char style="ft" closed="false">“Behold”, from “הִנֵּה”, means look at, take notice, observe, see, or gaze at. It is often used as an interjection.</char></note> I have set the land before you. Go in and possess the land which the LORD swore to your fathers—to Abraham, to Isaac, and to Jacob—to give to them and to their offspring<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">1:8 </char><char style="ft" closed="false">or, seed</char></note> after them.’”</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="9" style="v" />I spoke to you at that time, saying, “I am not able to bear you myself alone. <verse number="10" style="v" />The LORD your God has multiplied you, and behold, you are today as the stars of the sky for multitude. <verse number="11" style="v" />The LORD, the God of your fathers, make you a thousand times as many as you are and bless you, as he has promised you! <verse number="12" style="v" />How can I myself alone bear your problems, your burdens, and your strife? <verse number="13" style="v" />Take wise men of understanding who are respected amongst your tribes, and I will make them heads over you.”</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="14" style="v" />You answered me, and said, “The thing which you have spoken is good to do.” <verse number="15" style="v" />So I took the heads of your tribes, wise and respected men, and made them heads over you, captains of thousands, captains of hundreds, captains of fifties, captains of tens, and officers, according to your tribes. <verse number="16" style="v" />I commanded your judges at that time, saying, “Hear cases between your brothers and judge righteously between a man and his brother, and the foreigner who is living with him. <verse number="17" style="v" />You shall not show partiality in judgement; you shall hear the small and the great alike. You shall not be afraid of the face of man, for the judgement is God’s. The case that is too hard for you, you shall bring to me, and I will hear it.” <verse number="18" style="v" />I commanded you at that time all the things which you should do. <verse number="19" style="v" />We travelled from Horeb and went through all that great and terrible wilderness which you saw, by the way to the hill country of the Amorites, as the LORD our God commanded us; and we came to Kadesh Barnea. <verse number="20" style="v" />I said to you, “You have come to the hill country of the Amorites, which the LORD our God gives to us. <verse number="21" style="v" />Behold, the LORD your God has set the land before you. Go up, take possession, as the LORD the God of your fathers has spoken to you. Don’t be afraid, neither be dismayed.”</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="22" style="v" />You came near to me, everyone of you, and said, “Let’s send men before us, that they may search the land for us, and bring back to us word of the way by which we must go up, and the cities to which we shall come.”</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="23" style="v" />The thing pleased me well. I took twelve of your men, one man for every tribe. <verse number="24" style="v" />They turned and went up into the hill country, and came to the valley of Eshcol, and spied it out. <verse number="25" style="v" />They took some of the fruit of the land in their hands and brought it down to us, and brought us word again, and said, “It is a good land which the LORD our God gives to us.”</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="26" style="v" />Yet you wouldn’t go up, but rebelled against the commandment of the LORD your God. <verse number="27" style="v" />You murmured in your tents, and said, “Because the LORD hated us, he has brought us out of the land of Egypt, to deliver us into the hand of the Amorites to destroy us. <verse number="28" style="v" />Where are we going up? Our brothers have made our heart melt, saying, ‘The people are greater and taller than we. The cities are great and fortified up to the sky. Moreover we have seen the sons of the Anakim there!’”</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="29" style="v" />Then I said to you, “Don’t be terrified. Don’t be afraid of them. <verse number="30" style="v" />The LORD your God, who goes before you, he will fight for you, according to all that he did for you in Egypt before your eyes, <verse number="31" style="v" />and in the wilderness where you have seen how that the LORD your God carried you, as a man carries his son, in all the way that you went, until you came to this place.”</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="32" style="v" />Yet in this thing you didn’t believe the LORD your God, <verse number="33" style="v" />who went before you on the way, to seek out a place for you to pitch your tents in: in fire by night, to show you by what way you should go, and in the cloud by day. <verse number="34" style="v" />The LORD heard the voice of your words and was angry, and swore, saying, <verse number="35" style="v" />“Surely not one of these men of this evil generation shall see the good land which I swore to give to your fathers, <verse number="36" style="v" />except Caleb the son of Jephunneh. He shall see it. I will give the land that he has trodden on to him and to his children, because he has wholly followed the LORD.”</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="37" style="v" />Also the LORD was angry with me for your sakes, saying, “You also shall not go in there. <verse number="38" style="v" />Joshua the son of Nun, who stands before you, shall go in there. Encourage him, for he shall cause Israel to inherit it. <verse number="39" style="v" />Moreover your little ones, whom you said would be captured or killed, your children, who today have no knowledge of good or evil, shall go in there. I will give it to them, and they shall possess it. <verse number="40" style="v" />But as for you, turn, and take your journey into the wilderness by the way to the Red Sea.”</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="41" style="v" />Then you answered and said to me, “We have sinned against the LORD. We will go up and fight, according to all that the LORD our God commanded us.” Every man of you put on his weapons of war, and presumed to go up into the hill country.</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="42" style="v" />The LORD said to me, “Tell them, ‘Don’t go up and don’t fight; for I am not amongst you, lest you be struck before your enemies.’”</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="43" style="v" />So I spoke to you, and you didn’t listen; but you rebelled against the commandment of the LORD, and were presumptuous, and went up into the hill country. <verse number="44" style="v" />The Amorites, who lived in that hill country, came out against you and chased you as bees do, and beat you down in Seir, even to Hormah. <verse number="45" style="v" />You returned and wept before the LORD; but the LORD didn’t listen to your voice, nor turn his ear to you. <verse number="46" style="v" />So you stayed in Kadesh many days, according to the days that you remained.</para>
  <chapter number="2" style="c" />
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="1" style="v" />Then we turned, and took our journey into the wilderness by the way to the Red Sea, as the LORD spoke to me; and we encircled Mount Seir many days.</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="2" style="v" />The LORD spoke to me, saying, <verse number="3" style="v" />“You have encircled this mountain long enough. Turn northward. <verse number="4" style="v" />Command the people, saying, ‘You are to pass through the border of your brothers, the children of Esau, who dwell in Seir; and they will be afraid of you. Therefore be careful. <verse number="5" style="v" />Don’t contend with them; for I will not give you any of their land, no, not so much as for the sole of the foot to tread on, because I have given Mount Seir to Esau for a possession. <verse number="6" style="v" />You shall purchase food from them for money, that you may eat. You shall also buy water from them for money, that you may drink.’”</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="7" style="v" />For the LORD your God has blessed you in all the work of your hands. He has known your walking through this great wilderness. These forty years, the LORD your God has been with you. You have lacked nothing.</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="8" style="v" />So we passed by from our brothers, the children of Esau, who dwell in Seir, from the way of the Arabah from Elath and from Ezion Geber. We turned and passed by the way of the wilderness of Moab.</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="9" style="v" />The LORD said to me, “Don’t bother Moab, neither contend with them in battle; for I will not give you any of his land for a possession, because I have given Ar to the children of Lot for a possession.”</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="10" style="v" />(The Emim lived there before, a great and numerous people, and tall as the Anakim. <verse number="11" style="v" />These also are considered to be Rephaim, as the Anakim; but the Moabites call them Emim. <verse number="12" style="v" />The Horites also lived in Seir in the past, but the children of Esau succeeded them. They destroyed them from before them, and lived in their place, as Israel did to the land of his possession, which the LORD gave to them.)</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="13" style="v" />“Now rise up, and cross over the brook Zered.” We went over the brook Zered.</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="14" style="v" />The days in which we came from Kadesh Barnea until we had come over the brook Zered were thirty-eight years: until all the generation of the men of war were consumed from the middle of the camp, as the LORD swore to them. <verse number="15" style="v" />Moreover the LORD’s hand was against them, to destroy them from the middle of the camp, until they were consumed. <verse number="16" style="v" />So, when all the men of war were consumed and dead from amongst the people, <verse number="17" style="v" />the LORD spoke to me, saying, <verse number="18" style="v" />“You are to pass over Ar, the border of Moab, today. <verse number="19" style="v" />When you come near the border of the children of Ammon, don’t bother them, nor contend with them; for I will not give you any of the land of the children of Ammon for a possession, because I have given it to the children of Lot for a possession.”</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="20" style="v" />(That also is considered a land of Rephaim. Rephaim lived there in the past, but the Ammonites call them Zamzummim, <verse number="21" style="v" />a great people, many, and tall, as the Anakim; but the LORD destroyed them from before Israel, and they succeeded them, and lived in their place; <verse number="22" style="v" />as he did for the children of Esau who dwell in Seir, when he destroyed the Horites from before them; and they succeeded them, and lived in their place even to this day. <verse number="23" style="v" />Then the Avvim, who lived in villages as far as Gaza: the Caphtorim, who came out of Caphtor, destroyed them and lived in their place.)</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="24" style="v" />“Rise up, take your journey, and pass over the valley of the Arnon. Behold, I have given into your hand Sihon the Amorite, king of Heshbon, and his land; begin to possess it, and contend with him in battle. <verse number="25" style="v" />Today I will begin to put the dread of you and the fear of you on the peoples who are under the whole sky, who shall hear the report of you, and shall tremble and be in anguish because of you.”</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="26" style="v" />I sent messengers out of the wilderness of Kedemoth to Sihon king of Heshbon with words of peace, saying, <verse number="27" style="v" />“Let me pass through your land. I will go along by the highway. I will turn neither to the right hand nor to the left. <verse number="28" style="v" />You shall sell me food for money, that I may eat; and give me water for money, that I may drink. Just let me pass through on my feet, <verse number="29" style="v" />as the children of Esau who dwell in Seir, and the Moabites who dwell in Ar, did to me; until I pass over the Jordan into the land which the LORD our God gives us.” <verse number="30" style="v" />But Sihon king of Heshbon would not let us pass by him; for the LORD your God hardened his spirit and made his heart obstinate, that he might deliver him into your hand, as it is today.</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="31" style="v" />The LORD said to me, “Behold, I have begun to deliver up Sihon and his land before you. Begin to possess, that you may inherit his land.” <verse number="32" style="v" />Then Sihon came out against us, he and all his people, to battle at Jahaz. <verse number="33" style="v" />The LORD our God delivered him up before us; and we struck him, his sons, and all his people. <verse number="34" style="v" />We took all his cities at that time, and utterly destroyed every inhabited city, with the women and the little ones. We left no one remaining. <verse number="35" style="v" />Only the livestock we took for plunder for ourselves, with the plunder of the cities which we had taken. <verse number="36" style="v" />From Aroer, which is on the edge of the valley of the Arnon, and the city that is in the valley, even to Gilead, there was not a city too high for us. The LORD our God delivered up all before us. <verse number="37" style="v" />Only to the land of the children of Ammon you didn’t come near: all the banks of the river Jabbok, and the cities of the hill country, and wherever the LORD our God forbade us.</para>
  <chapter number="3" style="c" />
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="1" style="v" />Then we turned, and went up the way to Bashan. Og the king of Bashan came out against us, he and all his people, to battle at Edrei. <verse number="2" style="v" />The LORD said to me, “Don’t fear him; for I have delivered him, with all his people and his land, into your hand. You shall do to him as you did to Sihon king of the Amorites, who lived at Heshbon.”</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="3" style="v" />So the LORD our God also delivered into our hand Og, the king of Bashan, and all his people. We struck him until no one was left to him remaining. <verse number="4" style="v" />We took all his cities at that time. There was not a city which we didn’t take from them: sixty cities, all the region of Argob, the kingdom of Og in Bashan. <verse number="5" style="v" />All these were cities fortified with high walls, gates, and bars, in addition to a great many villages without walls. <verse number="6" style="v" />We utterly destroyed them, as we did to Sihon king of Heshbon, utterly destroying every inhabited city, with the women and the little ones. <verse number="7" style="v" />But all the livestock, and the plunder of the cities, we took for plunder for ourselves. <verse number="8" style="v" />We took the land at that time out of the hand of the two kings of the Amorites who were beyond the Jordan, from the valley of the Arnon to Mount Hermon. <verse number="9" style="v" />(The Sidonians call Hermon Sirion, and the Amorites call it Senir.) <verse number="10" style="v" />We took all the cities of the plain, and all Gilead, and all Bashan, to Salecah and Edrei, cities of the kingdom of Og in Bashan. <verse number="11" style="v" />(For only Og king of Bashan remained of the remnant of the Rephaim. Behold, his bedstead was a bedstead of iron. Isn’t it in Rabbah of the children of Ammon? Nine cubits<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">3:11 </char><char style="ft" closed="false">A cubit is the length from the tip of the middle finger to the elbow on a man’s arm, or about 18 inches or 46 centimetres.</char></note> was its length, and four cubits its width, after the cubit of a man.) <verse number="12" style="v" />This land we took in possession at that time: from Aroer, which is by the valley of the Arnon, and half the hill country of Gilead with its cities, I gave to the Reubenites and to the Gadites; <verse number="13" style="v" />and the rest of Gilead, and all Bashan, the kingdom of Og, I gave to the half-tribe of Manasseh—all the region of Argob, even all Bashan. (The same is called the land of Rephaim. <verse number="14" style="v" />Jair the son of Manasseh took all the region of Argob, to the border of the Geshurites and the Maacathites, and called them, even Bashan, after his own name, Havvoth Jair, to this day.) <verse number="15" style="v" />I gave Gilead to Machir. <verse number="16" style="v" />To the Reubenites and to the Gadites I gave from Gilead even to the valley of the Arnon, the middle of the valley, and its border, even to the river Jabbok, which is the border of the children of Ammon; <verse number="17" style="v" />the Arabah also, and the Jordan and its border, from Chinnereth even to the sea of the Arabah, the Salt Sea, under the slopes of Pisgah eastward.</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="18" style="v" />I commanded you at that time, saying, “The LORD your God has given you this land to possess it. All of you men of valour shall pass over armed before your brothers, the children of Israel. <verse number="19" style="v" />But your wives, and your little ones, and your livestock, (I know that you have much livestock), shall live in your cities which I have given you, <verse number="20" style="v" />until the LORD gives rest to your brothers, as to you, and they also possess the land which the LORD your God gives them beyond the Jordan. Then you shall each return to his own possession, which I have given you.”</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="21" style="v" />I commanded Joshua at that time, saying, “Your eyes have seen all that the LORD your God has done to these two kings. So shall the LORD do to all the kingdoms where you go over. <verse number="22" style="v" />You shall not fear them; for the LORD your God himself fights for you.”</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="23" style="v" />I begged GOD at that time, saying, <verse number="24" style="v" />“Lord<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">3:24 </char><char style="ft" closed="false">The word translated “Lord” is “Adonai.”</char></note> GOD, you have begun to show your servant your greatness, and your strong hand. For what god is there in heaven or in earth that can do works like yours, and mighty acts like yours? <verse number="25" style="v" />Please let me go over and see the good land that is beyond the Jordan, that fine mountain, and Lebanon.”</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="26" style="v" />But the LORD was angry with me because of you, and didn’t listen to me. The LORD said to me, “That is enough! Speak no more to me of this matter. <verse number="27" style="v" />Go up to the top of Pisgah, and lift up your eyes westward, and northward, and southward, and eastward, and see with your eyes; for you shall not go over this Jordan. <verse number="28" style="v" />But commission Joshua, and encourage him, and strengthen him; for he shall go over before this people, and he shall cause them to inherit the land which you shall see.” <verse number="29" style="v" />So we stayed in the valley near Beth Peor.</para>
  <chapter number="4" style="c" />
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="1" style="v" />Now, Israel, listen to the statutes and to the ordinances which I teach you, to do them; that you may live, and go in and possess the land which the LORD, the God of your fathers, gives you. <verse number="2" style="v" />You shall not add to the word which I command you, neither shall you take away from it, that you may keep the commandments of the LORD your God which I command you. <verse number="3" style="v" />Your eyes have seen what the LORD did because of Baal Peor; for the LORD your God has destroyed all the men who followed Baal Peor from amongst you. <verse number="4" style="v" />But you who were faithful to the LORD your God are all alive today. <verse number="5" style="v" />Behold, I have taught you statutes and ordinances, even as the LORD my God commanded me, that you should do so in the middle of the land where you go in to possess it. <verse number="6" style="v" />Keep therefore and do them; for this is your wisdom and your understanding in the sight of the peoples who shall hear all these statutes and say, “Surely this great nation is a wise and understanding people.” <verse number="7" style="v" />For what great nation is there that has a god so near to them as the LORD our God is whenever we call on him? <verse number="8" style="v" />What great nation is there that has statutes and ordinances so righteous as all this law which I set before you today?</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="9" style="v" />Only be careful, and keep your soul diligently, lest you forget the things which your eyes saw, and lest they depart from your heart all the days of your life; but make them known to your children and your children’s children— <verse number="10" style="v" />the day that you stood before the LORD your God in Horeb, when the LORD said to me, “Assemble the people to me, and I will make them hear my words, that they may learn to fear me all the days that they live on the earth, and that they may teach their children.” <verse number="11" style="v" />You came near and stood under the mountain. The mountain burnt with fire to the heart of the sky, with darkness, cloud, and thick darkness. <verse number="12" style="v" />The LORD spoke to you out of the middle of the fire: you heard the voice of words, but you saw no form; you only heard a voice. <verse number="13" style="v" />He declared to you his covenant, which he commanded you to perform, even the ten commandments. He wrote them on two stone tablets. <verse number="14" style="v" />The LORD commanded me at that time to teach you statutes and ordinances, that you might do them in the land where you go over to possess it. <verse number="15" style="v" />Be very careful, for you saw no kind of form on the day that the LORD spoke to you in Horeb out of the middle of the fire, <verse number="16" style="v" />lest you corrupt yourselves, and make yourself a carved image in the form of any figure, the likeness of male or female, <verse number="17" style="v" />the likeness of any animal that is on the earth, the likeness of any winged bird that flies in the sky, <verse number="18" style="v" />the likeness of anything that creeps on the ground, the likeness of any fish that is in the water under the earth; <verse number="19" style="v" />and lest you lift up your eyes to the sky, and when you see the sun and the moon and the stars, even all the army of the sky, you are drawn away and worship them, and serve them, which the LORD your God has allotted to all the peoples under the whole sky. <verse number="20" style="v" />But the LORD has taken you, and brought you out of the iron furnace, out of Egypt, to be to him a people of inheritance, as it is today. <verse number="21" style="v" />Furthermore the LORD was angry with me for your sakes, and swore that I should not go over the Jordan, and that I should not go in to that good land which the LORD your God gives you for an inheritance; <verse number="22" style="v" />but I must die in this land. I must not go over the Jordan, but you shall go over and possess that good land. <verse number="23" style="v" />Be careful, lest you forget the covenant of the LORD your God, which he made with you, and make yourselves a carved image in the form of anything which the LORD your God has forbidden you. <verse number="24" style="v" />For the LORD your God is a devouring fire, a jealous God. <verse number="25" style="v" />When you father children and children’s children, and you have been long in the land, and then corrupt yourselves, and make a carved image in the form of anything, and do that which is evil in the LORD your God’s sight to provoke him to anger, <verse number="26" style="v" />I call heaven and earth to witness against you today, that you will soon utterly perish from off the land which you go over the Jordan to possess it. You will not prolong your days on it, but will utterly be destroyed. <verse number="27" style="v" />The LORD will scatter you amongst the peoples, and you will be left few in number amongst the nations where the LORD will lead you away. <verse number="28" style="v" />There you will serve gods, the work of men’s hands, wood and stone, which neither see, nor hear, nor eat, nor smell. <verse number="29" style="v" />But from there you shall seek the LORD your God, and you will find him when you search after him with all your heart and with all your soul. <verse number="30" style="v" />When you are in oppression, and all these things have come on you, in the latter days you shall return to the LORD your God and listen to his voice. <verse number="31" style="v" />For the LORD your God is a merciful God. He will not fail you nor destroy you, nor forget the covenant of your fathers which he swore to them. <verse number="32" style="v" />For ask now of the days that are past, which were before you, since the day that God created man on the earth, and from the one end of the sky to the other, whether there has been anything as great as this thing is, or has been heard like it? <verse number="33" style="v" />Did a people ever hear the voice of God speaking out of the middle of the fire, as you have heard, and live? <verse number="34" style="v" />Or has God tried to go and take a nation for himself from amongst another nation, by trials, by signs, by wonders, by war, by a mighty hand, by an outstretched arm, and by great terrors, according to all that the LORD your God did for you in Egypt before your eyes? <verse number="35" style="v" />It was shown to you so that you might know that the LORD is God. There is no one else besides him. <verse number="36" style="v" />Out of heaven he made you to hear his voice, that he might instruct you. On earth he made you to see his great fire; and you heard his words out of the middle of the fire. <verse number="37" style="v" />Because he loved your fathers, therefore he chose their offspring after them, and brought you out with his presence, with his great power, out of Egypt; <verse number="38" style="v" />to drive out nations from before you greater and mightier than you, to bring you in, to give you their land for an inheritance, as it is today. <verse number="39" style="v" />Know therefore today, and take it to heart, that the LORD himself is God in heaven above and on the earth beneath. There is no one else. <verse number="40" style="v" />You shall keep his statutes and his commandments which I command you today, that it may go well with you and with your children after you, and that you may prolong your days in the land which the LORD your God gives you for all time.</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="41" style="v" />Then Moses set apart three cities beyond the Jordan towards the sunrise, <verse number="42" style="v" />that the man slayer might flee there, who kills his neighbour unintentionally and didn’t hate him in time past, and that fleeing to one of these cities he might live: <verse number="43" style="v" />Bezer in the wilderness, in the plain country, for the Reubenites; and Ramoth in Gilead for the Gadites; and Golan in Bashan for the Manassites.</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="44" style="v" />This is the law which Moses set before the children of Israel. <verse number="45" style="v" />These are the testimonies, and the statutes, and the ordinances which Moses spoke to the children of Israel when they came out of Egypt, <verse number="46" style="v" />beyond the Jordan, in the valley opposite Beth Peor, in the land of Sihon king of the Amorites, who lived at Heshbon, whom Moses and the children of Israel struck when they came out of Egypt. <verse number="47" style="v" />They took possession of his land and the land of Og king of Bashan, the two kings of the Amorites, who were beyond the Jordan towards the sunrise; <verse number="48" style="v" />from Aroer, which is on the edge of the valley of the Arnon, even to Mount Sion (also called Hermon), <verse number="49" style="v" />and all the Arabah beyond the Jordan eastward, even to the sea of the Arabah, under the slopes of Pisgah.</para>
  <chapter number="5" style="c" />
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="1" style="v" />Moses called to all Israel, and said to them, “Hear, Israel, the statutes and the ordinances which I speak in your ears today, that you may learn them, and observe to do them.” <verse number="2" style="v" />The LORD our God made a covenant with us in Horeb. <verse number="3" style="v" />The LORD didn’t make this covenant with our fathers, but with us, even us, who are all of us here alive today. <verse number="4" style="v" />The LORD spoke with you face to face on the mountain out of the middle of the fire, <verse number="5" style="v" />(I stood between the LORD and you at that time, to show you the LORD’s word; for you were afraid because of the fire, and didn’t go up onto the mountain) saying,</para>
  <para style="m">
    <verse number="6" style="v" />“I am the LORD your God, who brought you out of the land of Egypt, out of the house of bondage.</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="7" style="v" />“You shall have no other gods before me.</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="8" style="v" />“You shall not make a carved image for yourself—any likeness of what is in heaven above, or what is in the earth beneath, or that is in the water under the earth. <verse number="9" style="v" />You shall not bow yourself down to them, nor serve them; for I, the LORD your God, am a jealous God, visiting the iniquity of the fathers on the children and on the third and on the fourth generation of those who hate me; <verse number="10" style="v" />and showing loving kindness to thousands of those who love me and keep my commandments.</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="11" style="v" />“You shall not misuse the name of the LORD your God;<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">5:11 </char><char style="ft" closed="false">or, You shall not take the name of Yahweh your God in vain;</char></note> for the LORD will not hold him guiltless who misuses his name.</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="12" style="v" />“Observe the Sabbath day, to keep it holy, as the LORD your God commanded you. <verse number="13" style="v" />You shall labour six days, and do all your work; <verse number="14" style="v" />but the seventh day is a Sabbath to the LORD your God, in which you shall not do any work— neither you, nor your son, nor your daughter, nor your male servant, nor your female servant, nor your ox, nor your donkey, nor any of your livestock, nor your stranger who is within your gates; that your male servant and your female servant may rest as well as you. <verse number="15" style="v" />You shall remember that you were a servant in the land of Egypt, and the LORD your God brought you out of there by a mighty hand and by an outstretched arm. Therefore the LORD your God commanded you to keep the Sabbath day.</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="16" style="v" />“Honour your father and your mother, as the LORD your God commanded you; that your days may be long, and that it may go well with you in the land which the LORD your God gives you.</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="17" style="v" />“You shall not murder.</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="18" style="v" />“You shall not commit adultery.</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="19" style="v" />“You shall not steal.</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="20" style="v" />“You shall not give false testimony against your neighbour.</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="21" style="v" />“You shall not covet your neighbour’s wife. Neither shall you desire your neighbour’s house, his field, or his male servant, or his female servant, his ox, or his donkey, or anything that is your neighbour’s.”</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="22" style="v" />The LORD spoke these words to all your assembly on the mountain out of the middle of the fire, of the cloud, and of the thick darkness, with a great voice. He added no more. He wrote them on two stone tablets, and gave them to me. <verse number="23" style="v" />When you heard the voice out of the middle of the darkness, while the mountain was burning with fire, you came near to me, even all the heads of your tribes, and your elders; <verse number="24" style="v" />and you said, “Behold, the LORD our God has shown us his glory and his greatness, and we have heard his voice out of the middle of the fire. We have seen today that God does speak with man, and he lives. <verse number="25" style="v" />Now therefore, why should we die? For this great fire will consume us. If we hear the LORD our God’s voice any more, then we shall die. <verse number="26" style="v" />For who is there of all flesh who has heard the voice of the living God speaking out of the middle of the fire, as we have, and lived? <verse number="27" style="v" />Go near, and hear all that the LORD our God shall say, and tell us all that the LORD our God tells you; and we will hear it, and do it.”</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="28" style="v" />The LORD heard the voice of your words when you spoke to me; and the LORD said to me, “I have heard the voice of the words of this people which they have spoken to you. They have well said all that they have spoken. <verse number="29" style="v" />Oh that there were such a heart in them that they would fear me and keep all my commandments always, that it might be well with them and with their children forever!</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="30" style="v" />“Go tell them, ‘Return to your tents.’ <verse number="31" style="v" />But as for you, stand here by me, and I will tell you all the commandments, and the statutes, and the ordinances, which you shall teach them, that they may do them in the land which I give them to possess.”</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="32" style="v" />You shall observe to do therefore as the LORD your God has commanded you. You shall not turn away to the right hand or to the left. <verse number="33" style="v" />You shall walk in all the way which the LORD your God has commanded you, that you may live and that it may be well with you, and that you may prolong your days in the land which you shall possess.</para>
  <chapter number="6" style="c" />
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="1" style="v" />Now these are the commandments, the statutes, and the ordinances, which the LORD your God commanded to teach you, that you might do them in the land that you go over to possess; <verse number="2" style="v" />that you might fear the LORD your God, to keep all his statutes and his commandments, which I command you—you, your son, and your son’s son, all the days of your life; and that your days may be prolonged. <verse number="3" style="v" />Hear therefore, Israel, and observe to do it, that it may be well with you, and that you may increase mightily, as the LORD, the God of your fathers, has promised to you, in a land flowing with milk and honey.</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="4" style="v" />Hear, Israel: the LORD is our God. The LORD is one. <verse number="5" style="v" />You shall love the LORD your God with all your heart, with all your soul, and with all your might. <verse number="6" style="v" />These words, which I command you today, shall be on your heart; <verse number="7" style="v" />and you shall teach them diligently to your children, and shall talk of them when you sit in your house, and when you walk by the way, and when you lie down, and when you rise up. <verse number="8" style="v" />You shall bind them for a sign on your hand, and they shall be for frontlets between your eyes. <verse number="9" style="v" />You shall write them on the door posts of your house and on your gates.</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="10" style="v" />It shall be, when the LORD your God brings you into the land which he swore to your fathers, to Abraham, to Isaac, and to Jacob, to give you, great and goodly cities which you didn’t build, <verse number="11" style="v" />and houses full of all good things which you didn’t fill, and cisterns dug out which you didn’t dig, vineyards and olive trees which you didn’t plant, and you shall eat and be full; <verse number="12" style="v" />then beware lest you forget the LORD, who brought you out of the land of Egypt, out of the house of bondage. <verse number="13" style="v" />You shall fear the LORD your God; and you shall serve him, and shall swear by his name. <verse number="14" style="v" />You shall not go after other gods, of the gods of the peoples who are around you, <verse number="15" style="v" />for the LORD your God amongst you is a jealous God, lest the anger of the LORD your God be kindled against you, and he destroy you from off the face of the earth. <verse number="16" style="v" />You shall not tempt the LORD your God, as you tempted him in Massah. <verse number="17" style="v" />You shall diligently keep the commandments of the LORD your God, and his testimonies, and his statutes, which he has commanded you. <verse number="18" style="v" />You shall do that which is right and good in the LORD’s sight, that it may be well with you and that you may go in and possess the good land which the LORD swore to your fathers, <verse number="19" style="v" />to thrust out all your enemies from before you, as the LORD has spoken.</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="20" style="v" />When your son asks you in time to come, saying, “What do the testimonies, the statutes, and the ordinances, which the LORD our God has commanded you mean?” <verse number="21" style="v" />then you shall tell your son, “We were Pharaoh’s slaves in Egypt. The LORD brought us out of Egypt with a mighty hand; <verse number="22" style="v" />and the LORD showed great and awesome signs and wonders on Egypt, on Pharaoh, and on all his house, before our eyes; <verse number="23" style="v" />and he brought us out from there, that he might bring us in, to give us the land which he swore to our fathers. <verse number="24" style="v" />The LORD commanded us to do all these statutes, to fear the LORD our God, for our good always, that he might preserve us alive, as we are today. <verse number="25" style="v" />It shall be righteousness to us, if we observe to do all these commandments before the LORD our God, as he has commanded us.”</para>
  <chapter number="7" style="c" />
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="1" style="v" />When the LORD your God brings you into the land where you go to possess it, and casts out many nations before you—the Hittite, the Girgashite, the Amorite, the Canaanite, the Perizzite, the Hivite, and the Jebusite—seven nations greater and mightier than you; <verse number="2" style="v" />and when the LORD your God delivers them up before you, and you strike them, then you shall utterly destroy them. You shall make no covenant with them, nor show mercy to them. <verse number="3" style="v" />You shall not make marriages with them. You shall not give your daughter to his son, nor shall you take his daughter for your son. <verse number="4" style="v" />For that would turn away your sons from following me, that they may serve other gods. So the LORD’s anger would be kindled against you, and he would destroy you quickly. <verse number="5" style="v" />But you shall deal with them like this: you shall break down their altars, dash their pillars in pieces, cut down their Asherah poles, and burn their engraved images with fire. <verse number="6" style="v" />For you are a holy people to the LORD your God. The LORD your God has chosen you to be a people for his own possession, above all peoples who are on the face of the earth. <verse number="7" style="v" />The LORD didn’t set his love on you nor choose you, because you were more in number than any people; for you were the fewest of all peoples; <verse number="8" style="v" />but because the LORD loves you, and because he desires to keep the oath which he swore to your fathers, the LORD has brought you out with a mighty hand and redeemed you out of the house of bondage, from the hand of Pharaoh king of Egypt. <verse number="9" style="v" />Know therefore that the LORD your God himself is God, the faithful God, who keeps covenant and loving kindness to a thousand generations with those who love him and keep his commandments, <verse number="10" style="v" />and repays those who hate him to their face, to destroy them. He will not be slack to him who hates him. He will repay him to his face. <verse number="11" style="v" />You shall therefore keep the commandments, the statutes, and the ordinances which I command you today, to do them. <verse number="12" style="v" />It shall happen, because you listen to these ordinances and keep and do them, that the LORD your God will keep with you the covenant and the loving kindness which he swore to your fathers. <verse number="13" style="v" />He will love you, bless you, and multiply you. He will also bless the fruit of your body and the fruit of your ground, your grain and your new wine and your oil, the increase of your livestock and the young of your flock, in the land which he swore to your fathers to give you. <verse number="14" style="v" />You will be blessed above all peoples. There won’t be male or female barren amongst you, or amongst your livestock. <verse number="15" style="v" />The LORD will take away from you all sickness; and he will put none of the evil diseases of Egypt, which you know, on you, but will lay them on all those who hate you. <verse number="16" style="v" />You shall consume all the peoples whom the LORD your God shall deliver to you. Your eye shall not pity them. You shall not serve their gods; for that would be a snare to you. <verse number="17" style="v" />If you shall say in your heart, “These nations are more than I; how can I dispossess them?” <verse number="18" style="v" />you shall not be afraid of them. You shall remember well what the LORD your God did to Pharaoh and to all Egypt: <verse number="19" style="v" />the great trials which your eyes saw, the signs, the wonders, the mighty hand, and the outstretched arm, by which the LORD your God brought you out. So shall the LORD your God do to all the peoples of whom you are afraid. <verse number="20" style="v" />Moreover the LORD your God will send the hornet amongst them, until those who are left, and hide themselves, perish from before you. <verse number="21" style="v" />You shall not be scared of them; for the LORD your God is amongst you, a great and awesome God. <verse number="22" style="v" />The LORD your God will cast out those nations before you little by little. You may not consume them at once, lest the animals of the field increase on you. <verse number="23" style="v" />But the LORD your God will deliver them up before you, and will confuse them with a great confusion, until they are destroyed. <verse number="24" style="v" />He will deliver their kings into your hand, and you shall make their name perish from under the sky. No one will be able to stand before you until you have destroyed them. <verse number="25" style="v" />You shall burn the engraved images of their gods with fire. You shall not covet the silver or the gold that is on them, nor take it for yourself, lest you be snared in it; for it is an abomination to the LORD your God. <verse number="26" style="v" />You shall not bring an abomination into your house and become a devoted thing like it. You shall utterly detest it. You shall utterly abhor it; for it is a devoted thing.</para>
  <chapter number="8" style="c" />
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="1" style="v" />You shall observe to do all the commandments which I command you today, that you may live, and multiply, and go in and possess the land which the LORD swore to your fathers. <verse number="2" style="v" />You shall remember all the way which the LORD your God has led you these forty years in the wilderness, that he might humble you, to test you, to know what was in your heart, whether you would keep his commandments or not. <verse number="3" style="v" />He humbled you, allowed you to be hungry, and fed you with manna, which you didn’t know, neither did your fathers know, that he might teach you that man does not live by bread only, but man lives by every word that proceeds out of the LORD’s mouth. <verse number="4" style="v" />Your clothing didn’t grow old on you, neither did your foot swell, these forty years. <verse number="5" style="v" />You shall consider in your heart that as a man disciplines his son, so the LORD your God disciplines you. <verse number="6" style="v" />You shall keep the commandments of the LORD your God, to walk in his ways, and to fear him. <verse number="7" style="v" />For the LORD your God brings you into a good land, a land of brooks of water, of springs, and underground water flowing into valleys and hills; <verse number="8" style="v" />a land of wheat, barley, vines, fig trees, and pomegranates; a land of olive trees and honey; <verse number="9" style="v" />a land in which you shall eat bread without scarcity, you shall not lack anything in it; a land whose stones are iron, and out of whose hills you may dig copper. <verse number="10" style="v" />You shall eat and be full, and you shall bless the LORD your God for the good land which he has given you.</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="11" style="v" />Beware lest you forget the LORD your God, in not keeping his commandments, his ordinances, and his statutes, which I command you today; <verse number="12" style="v" />lest, when you have eaten and are full, and have built fine houses and lived in them; <verse number="13" style="v" />and when your herds and your flocks multiply, and your silver and your gold is multiplied, and all that you have is multiplied; <verse number="14" style="v" />then your heart might be lifted up, and you forget the LORD your God, who brought you out of the land of Egypt, out of the house of bondage; <verse number="15" style="v" />who led you through the great and terrible wilderness, with venomous snakes and scorpions, and thirsty ground where there was no water; who poured water for you out of the rock of flint; <verse number="16" style="v" />who fed you in the wilderness with manna, which your fathers didn’t know, that he might humble you, and that he might prove you, to do you good at your latter end; <verse number="17" style="v" />and lest you say in your heart, “My power and the might of my hand has gotten me this wealth.” <verse number="18" style="v" />But you shall remember the LORD your God, for it is he who gives you power to get wealth, that he may establish his covenant which he swore to your fathers, as it is today.</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="19" style="v" />It shall be, if you shall forget the LORD your God, and walk after other gods, and serve them and worship them, I testify against you today that you shall surely perish. <verse number="20" style="v" />As the nations that the LORD makes to perish before you, so you shall perish, because you wouldn’t listen to the LORD your God’s voice.</para>
  <chapter number="9" style="c" />
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="1" style="v" />Hear, Israel! You are to pass over the Jordan today, to go in to dispossess nations greater and mightier than yourself, cities great and fortified up to the sky, <verse number="2" style="v" />a people great and tall, the sons of the Anakim, whom you know, and of whom you have heard say, “Who can stand before the sons of Anak?” <verse number="3" style="v" />Know therefore today that the LORD your God is he who goes over before you as a devouring fire. He will destroy them and he will bring them down before you. So you shall drive them out and make them perish quickly, as the LORD has spoken to you.</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="4" style="v" />Don’t say in your heart, after the LORD your God has thrust them out from before you, “For my righteousness the LORD has brought me in to possess this land;” because the LORD drives them out before you because of the wickedness of these nations. <verse number="5" style="v" />Not for your righteousness or for the uprightness of your heart do you go in to possess their land; but for the wickedness of these nations the LORD your God does drive them out from before you, and that he may establish the word which the LORD swore to your fathers, to Abraham, to Isaac, and to Jacob. <verse number="6" style="v" />Know therefore that the LORD your God doesn’t give you this good land to possess for your righteousness, for you are a stiff-necked people. <verse number="7" style="v" />Remember, and don’t forget, how you provoked the LORD your God to wrath in the wilderness. From the day that you left the land of Egypt until you came to this place, you have been rebellious against the LORD. <verse number="8" style="v" />Also in Horeb you provoked the LORD to wrath, and the LORD was angry with you to destroy you. <verse number="9" style="v" />When I had gone up onto the mountain to receive the stone tablets, even the tablets of the covenant which the LORD made with you, then I stayed on the mountain forty days and forty nights. I neither ate bread nor drank water. <verse number="10" style="v" />The LORD delivered to me the two stone tablets written with God’s finger. On them were all the words which the LORD spoke with you on the mountain out of the middle of the fire in the day of the assembly.</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="11" style="v" />It came to pass at the end of forty days and forty nights that the LORD gave me the two stone tablets, even the tablets of the covenant. <verse number="12" style="v" />The LORD said to me, “Arise, get down quickly from here; for your people whom you have brought out of Egypt have corrupted themselves. They have quickly turned away from the way which I commanded them. They have made a molten image for themselves!”</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="13" style="v" />Furthermore the LORD spoke to me, saying, “I have seen these people, and behold, they are a stiff-necked people. <verse number="14" style="v" />Leave me alone, that I may destroy them, and blot out their name from under the sky; and I will make of you a nation mightier and greater than they.”</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="15" style="v" />So I turned and came down from the mountain, and the mountain was burning with fire. The two tablets of the covenant were in my two hands. <verse number="16" style="v" />I looked, and behold, you had sinned against the LORD your God. You had made yourselves a moulded calf. You had quickly turned away from the way which the LORD had commanded you. <verse number="17" style="v" />I took hold of the two tablets, and threw them out of my two hands, and broke them before your eyes. <verse number="18" style="v" />I fell down before the LORD, as at the first, forty days and forty nights. I neither ate bread nor drank water, because of all your sin which you sinned, in doing that which was evil in the LORD’s sight, to provoke him to anger. <verse number="19" style="v" />For I was afraid of the anger and hot displeasure with which the LORD was angry against you to destroy you. But the LORD listened to me that time also. <verse number="20" style="v" />The LORD was angry enough with Aaron to destroy him. I prayed for Aaron also at the same time. <verse number="21" style="v" />I took your sin, the calf which you had made, and burnt it with fire, and crushed it, grinding it very small, until it was as fine as dust. I threw its dust into the brook that descended out of the mountain. <verse number="22" style="v" />At Taberah, at Massah, and at Kibroth Hattaavah you provoked the LORD to wrath. <verse number="23" style="v" />When the LORD sent you from Kadesh Barnea, saying, “Go up and possess the land which I have given you,” you rebelled against the commandment of the LORD your God, and you didn’t believe him or listen to his voice. <verse number="24" style="v" />You have been rebellious against the LORD from the day that I knew you. <verse number="25" style="v" />So I fell down before the LORD the forty days and forty nights that I fell down, because the LORD had said he would destroy you. <verse number="26" style="v" />I prayed to the LORD, and said, “Lord GOD, don’t destroy your people and your inheritance that you have redeemed through your greatness, that you have brought out of Egypt with a mighty hand. <verse number="27" style="v" />Remember your servants, Abraham, Isaac, and Jacob. Don’t look at the stubbornness of this people, nor at their wickedness, nor at their sin, <verse number="28" style="v" />lest the land you brought us out from say, ‘Because the LORD was not able to bring them into the land which he promised to them, and because he hated them, he has brought them out to kill them in the wilderness.’ <verse number="29" style="v" />Yet they are your people and your inheritance, which you brought out by your great power and by your outstretched arm.”</para>
  <chapter number="10" style="c" />
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="1" style="v" />At that time the LORD said to me, “Cut two stone tablets like the first, and come up to me onto the mountain, and make an ark of wood. <verse number="2" style="v" />I will write on the tablets the words that were on the first tablets which you broke, and you shall put them in the ark.” <verse number="3" style="v" />So I made an ark of acacia wood, and cut two stone tablets like the first, and went up onto the mountain, having the two tablets in my hand. <verse number="4" style="v" />He wrote on the tablets, according to the first writing, the ten commandments, which the LORD spoke to you on the mountain out of the middle of the fire in the day of the assembly; and the LORD gave them to me. <verse number="5" style="v" />I turned and came down from the mountain, and put the tablets in the ark which I had made; and there they are as the LORD commanded me.</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="6" style="v" />(The children of Israel travelled from Beeroth Bene Jaakan to Moserah. There Aaron died, and there he was buried; and Eleazar his son ministered in the priest’s office in his place. <verse number="7" style="v" />From there they travelled to Gudgodah; and from Gudgodah to Jotbathah, a land of brooks of water. <verse number="8" style="v" />At that time the LORD set apart the tribe of Levi to bear the ark of the LORD’s covenant, to stand before the LORD to minister to him, and to bless in his name, to this day. <verse number="9" style="v" />Therefore Levi has no portion nor inheritance with his brothers; the LORD is his inheritance, according as the LORD your God spoke to him.)</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="10" style="v" />I stayed on the mountain, as at the first time, forty days and forty nights; and the LORD listened to me that time also. The LORD would not destroy you. <verse number="11" style="v" />The LORD said to me, “Arise, take your journey before the people; and they shall go in and possess the land which I swore to their fathers to give to them.”</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="12" style="v" />Now, Israel, what does the LORD your God require of you, but to fear the LORD your God, to walk in all his ways, to love him, and to serve the LORD your God with all your heart and with all your soul, <verse number="13" style="v" />to keep the LORD’s commandments and statutes, which I command you today for your good? <verse number="14" style="v" />Behold, to the LORD your God belongs heaven, the heaven of heavens, and the earth, with all that is therein. <verse number="15" style="v" />Only the LORD had a delight in your fathers to love them, and he chose their offspring after them, even you above all peoples, as it is today. <verse number="16" style="v" />Circumcise therefore the foreskin of your heart, and be no more stiff-necked. <verse number="17" style="v" />For the LORD your God, he is God of gods and Lord of lords, the great God, the mighty, and the awesome, who doesn’t respect persons or take bribes. <verse number="18" style="v" />He executes justice for the fatherless and widow and loves the foreigner in giving him food and clothing. <verse number="19" style="v" />Therefore love the foreigner, for you were foreigners in the land of Egypt. <verse number="20" style="v" />You shall fear the LORD your God. You shall serve him. You shall cling to him, and you shall swear by his name. <verse number="21" style="v" />He is your praise, and he is your God, who has done for you these great and awesome things which your eyes have seen. <verse number="22" style="v" />Your fathers went down into Egypt with seventy persons; and now the LORD your God has made you as the stars of the sky for multitude.</para>
  <chapter number="11" style="c" />
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="1" style="v" />Therefore you shall love the LORD your God, and keep his instructions, his statutes, his ordinances, and his commandments, always. <verse number="2" style="v" />Know this day—for I don’t speak with your children who have not known, and who have not seen the chastisement of the LORD your God, his greatness, his mighty hand, his outstretched arm, <verse number="3" style="v" />his signs, and his works, which he did in the middle of Egypt to Pharaoh the king of Egypt, and to all his land; <verse number="4" style="v" />and what he did to the army of Egypt, to their horses, and to their chariots; how he made the water of the Red Sea to overflow them as they pursued you, and how the LORD has destroyed them to this day; <verse number="5" style="v" />and what he did to you in the wilderness until you came to this place; <verse number="6" style="v" />and what he did to Dathan and Abiram, the sons of Eliab, the son of Reuben—how the earth opened its mouth and swallowed them up, with their households, their tents, and every living thing that followed them, in the middle of all Israel; <verse number="7" style="v" />but your eyes have seen all of the LORD’s great work which he did.</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="8" style="v" />Therefore you shall keep the entire commandment which I command you today, that you may be strong, and go in and possess the land that you go over to possess; <verse number="9" style="v" />and that you may prolong your days in the land which the LORD swore to your fathers to give to them and to their offspring, a land flowing with milk and honey. <verse number="10" style="v" />For the land, where you go in to possess isn’t like the land of Egypt that you came out of, where you sowed your seed and watered it with your foot, as a garden of herbs; <verse number="11" style="v" />but the land that you go over to possess is a land of hills and valleys which drinks water from the rain of the sky, <verse number="12" style="v" />a land which the LORD your God cares for. The LORD your God’s eyes are always on it, from the beginning of the year even to the end of the year. <verse number="13" style="v" />It shall happen, if you shall listen diligently to my commandments which I command you today, to love the LORD your God, and to serve him with all your heart and with all your soul, <verse number="14" style="v" />that I will give the rain for your land in its season, the early rain and the latter rain, that you may gather in your grain, your new wine, and your oil. <verse number="15" style="v" />I will give grass in your fields for your livestock, and you shall eat and be full. <verse number="16" style="v" />Be careful, lest your heart be deceived, and you turn away to serve other gods and worship them; <verse number="17" style="v" />and the LORD’s anger be kindled against you, and he shut up the sky so that there is no rain, and the land doesn’t yield its fruit; and you perish quickly from off the good land which the LORD gives you. <verse number="18" style="v" />Therefore you shall lay up these words of mine in your heart and in your soul. You shall bind them for a sign on your hand, and they shall be for frontlets between your eyes. <verse number="19" style="v" />You shall teach them to your children, talking of them when you sit in your house, when you walk by the way, when you lie down, and when you rise up. <verse number="20" style="v" />You shall write them on the door posts of your house and on your gates; <verse number="21" style="v" />that your days and your children’s days may be multiplied in the land which the LORD swore to your fathers to give them, as the days of the heavens above the earth. <verse number="22" style="v" />For if you shall diligently keep all these commandments which I command you—to do them, to love the LORD your God, to walk in all his ways, and to cling to him— <verse number="23" style="v" />then the LORD will drive out all these nations from before you, and you shall dispossess nations greater and mightier than yourselves. <verse number="24" style="v" />Every place on which the sole of your foot treads shall be yours: from the wilderness and Lebanon, from the river, the river Euphrates, even to the western sea shall be your border. <verse number="25" style="v" />No man will be able to stand before you. The LORD your God will lay the fear of you and the dread of you on all the land that you tread on, as he has spoken to you. <verse number="26" style="v" />Behold, I set before you today a blessing and a curse: <verse number="27" style="v" />the blessing, if you listen to the commandments of the LORD your God, which I command you today; <verse number="28" style="v" />and the curse, if you do not listen to the commandments of the LORD your God, but turn away out of the way which I command you today, to go after other gods which you have not known. <verse number="29" style="v" />It shall happen, when the LORD your God brings you into the land that you go to possess, that you shall set the blessing on Mount Gerizim, and the curse on Mount Ebal. <verse number="30" style="v" />Aren’t they beyond the Jordan, behind the way of the going down of the sun, in the land of the Canaanites who dwell in the Arabah near Gilgal, beside the oaks of Moreh? <verse number="31" style="v" />For you are to pass over the Jordan to go in to possess the land which the LORD your God gives you, and you shall possess it and dwell in it. <verse number="32" style="v" />You shall observe to do all the statutes and the ordinances which I set before you today.</para>
  <chapter number="12" style="c" />
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="1" style="v" />These are the statutes and the ordinances which you shall observe to do in the land which the LORD, the God of your fathers, has given you to possess all the days that you live on the earth. <verse number="2" style="v" />You shall surely destroy all the places in which the nations that you shall dispossess served their gods: on the high mountains, and on the hills, and under every green tree. <verse number="3" style="v" />You shall break down their altars, dash their pillars in pieces, and burn their Asherah poles with fire. You shall cut down the engraved images of their gods. You shall destroy their name out of that place. <verse number="4" style="v" />You shall not do so to the LORD your God. <verse number="5" style="v" />But to the place which the LORD your God shall choose out of all your tribes, to put his name there, you shall seek his habitation, and you shall come there. <verse number="6" style="v" />You shall bring your burnt offerings, your sacrifices, your tithes, the wave offering of your hand, your vows, your free will offerings, and the firstborn of your herd and of your flock there. <verse number="7" style="v" />There you shall eat before the LORD your God, and you shall rejoice in all that you put your hand to, you and your households, in which the LORD your God has blessed you. <verse number="8" style="v" />You shall not do all the things that we do here today, every man whatever is right in his own eyes; <verse number="9" style="v" />for you haven’t yet come to the rest and to the inheritance which the LORD your God gives you. <verse number="10" style="v" />But when you go over the Jordan and dwell in the land which the LORD your God causes you to inherit, and he gives you rest from all your enemies around you, so that you dwell in safety, <verse number="11" style="v" />then it shall happen that to the place which the LORD your God shall choose, to cause his name to dwell there, there you shall bring all that I command you: your burnt offerings, your sacrifices, your tithes, the wave offering of your hand, and all your choice vows which you vow to the LORD. <verse number="12" style="v" />You shall rejoice before the LORD your God—you, and your sons, your daughters, your male servants, your female servants, and the Levite who is within your gates, because he has no portion nor inheritance with you. <verse number="13" style="v" />Be careful that you don’t offer your burnt offerings in every place that you see; <verse number="14" style="v" />but in the place which the LORD chooses in one of your tribes, there you shall offer your burnt offerings, and there you shall do all that I command you.</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="15" style="v" />Yet you may kill and eat meat within all your gates, after all the desire of your soul, according to the LORD your God’s blessing which he has given you. The unclean and the clean may eat of it, as of the gazelle and the deer. <verse number="16" style="v" />Only you shall not eat the blood. You shall pour it out on the earth like water. <verse number="17" style="v" />You may not eat within your gates the tithe of your grain, or of your new wine, or of your oil, or the firstborn of your herd or of your flock, nor any of your vows which you vow, nor your free will offerings, nor the wave offering of your hand; <verse number="18" style="v" />but you shall eat them before the LORD your God in the place which the LORD your God shall choose: you, your son, your daughter, your male servant, your female servant, and the Levite who is within your gates. You shall rejoice before the LORD your God in all that you put your hand to. <verse number="19" style="v" />Be careful that you don’t forsake the Levite as long as you live in your land.</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="20" style="v" />When the LORD your God enlarges your border, as he has promised you, and you say, “I want to eat meat,” because your soul desires to eat meat, you may eat meat, after all the desire of your soul. <verse number="21" style="v" />If the place which the LORD your God shall choose to put his name is too far from you, then you shall kill of your herd and of your flock, which the LORD has given you, as I have commanded you; and you may eat within your gates, after all the desire of your soul. <verse number="22" style="v" />Even as the gazelle and as the deer is eaten, so you shall eat of it. The unclean and the clean may eat of it alike. <verse number="23" style="v" />Only be sure that you don’t eat the blood; for the blood is the life. You shall not eat the life with the meat. <verse number="24" style="v" />You shall not eat it. You shall pour it out on the earth like water. <verse number="25" style="v" />You shall not eat it, that it may go well with you and with your children after you, when you do that which is right in the LORD’s eyes. <verse number="26" style="v" />Only your holy things which you have, and your vows, you shall take and go to the place which the LORD shall choose. <verse number="27" style="v" />You shall offer your burnt offerings, the meat and the blood, on the LORD your God’s altar. The blood of your sacrifices shall be poured out on the LORD your God’s altar, and you shall eat the meat. <verse number="28" style="v" />Observe and hear all these words which I command you, that it may go well with you and with your children after you forever, when you do that which is good and right in the LORD your God’s eyes.</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="29" style="v" />When the LORD your God cuts off the nations from before you where you go in to dispossess them, and you dispossess them and dwell in their land, <verse number="30" style="v" />be careful that you are not ensnared to follow them after they are destroyed from before you, and that you not enquire after their gods, saying, “How do these nations serve their gods? I will do likewise.” <verse number="31" style="v" />You shall not do so to the LORD your God; for every abomination to the LORD, which he hates, they have done to their gods; for they even burn their sons and their daughters in the fire to their gods. <verse number="32" style="v" />Whatever thing I command you, that you shall observe to do. You shall not add to it, nor take away from it.</para>
  <chapter number="13" style="c" />
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="1" style="v" />If a prophet or a dreamer of dreams arises amongst you, and he gives you a sign or a wonder, <verse number="2" style="v" />and the sign or the wonder comes to pass, of which he spoke to you, saying, “Let’s go after other gods” (which you have not known) “and let’s serve them,” <verse number="3" style="v" />you shall not listen to the words of that prophet, or to that dreamer of dreams; for the LORD your God is testing you, to know whether you love the LORD your God with all your heart and with all your soul. <verse number="4" style="v" />You shall walk after the LORD your God, fear him, keep his commandments, and obey his voice. You shall serve him, and cling to him. <verse number="5" style="v" />That prophet, or that dreamer of dreams, shall be put to death, because he has spoken rebellion against the LORD your God, who brought you out of the land of Egypt and redeemed you out of the house of bondage, to draw you aside out of the way which the LORD your God commanded you to walk in. So you shall remove the evil from amongst you.</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="6" style="v" />If your brother, the son of your mother, or your son, or your daughter, or the wife of your bosom, or your friend who is as your own soul, entices you secretly, saying, “Let’s go and serve other gods”—which you have not known, you, nor your fathers; <verse number="7" style="v" />of the gods of the peoples who are around you, near to you, or far off from you, from the one end of the earth even to the other end of the earth— <verse number="8" style="v" />you shall not consent to him nor listen to him; neither shall your eye pity him, neither shall you spare, neither shall you conceal him; <verse number="9" style="v" />but you shall surely kill him. Your hand shall be first on him to put him to death, and afterwards the hands of all the people. <verse number="10" style="v" />You shall stone him to death with stones, because he has sought to draw you away from the LORD your God, who brought you out of the land of Egypt, out of the house of bondage. <verse number="11" style="v" />All Israel shall hear, and fear, and shall not do any more wickedness like this amongst you.</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="12" style="v" />If you hear about one of your cities, which the LORD your God gives you to dwell there, that <verse number="13" style="v" />certain wicked fellows have gone out from amongst you and have drawn away the inhabitants of their city, saying, “Let’s go and serve other gods,” which you have not known, <verse number="14" style="v" />then you shall enquire, investigate, and ask diligently. Behold, if it is true, and the thing certain, that such abomination was done amongst you, <verse number="15" style="v" />you shall surely strike the inhabitants of that city with the edge of the sword, destroying it utterly, with all that is therein and its livestock, with the edge of the sword. <verse number="16" style="v" />You shall gather all its plunder into the middle of its street, and shall burn with fire the city, with all of its plunder, to the LORD your God. It shall be a heap forever. It shall not be built again. <verse number="17" style="v" />Nothing of the devoted thing shall cling to your hand, that the LORD may turn from the fierceness of his anger and show you mercy, and have compassion on you and multiply you, as he has sworn to your fathers, <verse number="18" style="v" />when you listen to the LORD your God’s voice, to keep all his commandments which I command you today, to do that which is right in the LORD your God’s eyes.</para>
  <chapter number="14" style="c" />
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="1" style="v" />You are the children of the LORD your God. You shall not cut yourselves, nor make any baldness between your eyes for the dead. <verse number="2" style="v" />For you are a holy people to the LORD your God, and the LORD has chosen you to be a people for his own possession, above all peoples who are on the face of the earth.</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="3" style="v" />You shall not eat any abominable thing. <verse number="4" style="v" />These are the animals which you may eat: the ox, the sheep, the goat, <verse number="5" style="v" />the deer, the gazelle, the roebuck, the wild goat, the ibex, the antelope, and the chamois. <verse number="6" style="v" />Every animal that parts the hoof, and has the hoof split in two and chews the cud, amongst the animals, you may eat. <verse number="7" style="v" />Nevertheless these you shall not eat of them that chew the cud, or of those who have the hoof split: the camel, the hare, and the rabbit. Because they chew the cud but don’t part the hoof, they are unclean to you. <verse number="8" style="v" />The pig, because it has a split hoof but doesn’t chew the cud, is unclean to you. You shall not eat their meat. You shall not touch their carcasses. <verse number="9" style="v" />These you may eat of all that are in the waters: you may eat whatever has fins and scales. <verse number="10" style="v" />You shall not eat whatever doesn’t have fins and scales. It is unclean to you. <verse number="11" style="v" />Of all clean birds you may eat. <verse number="12" style="v" />But these are they of which you shall not eat: the eagle, the vulture, the osprey, <verse number="13" style="v" />the red kite, the falcon, the kite of any kind, <verse number="14" style="v" />every raven of any kind, <verse number="15" style="v" />the ostrich, the owl, the seagull, the hawk of any kind, <verse number="16" style="v" />the little owl, the great owl, the horned owl, <verse number="17" style="v" />the pelican, the vulture, the cormorant, <verse number="18" style="v" />the stork, the heron after its kind, the hoopoe, and the bat. <verse number="19" style="v" />All winged creeping things are unclean to you. They shall not be eaten. <verse number="20" style="v" />Of all clean birds you may eat.</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="21" style="v" />You shall not eat of anything that dies of itself. You may give it to the foreigner living amongst you who is within your gates, that he may eat it; or you may sell it to a foreigner; for you are a holy people to the LORD your God.</para>
  <para style="p">You shall not boil a young goat in its mother’s milk.</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="22" style="v" />You shall surely tithe all the increase of your seed, that which comes out of the field year by year. <verse number="23" style="v" />You shall eat before the LORD your God, in the place which he chooses to cause his name to dwell, the tithe of your grain, of your new wine, and of your oil, and the firstborn of your herd and of your flock; that you may learn to fear the LORD your God always. <verse number="24" style="v" />If the way is too long for you, so that you are not able to carry it because the place which the LORD your God shall choose to set his name there is too far from you, when the LORD your God blesses you, <verse number="25" style="v" />then you shall turn it into money, bind up the money in your hand, and shall go to the place which the LORD your God shall choose. <verse number="26" style="v" />You shall trade the money for whatever your soul desires: for cattle, or for sheep, or for wine, or for strong drink, or for whatever your soul asks of you. You shall eat there before the LORD your God, and you shall rejoice, you and your household. <verse number="27" style="v" />You shall not forsake the Levite who is within your gates, for he has no portion nor inheritance with you. <verse number="28" style="v" />At the end of every three years you shall bring all the tithe of your increase in the same year, and shall store it within your gates. <verse number="29" style="v" />The Levite, because he has no portion nor inheritance with you, as well as the foreigner living amongst you, the fatherless, and the widow who are within your gates shall come, and shall eat and be satisfied; that the LORD your God may bless you in all the work of your hand which you do.</para>
  <chapter number="15" style="c" />
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="1" style="v" />At the end of every seven years, you shall cancel debts. <verse number="2" style="v" />This is the way it shall be done: every creditor shall release that which he has lent to his neighbour. He shall not require payment from his neighbour and his brother, because the LORD’s release has been proclaimed. <verse number="3" style="v" />Of a foreigner you may require it; but whatever of yours is with your brother, your hand shall release. <verse number="4" style="v" />However there will be no poor with you (for the LORD will surely bless you in the land which the LORD your God gives you for an inheritance to possess) <verse number="5" style="v" />if only you diligently listen to the LORD your God’s voice, to observe to do all this commandment which I command you today. <verse number="6" style="v" />For the LORD your God will bless you, as he promised you. You will lend to many nations, but you will not borrow. You will rule over many nations, but they will not rule over you. <verse number="7" style="v" />If a poor man, one of your brothers, is with you within any of your gates in your land which the LORD your God gives you, you shall not harden your heart, nor shut your hand from your poor brother; <verse number="8" style="v" />but you shall surely open your hand to him, and shall surely lend him sufficient for his need, which he lacks. <verse number="9" style="v" />Beware that there not be a wicked thought in your heart, saying, “The seventh year, the year of release, is at hand,” and your eye be evil against your poor brother and you give him nothing; and he cry to the LORD against you, and it be sin to you. <verse number="10" style="v" />You shall surely give, and your heart shall not be grieved when you give to him, because it is for this thing the LORD your God will bless you in all your work and in all that you put your hand to. <verse number="11" style="v" />For the poor will never cease out of the land. Therefore I command you to surely open your hand to your brother, to your needy, and to your poor, in your land. <verse number="12" style="v" />If your brother, a Hebrew man, or a Hebrew woman, is sold to you and serves you six years, then in the seventh year you shall let him go free from you. <verse number="13" style="v" />When you let him go free from you, you shall not let him go empty. <verse number="14" style="v" />You shall furnish him liberally out of your flock, out of your threshing floor, and out of your wine press. As the LORD your God has blessed you, you shall give to him. <verse number="15" style="v" />You shall remember that you were a slave in the land of Egypt, and the LORD your God redeemed you. Therefore I command you this thing today. <verse number="16" style="v" />It shall be, if he tells you, “I will not go out from you,” because he loves you and your house, because he is well with you, <verse number="17" style="v" />then you shall take an awl, and thrust it through his ear to the door, and he shall be your servant forever. Also to your female servant you shall do likewise. <verse number="18" style="v" />It shall not seem hard to you when you let him go free from you, for he has been double the value of a hired hand as he served you six years. The LORD your God will bless you in all that you do. <verse number="19" style="v" />You shall dedicate all the firstborn males that are born of your herd and of your flock to the LORD your God. You shall do no work with the firstborn of your herd, nor shear the firstborn of your flock. <verse number="20" style="v" />You shall eat it before the LORD your God year by year in the place which the LORD shall choose, you and your household. <verse number="21" style="v" />If it has any defect—is lame or blind, or has any defect whatever, you shall not sacrifice it to the LORD your God. <verse number="22" style="v" />You shall eat it within your gates. The unclean and the clean shall eat it alike, as the gazelle and as the deer. <verse number="23" style="v" />Only you shall not eat its blood. You shall pour it out on the ground like water.</para>
  <chapter number="16" style="c" />
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="1" style="v" />Observe the month of Abib, and keep the Passover to the LORD your God; for in the month of Abib the LORD your God brought you out of Egypt by night. <verse number="2" style="v" />You shall sacrifice the Passover to the LORD your God, of the flock and the herd, in the place which the LORD shall choose to cause his name to dwell there. <verse number="3" style="v" />You shall eat no leavened bread with it. You shall eat unleavened bread with it seven days, even the bread of affliction (for you came out of the land of Egypt in haste) that you may remember the day when you came out of the land of Egypt all the days of your life. <verse number="4" style="v" />No yeast shall be seen with you in all your borders seven days; neither shall any of the meat, which you sacrifice the first day at evening, remain all night until the morning. <verse number="5" style="v" />You may not sacrifice the Passover within any of your gates which the LORD your God gives you; <verse number="6" style="v" />but at the place which the LORD your God shall choose to cause his name to dwell in, there you shall sacrifice the Passover at evening, at the going down of the sun, at the season that you came out of Egypt. <verse number="7" style="v" />You shall roast and eat it in the place which the LORD your God chooses. In the morning you shall return to your tents. <verse number="8" style="v" />Six days you shall eat unleavened bread. On the seventh day shall be a solemn assembly to the LORD your God. You shall do no work.</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="9" style="v" />You shall count for yourselves seven weeks. From the time you begin to put the sickle to the standing grain you shall begin to count seven weeks. <verse number="10" style="v" />You shall keep the feast of weeks to the LORD your God with a tribute of a free will offering of your hand, which you shall give according to how the LORD your God blesses you. <verse number="11" style="v" />You shall rejoice before the LORD your God: you, your son, your daughter, your male servant, your female servant, the Levite who is within your gates, the foreigner, the fatherless, and the widow who are amongst you, in the place which the LORD your God shall choose to cause his name to dwell there. <verse number="12" style="v" />You shall remember that you were a slave in Egypt. You shall observe and do these statutes.</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="13" style="v" />You shall keep the feast of booths seven days, after you have gathered in from your threshing floor and from your wine press. <verse number="14" style="v" />You shall rejoice in your feast, you, your son, your daughter, your male servant, your female servant, the Levite, the foreigner, the fatherless, and the widow who are within your gates. <verse number="15" style="v" />You shall keep a feast to the LORD your God seven days in the place which the LORD chooses, because the LORD your God will bless you in all your increase and in all the work of your hands, and you shall be altogether joyful. <verse number="16" style="v" />Three times in a year all of your males shall appear before the LORD your God in the place which he chooses: in the feast of unleavened bread, in the feast of weeks, and in the feast of booths. They shall not appear before the LORD empty. <verse number="17" style="v" />Every man shall give as he is able, according to the LORD your God’s blessing which he has given you. <verse number="18" style="v" />You shall make judges and officers in all your gates, which the LORD your God gives you, according to your tribes; and they shall judge the people with righteous judgement. <verse number="19" style="v" />You shall not pervert justice. You shall not show partiality. You shall not take a bribe, for a bribe blinds the eyes of the wise and perverts the words of the righteous. <verse number="20" style="v" />You shall follow that which is altogether just, that you may live and inherit the land which the LORD your God gives you. <verse number="21" style="v" />You shall not plant for yourselves an Asherah of any kind of tree beside the LORD your God’s altar, which you shall make for yourselves. <verse number="22" style="v" />Neither shall you set yourself up a sacred stone which the LORD your God hates.</para>
  <chapter number="17" style="c" />
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="1" style="v" />You shall not sacrifice to the LORD your God an ox or a sheep in which is a defect or anything evil; for that is an abomination to the LORD your God.</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="2" style="v" />If there is found amongst you, within any of your gates which the LORD your God gives you, a man or woman who does that which is evil in the LORD your God’s sight in transgressing his covenant, <verse number="3" style="v" />and has gone and served other gods and worshipped them, or the sun, or the moon, or any of the stars of the sky, which I have not commanded, <verse number="4" style="v" />and you are told, and you have heard of it, then you shall enquire diligently. Behold, if it is true, and the thing certain, that such abomination is done in Israel, <verse number="5" style="v" />then you shall bring out that man or that woman who has done this evil thing to your gates, even that same man or woman; and you shall stone them to death with stones. <verse number="6" style="v" />At the mouth of two witnesses, or three witnesses, he who is to die shall be put to death. At the mouth of one witness he shall not be put to death. <verse number="7" style="v" />The hands of the witnesses shall be first on him to put him to death, and afterward the hands of all the people. So you shall remove the evil from amongst you.</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="8" style="v" />If there arises a matter too hard for you in judgement, between blood and blood, between plea and plea, and between stroke and stroke, being matters of controversy within your gates, then you shall arise, and go up to the place which the LORD your God chooses. <verse number="9" style="v" />You shall come to the priests who are Levites and to the judge who shall be in those days. You shall enquire, and they shall give you the verdict. <verse number="10" style="v" />You shall do according to the decisions of the verdict which they shall give you from that place which the LORD chooses. You shall observe to do according to all that they shall teach you. <verse number="11" style="v" />According to the decisions of the law which they shall teach you, and according to the judgement which they shall tell you, you shall do. You shall not turn away from the sentence which they announce to you, to the right hand, nor to the left. <verse number="12" style="v" />The man who does presumptuously in not listening to the priest who stands to minister there before the LORD your God, or to the judge, even that man shall die. You shall put away the evil from Israel. <verse number="13" style="v" />All the people shall hear and fear, and do no more presumptuously.</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="14" style="v" />When you have come to the land which the LORD your God gives you, and possess it and dwell in it, and say, “I will set a king over me, like all the nations that are around me,” <verse number="15" style="v" />you shall surely set him whom the LORD your God chooses as king over yourselves. You shall set as king over you one from amongst your brothers. You may not put a foreigner over you, who is not your brother. <verse number="16" style="v" />Only he shall not multiply horses to himself, nor cause the people to return to Egypt, to the end that he may multiply horses; because the LORD has said to you, “You shall not go back that way again.” <verse number="17" style="v" />He shall not multiply wives to himself, that his heart not turn away. He shall not greatly multiply to himself silver and gold.</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="18" style="v" />It shall be, when he sits on the throne of his kingdom, that he shall write himself a copy of this law in a book, out of that which is before the Levitical priests. <verse number="19" style="v" />It shall be with him, and he shall read from it all the days of his life, that he may learn to fear the LORD his God, to keep all the words of this law and these statutes, to do them; <verse number="20" style="v" />that his heart not be lifted up above his brothers, and that he not turn away from the commandment to the right hand, or to the left, to the end that he may prolong his days in his kingdom, he and his children, in the middle of Israel.</para>
  <chapter number="18" style="c" />
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="1" style="v" />The priests and the Levites—all the tribe of Levi—shall have no portion nor inheritance with Israel. They shall eat the offerings of the LORD made by fire and his portion. <verse number="2" style="v" />They shall have no inheritance amongst their brothers. The LORD is their inheritance, as he has spoken to them. <verse number="3" style="v" />This shall be the priests’ due from the people, from those who offer a sacrifice, whether it be ox or sheep, that they shall give to the priest: the shoulder, the two cheeks, and the inner parts. <verse number="4" style="v" />You shall give him the first fruits of your grain, of your new wine, and of your oil, and the first of the fleece of your sheep. <verse number="5" style="v" />For the LORD your God has chosen him out of all your tribes to stand to minister in the LORD’s name, him and his sons forever.</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="6" style="v" />If a Levite comes from any of your gates out of all Israel where he lives, and comes with all the desire of his soul to the place which the LORD shall choose, <verse number="7" style="v" />then he shall minister in the name of the LORD his God, as all his brothers the Levites do, who stand there before the LORD. <verse number="8" style="v" />They shall have like portions to eat, in addition to that which comes from the sale of his family possessions.</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="9" style="v" />When you have come into the land which the LORD your God gives you, you shall not learn to imitate the abominations of those nations. <verse number="10" style="v" />There shall not be found with you anyone who makes his son or his daughter to pass through the fire, one who uses divination, one who tells fortunes, or an enchanter, or a sorcerer, <verse number="11" style="v" />or a charmer, or someone who consults with a familiar spirit, or a wizard, or a necromancer. <verse number="12" style="v" />For whoever does these things is an abomination to the LORD. Because of these abominations, the LORD your God drives them out from before you. <verse number="13" style="v" />You shall be blameless with the LORD your God. <verse number="14" style="v" />For these nations that you shall dispossess listen to those who practise sorcery and to diviners; but as for you, the LORD your God has not allowed you so to do. <verse number="15" style="v" />The LORD your God will raise up to you a prophet from amongst you, of your brothers, like me. You shall listen to him. <verse number="16" style="v" />This is according to all that you desired of the LORD your God in Horeb in the day of the assembly, saying, “Let me not hear again the LORD my God’s voice, neither let me see this great fire any more, that I not die.”</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="17" style="v" />The LORD said to me, “They have well said that which they have spoken. <verse number="18" style="v" />I will raise them up a prophet from amongst their brothers, like you. I will put my words in his mouth, and he shall speak to them all that I shall command him. <verse number="19" style="v" />It shall happen, that whoever will not listen to my words which he shall speak in my name, I will require it of him. <verse number="20" style="v" />But the prophet who speaks a word presumptuously in my name, which I have not commanded him to speak, or who speaks in the name of other gods, that same prophet shall die.”</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="21" style="v" />You may say in your heart, “How shall we know the word which the LORD has not spoken?” <verse number="22" style="v" />When a prophet speaks in the LORD’s name, if the thing doesn’t follow, nor happen, that is the thing which the LORD has not spoken. The prophet has spoken it presumptuously. You shall not be afraid of him.</para>
  <chapter number="19" style="c" />
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="1" style="v" />When the LORD your God cuts off the nations whose land the LORD your God gives you, and you succeed them and dwell in their cities and in their houses, <verse number="2" style="v" />you shall set apart three cities for yourselves in the middle of your land, which the LORD your God gives you to possess. <verse number="3" style="v" />You shall prepare the way, and divide the borders of your land which the LORD your God causes you to inherit into three parts, that every man slayer may flee there. <verse number="4" style="v" />This is the case of the man slayer who shall flee there and live: Whoever kills his neighbour unintentionally, and didn’t hate him in time past— <verse number="5" style="v" />as when a man goes into the forest with his neighbour to chop wood and his hand swings the axe to cut down the tree, and the head slips from the handle and hits his neighbour so that he dies—he shall flee to one of these cities and live. <verse number="6" style="v" />Otherwise, the avenger of blood might pursue the man slayer while hot anger is in his heart and overtake him, because the way is long, and strike him mortally, even though he was not worthy of death, because he didn’t hate him in time past. <verse number="7" style="v" />Therefore I command you to set apart three cities for yourselves. <verse number="8" style="v" />If the LORD your God enlarges your border, as he has sworn to your fathers, and gives you all the land which he promised to give to your fathers; <verse number="9" style="v" />and if you keep all this commandment to do it, which I command you today, to love the LORD your God, and to walk ever in his ways, then you shall add three cities more for yourselves, in addition to these three. <verse number="10" style="v" />This is so that innocent blood will not be shed in the middle of your land which the LORD your God gives you for an inheritance, leaving blood guilt on you. <verse number="11" style="v" />But if any man hates his neighbour, lies in wait for him, rises up against him, strikes him mortally so that he dies, and he flees into one of these cities; <verse number="12" style="v" />then the elders of his city shall send and bring him there, and deliver him into the hand of the avenger of blood, that he may die. <verse number="13" style="v" />Your eye shall not pity him, but you shall purge the innocent blood from Israel that it may go well with you.</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="14" style="v" />You shall not remove your neighbour’s landmark, which they of old time have set, in your inheritance which you shall inherit, in the land that the LORD your God gives you to possess.</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="15" style="v" />One witness shall not rise up against a man for any iniquity, or for any sin that he sins. At the mouth of two witnesses, or at the mouth of three witnesses, shall a matter be established. <verse number="16" style="v" />If an unrighteous witness rises up against any man to testify against him of wrongdoing, <verse number="17" style="v" />then both the men, between whom the controversy is, shall stand before the LORD, before the priests and the judges who shall be in those days; <verse number="18" style="v" />and the judges shall make diligent inquisition; and behold, if the witness is a false witness, and has testified falsely against his brother, <verse number="19" style="v" />then you shall do to him as he had thought to do to his brother. So you shall remove the evil from amongst you. <verse number="20" style="v" />Those who remain shall hear, and fear, and will never again commit any such evil amongst you. <verse number="21" style="v" />Your eyes shall not pity: life for life, eye for eye, tooth for tooth, hand for hand, foot for foot.</para>
  <chapter number="20" style="c" />
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="1" style="v" />When you go out to battle against your enemies, and see horses, chariots, and a people more numerous than you, you shall not be afraid of them; for the LORD your God is with you, who brought you up out of the land of Egypt. <verse number="2" style="v" />It shall be, when you draw near to the battle, that the priest shall approach and speak to the people, <verse number="3" style="v" />and shall tell them, “Hear, Israel, you draw near today to battle against your enemies. Don’t let your heart faint! Don’t be afraid, nor tremble, neither be scared of them; <verse number="4" style="v" />for the LORD your God is he who goes with you, to fight for you against your enemies, to save you.”</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="5" style="v" />The officers shall speak to the people, saying, “What man is there who has built a new house, and has not dedicated it? Let him go and return to his house, lest he die in the battle, and another man dedicate it. <verse number="6" style="v" />What man is there who has planted a vineyard, and has not used its fruit? Let him go and return to his house, lest he die in the battle, and another man use its fruit. <verse number="7" style="v" />What man is there who has pledged to be married to a wife, and has not taken her? Let him go and return to his house, lest he die in the battle, and another man take her.” <verse number="8" style="v" />The officers shall speak further to the people, and they shall say, “What man is there who is fearful and faint-hearted? Let him go and return to his house, lest his brother’s heart melt as his heart.” <verse number="9" style="v" />It shall be, when the officers have finished speaking to the people, that they shall appoint captains of armies at the head of the people.</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="10" style="v" />When you draw near to a city to fight against it, then proclaim peace to it. <verse number="11" style="v" />It shall be, if it gives you answer of peace and opens to you, then it shall be that all the people who are found therein shall become forced labourers to you, and shall serve you. <verse number="12" style="v" />If it will make no peace with you, but will make war against you, then you shall besiege it. <verse number="13" style="v" />When the LORD your God delivers it into your hand, you shall strike every male of it with the edge of the sword; <verse number="14" style="v" />but the women, the little ones, the livestock, and all that is in the city, even all its plunder, you shall take for plunder for yourself. You may use the plunder of your enemies, which the LORD your God has given you. <verse number="15" style="v" />Thus you shall do to all the cities which are very far off from you, which are not of the cities of these nations. <verse number="16" style="v" />But of the cities of these peoples that the LORD your God gives you for an inheritance, you shall save alive nothing that breathes; <verse number="17" style="v" />but you shall utterly destroy them: the Hittite, the Amorite, the Canaanite, the Perizzite, the Hivite, and the Jebusite, as the LORD your God has commanded you; <verse number="18" style="v" />that they not teach you to follow all their abominations, which they have done for their gods; so would you sin against the LORD your God. <verse number="19" style="v" />When you shall besiege a city a long time, in making war against it to take it, you shall not destroy its trees by wielding an axe against them; for you may eat of them. You shall not cut them down, for is the tree of the field man, that it should be besieged by you? <verse number="20" style="v" />Only the trees that you know are not trees for food, you shall destroy and cut them down. You shall build bulwarks against the city that makes war with you, until it falls.</para>
  <chapter number="21" style="c" />
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="1" style="v" />If someone is found slain in the land which the LORD your God gives you to possess, lying in the field, and it isn’t known who has struck him, <verse number="2" style="v" />then your elders and your judges shall come out, and they shall measure to the cities which are around him who is slain. <verse number="3" style="v" />It shall be that the elders of the city which is nearest to the slain man shall take a heifer of the herd, which hasn’t been worked with and which has not drawn in the yoke. <verse number="4" style="v" />The elders of that city shall bring the heifer down to a valley with running water, which is neither ploughed nor sown, and shall break the heifer’s neck there in the valley. <verse number="5" style="v" />The priests the sons of Levi shall come near, for them the LORD your God has chosen to minister to him, and to bless in the LORD’s name; and according to their word shall every controversy and every assault be decided. <verse number="6" style="v" />All the elders of that city which is nearest to the slain man shall wash their hands over the heifer whose neck was broken in the valley. <verse number="7" style="v" />They shall answer and say, “Our hands have not shed this blood, neither have our eyes seen it. <verse number="8" style="v" />Forgive, the LORD, your people Israel, whom you have redeemed, and don’t allow innocent blood amongst your people Israel.” The blood shall be forgiven them. <verse number="9" style="v" />So you shall put away the innocent blood from amongst you, when you shall do that which is right in the LORD’s eyes.</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="10" style="v" />When you go out to battle against your enemies, and the LORD your God delivers them into your hands and you carry them away captive, <verse number="11" style="v" />and see amongst the captives a beautiful woman, and you are attracted to her, and desire to take her as your wife, <verse number="12" style="v" />then you shall bring her home to your house. She shall shave her head and trim her nails. <verse number="13" style="v" />She shall take off the clothing of her captivity, and shall remain in your house, and bewail her father and her mother a full month. After that you shall go in to her and be her husband, and she shall be your wife. <verse number="14" style="v" />It shall be, if you have no delight in her, then you shall let her go where she desires; but you shall not sell her at all for money. You shall not deal with her as a slave, because you have humbled her.</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="15" style="v" />If a man has two wives, the one beloved and the other hated, and they have borne him children, both the beloved and the hated, and if the firstborn son is hers who was hated, <verse number="16" style="v" />then it shall be, in the day that he causes his sons to inherit that which he has, that he may not give the son of the beloved the rights of the firstborn before the son of the hated, who is the firstborn; <verse number="17" style="v" />but he shall acknowledge the firstborn, the son of the hated, by giving him a double portion of all that he has; for he is the beginning of his strength. The right of the firstborn is his.</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="18" style="v" />If a man has a stubborn and rebellious son who will not obey the voice of his father or the voice of his mother, and though they chasten him, will not listen to them, <verse number="19" style="v" />then his father and his mother shall take hold of him and bring him out to the elders of his city and to the gate of his place. <verse number="20" style="v" />They shall tell the elders of his city, “This our son is stubborn and rebellious. He will not obey our voice. He is a glutton and a drunkard.” <verse number="21" style="v" />All the men of his city shall stone him to death with stones. So you shall remove the evil from amongst you. All Israel shall hear, and fear.</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="22" style="v" />If a man has committed a sin worthy of death, and he is put to death, and you hang him on a tree, <verse number="23" style="v" />his body shall not remain all night on the tree, but you shall surely bury him the same day; for he who is hanged is accursed of God. Don’t defile your land which the LORD your God gives you for an inheritance.</para>
  <chapter number="22" style="c" />
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="1" style="v" />You shall not see your brother’s ox or his sheep go astray and hide yourself from them. You shall surely bring them again to your brother. <verse number="2" style="v" />If your brother isn’t near to you, or if you don’t know him, then you shall bring it home to your house, and it shall be with you until your brother comes looking for it, and you shall restore it to him. <verse number="3" style="v" />So you shall do with his donkey. So you shall do with his garment. So you shall do with every lost thing of your brother’s, which he has lost and you have found. You may not hide yourself. <verse number="4" style="v" />You shall not see your brother’s donkey or his ox fallen down by the way, and hide yourself from them. You shall surely help him to lift them up again.</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="5" style="v" />A woman shall not wear men’s clothing, neither shall a man put on women’s clothing; for whoever does these things is an abomination to the LORD your God.</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="6" style="v" />If you come across a bird’s nest on the way, in any tree or on the ground, with young ones or eggs, and the hen sitting on the young, or on the eggs, you shall not take the hen with the young. <verse number="7" style="v" />You shall surely let the hen go, but the young you may take for yourself, that it may be well with you, and that you may prolong your days.</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="8" style="v" />When you build a new house, then you shall make a railing around your roof, so that you don’t bring blood on your house if anyone falls from there.</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="9" style="v" />You shall not sow your vineyard with two kinds of seed, lest all the fruit be defiled, the seed which you have sown, and the increase of the vineyard. <verse number="10" style="v" />You shall not plough with an ox and a donkey together. <verse number="11" style="v" />You shall not wear clothes of wool and linen woven together.</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="12" style="v" />You shall make yourselves fringes<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">22:12 </char><char style="ft" closed="false">or, tassels</char></note> on the four corners of your cloak with which you cover yourself.</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="13" style="v" />If any man takes a wife, and goes in to her, hates her, <verse number="14" style="v" />accuses her of shameful things, gives her a bad name, and says, “I took this woman, and when I came near to her, I didn’t find in her the tokens of virginity;” <verse number="15" style="v" />then the young lady’s father and mother shall take and bring the tokens of the young lady’s virginity to the elders of the city in the gate. <verse number="16" style="v" />The young lady’s father shall tell the elders, “I gave my daughter to this man as his wife, and he hates her. <verse number="17" style="v" />Behold, he has accused her of shameful things, saying, ‘I didn’t find in your daughter the tokens of virginity;’ and yet these are the tokens of my daughter’s virginity.” They shall spread the cloth before the elders of the city. <verse number="18" style="v" />The elders of that city shall take the man and chastise him. <verse number="19" style="v" />They shall fine him one hundred shekels of silver,<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">22:19 </char><char style="ft" closed="false">A shekel is about 10 grams or about 0.35 ounces, so 100 shekels is about a kilogram or 2.2 pounds.</char></note> and give them to the father of the young lady, because he has given a bad name to a virgin of Israel. She shall be his wife. He may not put her away all his days.</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="20" style="v" />But if this thing is true, that the tokens of virginity were not found in the young lady, <verse number="21" style="v" />then they shall bring out the young lady to the door of her father’s house, and the men of her city shall stone her to death with stones, because she has done folly in Israel, to play the prostitute in her father’s house. So you shall remove the evil from amongst you.</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="22" style="v" />If a man is found lying with a woman married to a husband, then they shall both die, the man who lay with the woman and the woman. So you shall remove the evil from Israel. <verse number="23" style="v" />If there is a young lady who is a virgin pledged to be married to a husband, and a man finds her in the city, and lies with her, <verse number="24" style="v" />then you shall bring them both out to the gate of that city, and you shall stone them to death with stones; the lady, because she didn’t cry, being in the city; and the man, because he has humbled his neighbour’s wife. So you shall remove the evil from amongst you. <verse number="25" style="v" />But if the man finds the lady who is pledged to be married in the field, and the man forces her and lies with her, then only the man who lay with her shall die; <verse number="26" style="v" />but to the lady you shall do nothing. There is in the lady no sin worthy of death; for as when a man rises against his neighbour and kills him, even so is this matter; <verse number="27" style="v" />for he found her in the field, the pledged to be married lady cried, and there was no one to save her. <verse number="28" style="v" />If a man finds a lady who is a virgin, who is not pledged to be married, grabs her and lies with her, and they are found, <verse number="29" style="v" />then the man who lay with her shall give to the lady’s father fifty shekels<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">22:29 </char><char style="ft" closed="false">A shekel is about 10 grams or about 0.35 ounces.</char></note> of silver. She shall be his wife, because he has humbled her. He may not put her away all his days. <verse number="30" style="v" />A man shall not take his father’s wife, and shall not uncover his father’s skirt.</para>
  <chapter number="23" style="c" />
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="1" style="v" />He who is emasculated by crushing or cutting shall not enter into the LORD’s assembly. <verse number="2" style="v" />A person born of a forbidden union shall not enter into the LORD’s assembly; even to the tenth generation shall no one of his enter into the LORD’s assembly. <verse number="3" style="v" />An Ammonite or a Moabite shall not enter into the LORD’s assembly; even to the tenth generation shall no one belonging to them enter into the LORD’s assembly forever, <verse number="4" style="v" />because they didn’t meet you with bread and with water on the way when you came out of Egypt, and because they hired against you Balaam the son of Beor from Pethor of Mesopotamia, to curse you. <verse number="5" style="v" />Nevertheless the LORD your God wouldn’t listen to Balaam, but the LORD your God turned the curse into a blessing to you, because the LORD your God loved you. <verse number="6" style="v" />You shall not seek their peace nor their prosperity all your days forever. <verse number="7" style="v" />You shall not abhor an Edomite, for he is your brother. You shall not abhor an Egyptian, because you lived as a foreigner in his land. <verse number="8" style="v" />The children of the third generation who are born to them may enter into the LORD’s assembly.</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="9" style="v" />When you go out and camp against your enemies, then you shall keep yourselves from every evil thing. <verse number="10" style="v" />If there is amongst you any man who is not clean by reason of that which happens to him by night, then shall he go outside of the camp. He shall not come within the camp; <verse number="11" style="v" />but it shall be, when evening comes, he shall bathe himself in water. When the sun is down, he shall come within the camp. <verse number="12" style="v" />You shall have a place also outside of the camp where you go relieve yourself. <verse number="13" style="v" />You shall have a trowel amongst your weapons. It shall be, when you relieve yourself, you shall dig with it, and shall turn back and cover your excrement; <verse number="14" style="v" />for the LORD your God walks in the middle of your camp, to deliver you, and to give up your enemies before you. Therefore your camp shall be holy, that he may not see an unclean thing in you, and turn away from you.</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="15" style="v" />You shall not deliver to his master a servant who has escaped from his master to you. <verse number="16" style="v" />He shall dwell with you, amongst you, in the place which he shall choose within one of your gates, where it pleases him best. You shall not oppress him.</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="17" style="v" />There shall be no prostitute of the daughters of Israel, neither shall there be a sodomite of the sons of Israel. <verse number="18" style="v" />You shall not bring the hire of a prostitute, or the wages of a male prostitute,<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">23:18 </char><char style="ft" closed="false">literally, dog</char></note> into the house of the LORD your God for any vow; for both of these are an abomination to the LORD your God.</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="19" style="v" />You shall not lend on interest to your brother: interest of money, interest of food, interest of anything that is lent on interest. <verse number="20" style="v" />You may charge a foreigner interest; but you shall not charge your brother interest, that the LORD your God may bless you in all that you put your hand to, in the land where you go in to possess it.</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="21" style="v" />When you vow a vow to the LORD your God, you shall not be slack to pay it, for the LORD your God will surely require it of you; and it would be sin in you. <verse number="22" style="v" />But if you refrain from making a vow, it shall be no sin in you. <verse number="23" style="v" />You shall observe and do that which has gone out of your lips. Whatever you have vowed to the LORD your God as a free will offering, which you have promised with your mouth, you must do. <verse number="24" style="v" />When you come into your neighbour’s vineyard, then you may eat your fill of grapes at your own pleasure; but you shall not put any in your container. <verse number="25" style="v" />When you come into your neighbour’s standing grain, then you may pluck the ears with your hand; but you shall not use a sickle on your neighbour’s standing grain.</para>
  <chapter number="24" style="c" />
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="1" style="v" />When a man takes a wife and marries her, then it shall be, if she finds no favour in his eyes because he has found some unseemly thing in her, that he shall write her a certificate of divorce, put it in her hand, and send her out of his house. <verse number="2" style="v" />When she has departed out of his house, she may go and be another man’s wife. <verse number="3" style="v" />If the latter husband hates her, and write her a certificate of divorce, puts it in her hand, and sends her out of his house; or if the latter husband dies, who took her to be his wife; <verse number="4" style="v" />her former husband, who sent her away, may not take her again to be his wife after she is defiled; for that would be an abomination to the LORD. You shall not cause the land to sin, which the LORD your God gives you for an inheritance. <verse number="5" style="v" />When a man takes a new wife, he shall not go out in the army, neither shall he be assigned any business. He shall be free at home one year, and shall cheer his wife whom he has taken.</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="6" style="v" />No man shall take the mill or the upper millstone as a pledge, for he takes a life in pledge.</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="7" style="v" />If a man is found stealing any of his brothers of the children of Israel, and he deals with him as a slave, or sells him, then that thief shall die. So you shall remove the evil from amongst you.</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="8" style="v" />Be careful in the plague of leprosy, that you observe diligently and do according to all that the Levitical priests teach you. As I commanded them, so you shall observe to do. <verse number="9" style="v" />Remember what the LORD your God did to Miriam, by the way as you came out of Egypt.</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="10" style="v" />When you lend your neighbour any kind of loan, you shall not go into his house to get his pledge. <verse number="11" style="v" />You shall stand outside, and the man to whom you lend shall bring the pledge outside to you. <verse number="12" style="v" />If he is a poor man, you shall not sleep with his pledge. <verse number="13" style="v" />You shall surely restore to him the pledge when the sun goes down, that he may sleep in his garment and bless you. It shall be righteousness to you before the LORD your God.</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="14" style="v" />You shall not oppress a hired servant who is poor and needy, whether he is one of your brothers or one of the foreigners who are in your land within your gates. <verse number="15" style="v" />In his day you shall give him his wages, neither shall the sun go down on it; for he is poor and sets his heart on it; lest he cry against you to the LORD, and it be sin to you.</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="16" style="v" />The fathers shall not be put to death for the children, neither shall the children be put to death for the fathers. Every man shall be put to death for his own sin.</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="17" style="v" />You shall not deprive the foreigner or the fatherless of justice, nor take a widow’s clothing in pledge; <verse number="18" style="v" />but you shall remember that you were a slave in Egypt, and the LORD your God redeemed you there. Therefore I command you to do this thing.</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="19" style="v" />When you reap your harvest in your field, and have forgotten a sheaf in the field, you shall not go again to get it. It shall be for the foreigner, for the fatherless, and for the widow, that the LORD your God may bless you in all the work of your hands. <verse number="20" style="v" />When you beat your olive tree, you shall not go over the boughs again. It shall be for the foreigner, for the fatherless, and for the widow.</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="21" style="v" />When you harvest your vineyard, you shall not glean it after yourselves. It shall be for the foreigner, for the fatherless, and for the widow. <verse number="22" style="v" />You shall remember that you were a slave in the land of Egypt. Therefore I command you to do this thing.</para>
  <chapter number="25" style="c" />
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="1" style="v" />If there is a controversy between men, and they come to judgement and the judges judge them, then they shall justify the righteous and condemn the wicked. <verse number="2" style="v" />It shall be, if the wicked man is worthy to be beaten, that the judge shall cause him to lie down and to be beaten before his face, according to his wickedness, by number. <verse number="3" style="v" />He may sentence him to no more than forty stripes. He shall not give more, lest if he should give more and beat him more than that many stripes, then your brother will be degraded in your sight.</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="4" style="v" />You shall not muzzle the ox when he treads out the grain.</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="5" style="v" />If brothers dwell together, and one of them dies and has no son, the wife of the dead shall not be married outside to a stranger. Her husband’s brother shall go in to her, and take her as his wife, and perform the duty of a husband’s brother to her. <verse number="6" style="v" />It shall be that the firstborn whom she bears shall succeed in the name of his brother who is dead, that his name not be blotted out of Israel.</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="7" style="v" />If the man doesn’t want to take his brother’s wife, then his brother’s wife shall go up to the gate to the elders, and say, “My husband’s brother refuses to raise up to his brother a name in Israel. He will not perform the duty of a husband’s brother to me.” <verse number="8" style="v" />Then the elders of his city shall call him, and speak to him. If he stands and says, “I don’t want to take her,” <verse number="9" style="v" />then his brother’s wife shall come to him in the presence of the elders, and loose his sandal from off his foot, and spit in his face. She shall answer and say, “So shall it be done to the man who does not build up his brother’s house.” <verse number="10" style="v" />His name shall be called in Israel, “The house of him who had his sandal removed.”</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="11" style="v" />When men strive against each other, and the wife of one draws near to deliver her husband out of the hand of him who strikes him, and puts out her hand, and grabs him by his private parts, <verse number="12" style="v" />then you shall cut off her hand. Your eye shall have no pity.</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="13" style="v" />You shall not have in your bag diverse weights, one heavy and one light. <verse number="14" style="v" />You shall not have in your house diverse measures, one large and one small. <verse number="15" style="v" />You shall have a perfect and just weight. You shall have a perfect and just measure, that your days may be long in the land which the LORD your God gives you. <verse number="16" style="v" />For all who do such things, all who do unrighteously, are an abomination to the LORD your God.</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="17" style="v" />Remember what Amalek did to you by the way as you came out of Egypt; <verse number="18" style="v" />how he met you by the way, and struck the rearmost of you, all who were feeble behind you, when you were faint and weary; and he didn’t fear God. <verse number="19" style="v" />Therefore it shall be, when the LORD your God has given you rest from all your enemies all around, in the land which the LORD your God gives you for an inheritance to possess it, that you shall blot out the memory of Amalek from under the sky. You shall not forget.</para>
  <chapter number="26" style="c" />
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="1" style="v" />It shall be, when you have come in to the land which the LORD your God gives you for an inheritance, possess it, and dwell in it, <verse number="2" style="v" />that you shall take some of the first of all the fruit of the ground, which you shall bring in from your land that the LORD your God gives you. You shall put it in a basket, and shall go to the place which the LORD your God shall choose to cause his name to dwell there. <verse number="3" style="v" />You shall come to the priest who shall be in those days, and tell him, “I profess today to the LORD your God, that I have come to the land which the LORD swore to our fathers to give us.” <verse number="4" style="v" />The priest shall take the basket out of your hand, and set it down before the LORD your God’s altar. <verse number="5" style="v" />You shall answer and say before the LORD your God, “My father<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">26:5 </char><char style="ft" closed="false">or, forefather</char></note> was a Syrian ready to perish. He went down into Egypt, and lived there, few in number. There he became a great, mighty, and populous nation. <verse number="6" style="v" />The Egyptians mistreated us, afflicted us, and imposed hard labour on us. <verse number="7" style="v" />Then we cried to the LORD, the God of our fathers. The LORD heard our voice, and saw our affliction, our toil, and our oppression. <verse number="8" style="v" />The LORD brought us out of Egypt with a mighty hand, with an outstretched arm, with great terror, with signs, and with wonders; <verse number="9" style="v" />and he has brought us into this place, and has given us this land, a land flowing with milk and honey. <verse number="10" style="v" />Now, behold, I have brought the first of the fruit of the ground, which you, the LORD, have given me.” You shall set it down before the LORD your God, and worship before the LORD your God. <verse number="11" style="v" />You shall rejoice in all the good which the LORD your God has given to you, and to your house, you, and the Levite, and the foreigner who is amongst you.</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="12" style="v" />When you have finished tithing all the tithe of your increase in the third year, which is the year of tithing, then you shall give it to the Levite, to the foreigner, to the fatherless, and to the widow, that they may eat within your gates and be filled. <verse number="13" style="v" />You shall say before the LORD your God, “I have put away the holy things out of my house, and also have given them to the Levite, to the foreigner, to the fatherless, and to the widow, according to all your commandment which you have commanded me. I have not transgressed any of your commandments, neither have I forgotten them. <verse number="14" style="v" />I have not eaten of it in my mourning, neither have I removed any of it while I was unclean, nor given of it for the dead. I have listened to the LORD my God’s voice. I have done according to all that you have commanded me. <verse number="15" style="v" />Look down from your holy habitation, from heaven, and bless your people Israel, and the ground which you have given us, as you swore to our fathers, a land flowing with milk and honey.”</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="16" style="v" />Today the LORD your God commands you to do these statutes and ordinances. You shall therefore keep and do them with all your heart and with all your soul. <verse number="17" style="v" />You have declared today that the LORD is your God, and that you would walk in his ways, keep his statutes, his commandments, and his ordinances, and listen to his voice. <verse number="18" style="v" />The LORD has declared today that you are a people for his own possession, as he has promised you, and that you should keep all his commandments. <verse number="19" style="v" />He will make you high above all nations that he has made, in praise, in name, and in honour; and that you may be a holy people to the LORD your God, as he has spoken.</para>
  <chapter number="27" style="c" />
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="1" style="v" />Moses and the elders of Israel commanded the people, saying, “Keep all the commandment which I command you today. <verse number="2" style="v" />It shall be on the day when you shall pass over the Jordan to the land which the LORD your God gives you, that you shall set yourself up great stones, and coat them with plaster. <verse number="3" style="v" />You shall write on them all the words of this law, when you have passed over, that you may go in to the land which the LORD your God gives you, a land flowing with milk and honey, as the LORD, the God of your fathers, has promised you. <verse number="4" style="v" />It shall be, when you have crossed over the Jordan, that you shall set up these stones, which I command you today, on Mount Ebal, and you shall coat them with plaster. <verse number="5" style="v" />There you shall build an altar to the LORD your God, an altar of stones. You shall not use any iron tool on them. <verse number="6" style="v" />You shall build the LORD your God’s altar of uncut stones. You shall offer burnt offerings on it to the LORD your God. <verse number="7" style="v" />You shall sacrifice peace offerings, and shall eat there. You shall rejoice before the LORD your God. <verse number="8" style="v" />You shall write on the stones all the words of this law very plainly.”</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="9" style="v" />Moses and the Levitical priests spoke to all Israel, saying, “Be silent and listen, Israel! Today you have become the people of the LORD your God. <verse number="10" style="v" />You shall therefore obey the LORD your God’s voice, and do his commandments and his statutes, which I command you today.”</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="11" style="v" />Moses commanded the people the same day, saying, <verse number="12" style="v" />“These shall stand on Mount Gerizim to bless the people, when you have crossed over the Jordan: Simeon, Levi, Judah, Issachar, Joseph, and Benjamin. <verse number="13" style="v" />These shall stand on Mount Ebal for the curse: Reuben, Gad, Asher, Zebulun, Dan, and Naphtali. <verse number="14" style="v" />With a loud voice, the Levites shall say to all the men of Israel, <verse number="15" style="v" />‘Cursed is the man who makes an engraved or molten image, an abomination to the LORD, the work of the hands of the craftsman, and sets it up in secret.’</para>
  <para style="p">All the people shall answer and say, ‘Amen.’</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="16" style="v" />‘Cursed is he who dishonours his father or his mother.’</para>
  <para style="p">All the people shall say, ‘Amen.’</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="17" style="v" />‘Cursed is he who removes his neighbour’s landmark.’</para>
  <para style="p">All the people shall say, ‘Amen.’</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="18" style="v" />‘Cursed is he who leads the blind astray on the road.’</para>
  <para style="p">All the people shall say, ‘Amen.’</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="19" style="v" />‘Cursed is he who withholds justice from the foreigner, fatherless, and widow.’</para>
  <para style="p">All the people shall say, ‘Amen.’</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="20" style="v" />‘Cursed is he who lies with<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">27:20 </char><char style="ft" closed="false">i.e., has sexual relations with</char></note> his father’s wife, because he dishonours his father’s bed.’</para>
  <para style="p">All the people shall say, ‘Amen.’</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="21" style="v" />‘Cursed is he who lies with any kind of animal.’</para>
  <para style="p">All the people shall say, ‘Amen.’</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="22" style="v" />‘Cursed is he who lies with his sister, his father’s daughter or his mother’s daughter.’</para>
  <para style="p">All the people shall say, ‘Amen.’</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="23" style="v" />‘Cursed is he who lies with his mother-in-law.’</para>
  <para style="p">All the people shall say, ‘Amen.’</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="24" style="v" />‘Cursed is he who secretly kills his neighbour.’</para>
  <para style="p">All the people shall say, ‘Amen.’</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="25" style="v" />‘Cursed is he who takes a bribe to kill an innocent person.’</para>
  <para style="p">All the people shall say, ‘Amen.’</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="26" style="v" />‘Cursed is he who doesn’t uphold the words of this law by doing them.’</para>
  <para style="p">All the people shall say, ‘Amen.’”</para>
  <chapter number="28" style="c" />
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="1" style="v" />It shall happen, if you shall listen diligently to the LORD your God’s voice, to observe to do all his commandments which I command you today, that the LORD your God will set you high above all the nations of the earth. <verse number="2" style="v" />All these blessings will come upon you, and overtake you, if you listen to the LORD your God’s voice. <verse number="3" style="v" />You shall be blessed in the city, and you shall be blessed in the field. <verse number="4" style="v" />You shall be blessed in the fruit of your body, the fruit of your ground, the fruit of your animals, the increase of your livestock, and the young of your flock. <verse number="5" style="v" />Your basket and your kneading trough shall be blessed. <verse number="6" style="v" />You shall be blessed when you come in, and you shall be blessed when you go out. <verse number="7" style="v" />The LORD will cause your enemies who rise up against you to be struck before you. They will come out against you one way, and will flee before you seven ways. <verse number="8" style="v" />The LORD will command the blessing on you in your barns, and in all that you put your hand to. He will bless you in the land which the LORD your God gives you. <verse number="9" style="v" />The LORD will establish you for a holy people to himself, as he has sworn to you, if you shall keep the commandments of the LORD your God, and walk in his ways. <verse number="10" style="v" />All the peoples of the earth shall see that you are called by the LORD’s name, and they will be afraid of you. <verse number="11" style="v" />The LORD will grant you abundant prosperity in the fruit of your body, in the fruit of your livestock, and in the fruit of your ground, in the land which the LORD swore to your fathers to give you. <verse number="12" style="v" />The LORD will open to you his good treasure in the sky, to give the rain of your land in its season, and to bless all the work of your hand. You will lend to many nations, and you will not borrow. <verse number="13" style="v" />The LORD will make you the head, and not the tail. You will be above only, and you will not be beneath, if you listen to the commandments of the LORD your God which I command you today, to observe and to do, <verse number="14" style="v" />and shall not turn away from any of the words which I command you today, to the right hand or to the left, to go after other gods to serve them.</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="15" style="v" />But it shall come to pass, if you will not listen to the LORD your God’s voice, to observe to do all his commandments and his statutes which I command you today, that all these curses will come on you and overtake you. <verse number="16" style="v" />You will be cursed in the city, and you will be cursed in the field. <verse number="17" style="v" />Your basket and your kneading trough will be cursed. <verse number="18" style="v" />The fruit of your body, the fruit of your ground, the increase of your livestock, and the young of your flock will be cursed. <verse number="19" style="v" />You will be cursed when you come in, and you will be cursed when you go out. <verse number="20" style="v" />The LORD will send on you cursing, confusion, and rebuke in all that you put your hand to do, until you are destroyed and until you perish quickly, because of the evil of your doings, by which you have forsaken me. <verse number="21" style="v" />The LORD will make the pestilence cling to you, until he has consumed you from off the land where you go in to possess it. <verse number="22" style="v" />The LORD will strike you with consumption, with fever, with inflammation, with fiery heat, with the sword, with blight, and with mildew. They will pursue you until you perish. <verse number="23" style="v" />Your sky that is over your head will be bronze, and the earth that is under you will be iron. <verse number="24" style="v" />The LORD will make the rain of your land powder and dust. It will come down on you from the sky, until you are destroyed. <verse number="25" style="v" />The LORD will cause you to be struck before your enemies. You will go out one way against them, and will flee seven ways before them. You will be tossed back and forth amongst all the kingdoms of the earth. <verse number="26" style="v" />Your dead bodies will be food to all birds of the sky, and to the animals of the earth; and there will be no one to frighten them away. <verse number="27" style="v" />The LORD will strike you with the boils of Egypt, with the tumours, with the scurvy, and with the itch, of which you can not be healed. <verse number="28" style="v" />The LORD will strike you with madness, with blindness, and with astonishment of heart. <verse number="29" style="v" />You will grope at noonday, as the blind gropes in darkness, and you shall not prosper in your ways. You will only be oppressed and robbed always, and there will be no one to save you. <verse number="30" style="v" />You will betroth a wife, and another man shall lie with her. You will build a house, and you won’t dwell in it. You will plant a vineyard, and not use its fruit. <verse number="31" style="v" />Your ox will be slain before your eyes, and you will not eat any of it. Your donkey will be violently taken away from before your face, and will not be restored to you. Your sheep will be given to your enemies, and you will have no one to save you. <verse number="32" style="v" />Your sons and your daughters will be given to another people. Your eyes will look, and fail with longing for them all day long. There will be no power in your hand. <verse number="33" style="v" />A nation which you don’t know will eat the fruit of your ground and all of your work. You will only be oppressed and crushed always, <verse number="34" style="v" />so that the sights that you see with your eyes will drive you mad. <verse number="35" style="v" />The LORD will strike you in the knees and in the legs with a sore boil, of which you cannot be healed, from the sole of your foot to the crown of your head. <verse number="36" style="v" />The LORD will bring you, and your king whom you will set over yourselves, to a nation that you have not known, you nor your fathers. There you will serve other gods of wood and stone. <verse number="37" style="v" />You will become an astonishment, a proverb, and a byword amongst all the peoples where the LORD will lead you away. <verse number="38" style="v" />You will carry much seed out into the field, and will gather little in, for the locust will consume it. <verse number="39" style="v" />You will plant vineyards and dress them, but you will neither drink of the wine, nor harvest, because worms will eat them. <verse number="40" style="v" />You will have olive trees throughout all your borders, but you won’t anoint yourself with the oil, for your olives will drop off. <verse number="41" style="v" />You will father sons and daughters, but they will not be yours, for they will go into captivity. <verse number="42" style="v" />Locusts will consume all of your trees and the fruit of your ground. <verse number="43" style="v" />The foreigner who is amongst you will mount up above you higher and higher, and you will come down lower and lower. <verse number="44" style="v" />He will lend to you, and you won’t lend to him. He will be the head, and you will be the tail.</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="45" style="v" />All these curses will come on you, and will pursue you and overtake you, until you are destroyed, because you didn’t listen to the LORD your God’s voice, to keep his commandments and his statutes which he commanded you. <verse number="46" style="v" />They will be for a sign and for a wonder to you and to your offspring forever. <verse number="47" style="v" />Because you didn’t serve the LORD your God with joyfulness and with gladness of heart, by reason of the abundance of all things; <verse number="48" style="v" />therefore you will serve your enemies whom the LORD sends against you, in hunger, in thirst, in nakedness, and in lack of all things. He will put an iron yoke on your neck until he has destroyed you. <verse number="49" style="v" />The LORD will bring a nation against you from far, from the end of the earth, as the eagle flies: a nation whose language you will not understand, <verse number="50" style="v" />a nation of fierce facial expressions, that doesn’t respect the elderly, nor show favour to the young. <verse number="51" style="v" />They will eat the fruit of your livestock and the fruit of your ground, until you are destroyed. They also won’t leave you grain, new wine, oil, the increase of your livestock, or the young of your flock, until they have caused you to perish. <verse number="52" style="v" />They will besiege you in all your gates until your high and fortified walls in which you trusted come down throughout all your land. They will besiege you in all your gates throughout all your land which the LORD your God has given you. <verse number="53" style="v" />You will eat the fruit of your own body, the flesh of your sons and of your daughters, whom the LORD your God has given you, in the siege and in the distress with which your enemies will distress you. <verse number="54" style="v" />The man who is tender amongst you, and very delicate, his eye will be evil towards his brother, towards the wife whom he loves, and towards the remnant of his children whom he has remaining, <verse number="55" style="v" />so that he will not give to any of them of the flesh of his children whom he will eat, because he has nothing left to him, in the siege and in the distress with which your enemy will distress you in all your gates. <verse number="56" style="v" />The tender and delicate woman amongst you, who would not venture to set the sole of her foot on the ground for delicateness and tenderness, her eye will be evil towards the husband that she loves, towards her son, towards her daughter, <verse number="57" style="v" />towards her young one who comes out from between her feet, and towards her children whom she bears; for she will eat them secretly for lack of all things in the siege and in the distress with which your enemy will distress you in your gates. <verse number="58" style="v" />If you will not observe to do all the words of this law that are written in this book, that you may fear this glorious and fearful name, THE LORD your God, <verse number="59" style="v" />then the LORD will make your plagues and the plagues of your offspring fearful, even great plagues, and of long duration, and severe sicknesses, and of long duration. <verse number="60" style="v" />He will bring on you again all the diseases of Egypt, which you were afraid of; and they will cling to you. <verse number="61" style="v" />Also every sickness and every plague which is not written in the book of this law, the LORD will bring them on you until you are destroyed. <verse number="62" style="v" />You will be left few in number, even though you were as the stars of the sky for multitude, because you didn’t listen to the LORD your God’s voice. <verse number="63" style="v" />It will happen that as the LORD rejoiced over you to do you good, and to multiply you, so the LORD will rejoice over you to cause you to perish and to destroy you. You will be plucked from the land that you are going in to possess. <verse number="64" style="v" />The LORD will scatter you amongst all peoples, from one end of the earth to the other end of the earth. There you will serve other gods which you have not known, you nor your fathers, even wood and stone. <verse number="65" style="v" />Amongst these nations you will find no ease, and there will be no rest for the sole of your foot; but the LORD will give you there a trembling heart, failing of eyes, and pining of soul. <verse number="66" style="v" />Your life will hang in doubt before you. You will be afraid night and day, and will have no assurance of your life. <verse number="67" style="v" />In the morning you will say, “I wish it were evening!” and at evening you will say, “I wish it were morning!” for the fear of your heart which you will fear, and for the sights which your eyes will see. <verse number="68" style="v" />The LORD will bring you into Egypt again with ships, by the way of which I told to you that you would never see it again. There you will offer yourselves to your enemies for male and female slaves, and nobody will buy you.</para>
  <chapter number="29" style="c" />
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="1" style="v" />These are the words of the covenant which the LORD commanded Moses to make with the children of Israel in the land of Moab, in addition to the covenant which he made with them in Horeb. <verse number="2" style="v" />Moses called to all Israel, and said to them:</para>
  <para style="p">Your eyes have seen all that the LORD did in the land of Egypt to Pharaoh, and to all his servants, and to all his land; <verse number="3" style="v" />the great trials which your eyes saw, the signs, and those great wonders. <verse number="4" style="v" />But the LORD has not given you a heart to know, eyes to see, and ears to hear, to this day. <verse number="5" style="v" />I have led you forty years in the wilderness. Your clothes have not grown old on you, and your sandals have not grown old on your feet. <verse number="6" style="v" />You have not eaten bread, neither have you drunk wine or strong drink, that you may know that I am the LORD your God. <verse number="7" style="v" />When you came to this place, Sihon the king of Heshbon and Og the king of Bashan came out against us to battle, and we struck them. <verse number="8" style="v" />We took their land, and gave it for an inheritance to the Reubenites, and to the Gadites, and to the half-tribe of the Manassites. <verse number="9" style="v" />Therefore keep the words of this covenant and do them, that you may prosper in all that you do. <verse number="10" style="v" />All of you stand today in the presence of the LORD your God: your heads, your tribes, your elders, and your officers, even all the men of Israel, <verse number="11" style="v" />your little ones, your wives, and the foreigners who are in the middle of your camps, from the one who cuts your wood to the one who draws your water, <verse number="12" style="v" />that you may enter into the covenant of the LORD your God, and into his oath, which the LORD your God makes with you today, <verse number="13" style="v" />that he may establish you today as his people, and that he may be your God, as he spoke to you and as he swore to your fathers, to Abraham, to Isaac, and to Jacob. <verse number="14" style="v" />Neither do I make this covenant and this oath with you only, <verse number="15" style="v" />but with those who stand here with us today before the LORD our God, and also with those who are not here with us today <verse number="16" style="v" />(for you know how we lived in the land of Egypt, and how we came through the middle of the nations through which you passed; <verse number="17" style="v" />and you have seen their abominations and their idols of wood, stone, silver, and gold, which were amongst them); <verse number="18" style="v" />lest there should be amongst you man, woman, family, or tribe whose heart turns away today from the LORD our God, to go to serve the gods of those nations; lest there should be amongst you a root that produces bitter poison; <verse number="19" style="v" />and it happen, when he hears the words of this curse, that he bless himself in his heart, saying, “I shall have peace, though I walk in the stubbornness of my heart,” to destroy the moist with the dry. <verse number="20" style="v" />The LORD will not pardon him, but then the LORD’s anger and his jealousy will smoke against that man, and all the curse that is written in this book will fall on him, and the LORD will blot out his name from under the sky. <verse number="21" style="v" />The LORD will set him apart for evil out of all the tribes of Israel, according to all the curses of the covenant written in this book of the law.</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="22" style="v" />The generation to come—your children who will rise up after you, and the foreigner who will come from a far land—will say, when they see the plagues of that land, and the sicknesses with which the LORD has made it sick, <verse number="23" style="v" />that all of its land is sulphur, salt, and burning, that it is not sown, doesn’t produce, nor does any grass grow in it, like the overthrow of Sodom, Gomorrah, Admah, and Zeboiim, which the LORD overthrew in his anger, and in his wrath. <verse number="24" style="v" />Even all the nations will say, “Why has the LORD done this to this land? What does the heat of this great anger mean?”</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="25" style="v" />Then men will say, “Because they abandoned the covenant of the LORD, the God of their fathers, which he made with them when he brought them out of the land of Egypt, <verse number="26" style="v" />and went and served other gods and worshipped them, gods that they didn’t know and that he had not given to them. <verse number="27" style="v" />Therefore the LORD’s anger burnt against this land, to bring on it all the curses that are written in this book. <verse number="28" style="v" />The LORD rooted them out of their land in anger, in wrath, and in great indignation, and thrust them into another land, as it is today.”</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="29" style="v" />The secret things belong to the LORD our God; but the things that are revealed belong to us and to our children forever, that we may do all the words of this law.</para>
  <chapter number="30" style="c" />
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="1" style="v" />It shall happen, when all these things have come on you, the blessing and the curse, which I have set before you, and you shall call them to mind amongst all the nations where the LORD your God has driven you, <verse number="2" style="v" />and return to the LORD your God and obey his voice according to all that I command you today, you and your children, with all your heart and with all your soul, <verse number="3" style="v" />that then the LORD your God will release you from captivity, have compassion on you, and will return and gather you from all the peoples where the LORD your God has scattered you. <verse number="4" style="v" />If your outcasts are in the uttermost parts of the heavens, from there the LORD your God will gather you, and from there he will bring you back. <verse number="5" style="v" />The LORD your God will bring you into the land which your fathers possessed, and you will possess it. He will do you good, and increase your numbers more than your fathers. <verse number="6" style="v" />The LORD your God will circumcise your heart, and the heart of your offspring, to love the LORD your God with all your heart and with all your soul, that you may live. <verse number="7" style="v" />The LORD your God will put all these curses on your enemies and on those who hate you, who persecuted you. <verse number="8" style="v" />You shall return and obey the LORD’s voice, and do all his commandments which I command you today. <verse number="9" style="v" />The LORD your God will make you prosperous in all the work of your hand, in the fruit of your body, in the fruit of your livestock, and in the fruit of your ground, for good; for the LORD will again rejoice over you for good, as he rejoiced over your fathers, <verse number="10" style="v" />if you will obey the LORD your God’s voice, to keep his commandments and his statutes which are written in this book of the law; if you turn to the LORD your God with all your heart and with all your soul.</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="11" style="v" />For this commandment which I command you today is not too hard for you or too distant. <verse number="12" style="v" />It is not in heaven, that you should say, “Who will go up for us to heaven, bring it to us, and proclaim it to us, that we may do it?” <verse number="13" style="v" />Neither is it beyond the sea, that you should say, “Who will go over the sea for us, bring it to us, and proclaim it to us, that we may do it?” <verse number="14" style="v" />But the word is very near to you, in your mouth and in your heart, that you may do it. <verse number="15" style="v" />Behold, I have set before you today life and prosperity, and death and evil. <verse number="16" style="v" />For I command you today to love the LORD your God, to walk in his ways and to keep his commandments, his statutes, and his ordinances, that you may live and multiply, and that the LORD your God may bless you in the land where you go in to possess it. <verse number="17" style="v" />But if your heart turns away, and you will not hear, but are drawn away and worship other gods, and serve them, <verse number="18" style="v" />I declare to you today that you will surely perish. You will not prolong your days in the land where you pass over the Jordan to go in to possess it. <verse number="19" style="v" />I call heaven and earth to witness against you today that I have set before you life and death, the blessing and the curse. Therefore choose life, that you may live, you and your descendants, <verse number="20" style="v" />to love the LORD your God, to obey his voice, and to cling to him; for he is your life, and the length of your days, that you may dwell in the land which the LORD swore to your fathers, to Abraham, to Isaac, and to Jacob, to give them.</para>
  <chapter number="31" style="c" />
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="1" style="v" />Moses went and spoke these words to all Israel. <verse number="2" style="v" />He said to them, “I am one hundred and twenty years old today. I can no more go out and come in. The LORD has said to me, ‘You shall not go over this Jordan.’ <verse number="3" style="v" />The LORD your God himself will go over before you. He will destroy these nations from before you, and you shall dispossess them. Joshua will go over before you, as the LORD has spoken. <verse number="4" style="v" />The LORD will do to them as he did to Sihon and to Og, the kings of the Amorites, and to their land, when he destroyed them. <verse number="5" style="v" />The LORD will deliver them up before you, and you shall do to them according to all the commandment which I have commanded you. <verse number="6" style="v" />Be strong and courageous. Don’t be afraid or scared of them; for the LORD your God himself is who goes with you. He will not fail you nor forsake you.”</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="7" style="v" />Moses called to Joshua, and said to him in the sight of all Israel, “Be strong and courageous, for you shall go with this people into the land which the LORD has sworn to their fathers to give them; and you shall cause them to inherit it. <verse number="8" style="v" />The LORD himself is who goes before you. He will be with you. He will not fail you nor forsake you. Don’t be afraid. Don’t be discouraged.”</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="9" style="v" />Moses wrote this law and delivered it to the priests the sons of Levi, who bore the ark of the LORD’s covenant, and to all the elders of Israel. <verse number="10" style="v" />Moses commanded them, saying, “At the end of every seven years, in the set time of the year of release, in the feast of booths, <verse number="11" style="v" />when all Israel has come to appear before the LORD your God in the place which he will choose, you shall read this law before all Israel in their hearing. <verse number="12" style="v" />Assemble the people, the men and the women and the little ones, and the foreigners who are within your gates, that they may hear, learn, fear the LORD your God, and observe to do all the words of this law, <verse number="13" style="v" />and that their children, who have not known, may hear and learn to fear the LORD your God, as long as you live in the land where you go over the Jordan to possess it.”</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="14" style="v" />The LORD said to Moses, “Behold, your days approach that you must die. Call Joshua, and present yourselves in the Tent of Meeting, that I may commission him.”</para>
  <para style="p">Moses and Joshua went, and presented themselves in the Tent of Meeting.</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="15" style="v" />The LORD appeared in the Tent in a pillar of cloud, and the pillar of cloud stood over the Tent’s door. <verse number="16" style="v" />The LORD said to Moses, “Behold, you shall sleep with your fathers. This people will rise up and play the prostitute after the strange gods of the land where they go to be amongst them, and will forsake me and break my covenant which I have made with them. <verse number="17" style="v" />Then my anger shall be kindled against them in that day, and I will forsake them, and I will hide my face from them, and they shall be devoured, and many evils and troubles shall come on them; so that they will say in that day, ‘Haven’t these evils come on us because our God is not amongst us?’ <verse number="18" style="v" />I will surely hide my face in that day for all the evil which they have done, in that they have turned to other gods.</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="19" style="v" />“Now therefore write this song for yourselves, and teach it to the children of Israel. Put it in their mouths, that this song may be a witness for me against the children of Israel. <verse number="20" style="v" />For when I have brought them into the land which I swore to their fathers, flowing with milk and honey, and they have eaten and filled themselves, and grown fat, then they will turn to other gods, and serve them, and despise me, and break my covenant. <verse number="21" style="v" />It will happen, when many evils and troubles have come on them, that this song will testify before them as a witness; for it will not be forgotten out of the mouths of their descendants; for I know their ways and what they are doing today, before I have brought them into the land which I promised them.”</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="22" style="v" />So Moses wrote this song the same day, and taught it to the children of Israel.</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="23" style="v" />He commissioned Joshua the son of Nun, and said, “Be strong and courageous; for you shall bring the children of Israel into the land which I swore to them. I will be with you.”</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="24" style="v" />When Moses had finished writing the words of this law in a book, until they were finished, <verse number="25" style="v" />Moses commanded the Levites, who bore the ark of the LORD’s covenant, saying, <verse number="26" style="v" />“Take this book of the law, and put it by the side of the ark of the LORD your God’s covenant, that it may be there for a witness against you. <verse number="27" style="v" />For I know your rebellion and your stiff neck. Behold, while I am yet alive with you today, you have been rebellious against the LORD. How much more after my death? <verse number="28" style="v" />Assemble to me all the elders of your tribes and your officers, that I may speak these words in their ears, and call heaven and earth to witness against them. <verse number="29" style="v" />For I know that after my death you will utterly corrupt yourselves, and turn away from the way which I have commanded you; and evil will happen to you in the latter days, because you will do that which is evil in the LORD’s sight, to provoke him to anger through the work of your hands.”</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="30" style="v" />Moses spoke in the ears of all the assembly of Israel the words of this song, until they were finished.</para>
  <chapter number="32" style="c" />
  <para style="q1">
    <verse number="1" style="v" />Give ear, you heavens, and I will speak.</para>
  <para style="q2">Let the earth hear the words of my mouth.</para>
  <para style="q1">
    <verse number="2" style="v" />My doctrine will drop as the rain.</para>
  <para style="q2">My speech will condense as the dew,</para>
  <para style="q2">as the misty rain on the tender grass,</para>
  <para style="q2">as the showers on the herb.</para>
  <para style="q1">
    <verse number="3" style="v" />For I will proclaim the LORD’s name.</para>
  <para style="q2">Ascribe greatness to our God!</para>
  <para style="q1">
    <verse number="4" style="v" />The Rock: his work is perfect,</para>
  <para style="q2">for all his ways are just.</para>
  <para style="q2">A God of faithfulness who does no wrong,</para>
  <para style="q2">just and right is he.</para>
  <para style="q1">
    <verse number="5" style="v" />They have dealt corruptly with him.</para>
  <para style="q2">They are not his children, because of their defect.</para>
  <para style="q2">They are a perverse and crooked generation.</para>
  <para style="q1">
    <verse number="6" style="v" />Is this the way you repay the LORD,</para>
  <para style="q2">foolish and unwise people?</para>
  <para style="q1">Isn’t he your father who has bought you?</para>
  <para style="q2">He has made you and established you.</para>
  <para style="q1">
    <verse number="7" style="v" />Remember the days of old.</para>
  <para style="q2">Consider the years of many generations.</para>
  <para style="q1">Ask your father, and he will show you;</para>
  <para style="q2">your elders, and they will tell you.</para>
  <para style="q1">
    <verse number="8" style="v" />When the Most High gave to the nations their inheritance,</para>
  <para style="q2">when he separated the children of men,</para>
  <para style="q1">he set the bounds of the peoples</para>
  <para style="q2">according to the number of the children of Israel.</para>
  <para style="q1">
    <verse number="9" style="v" />For the LORD’s portion is his people.</para>
  <para style="q2">Jacob is the lot of his inheritance.</para>
  <para style="q1">
    <verse number="10" style="v" />He found him in a desert land,</para>
  <para style="q2">in the waste howling wilderness.</para>
  <para style="q1">He surrounded him.</para>
  <para style="q2">He cared for him.</para>
  <para style="q2">He kept him as the apple of his eye.</para>
  <para style="q1">
    <verse number="11" style="v" />As an eagle that stirs up her nest,</para>
  <para style="q2">that flutters over her young,</para>
  <para style="q1">he spread abroad his wings,</para>
  <para style="q2">he took them,</para>
  <para style="q2">he bore them on his feathers.</para>
  <para style="q1">
    <verse number="12" style="v" />The LORD alone led him.</para>
  <para style="q2">There was no foreign god with him.</para>
  <para style="q1">
    <verse number="13" style="v" />He made him ride on the high places of the earth.</para>
  <para style="q2">He ate the increase of the field.</para>
  <para style="q1">He caused him to suck honey out of the rock,</para>
  <para style="q2">oil out of the flinty rock;</para>
  <para style="q1">
    <verse number="14" style="v" />butter from the herd, and milk from the flock,</para>
  <para style="q2">with fat of lambs,</para>
  <para style="q2">rams of the breed of Bashan, and goats,</para>
  <para style="q2">with the finest of the wheat.</para>
  <para style="q2">From the blood of the grape, you drank wine.</para>
  <para style="q1">
    <verse number="15" style="v" />But Jeshurun grew fat, and kicked.</para>
  <para style="q2">You have grown fat.</para>
  <para style="q2">You have grown thick.</para>
  <para style="q2">You have become sleek.</para>
  <para style="q1">Then he abandoned God who made him,</para>
  <para style="q2">and rejected the Rock of his salvation.</para>
  <para style="q1">
    <verse number="16" style="v" />They moved him to jealousy with strange gods.</para>
  <para style="q2">They provoked him to anger with abominations.</para>
  <para style="q1">
    <verse number="17" style="v" />They sacrificed to demons, not God,</para>
  <para style="q2">to gods that they didn’t know,</para>
  <para style="q2">to new gods that came up recently,</para>
  <para style="q2">which your fathers didn’t dread.</para>
  <para style="q1">
    <verse number="18" style="v" />Of the Rock who became your father, you are unmindful,</para>
  <para style="q2">and have forgotten God who gave you birth.</para>
  <para style="q1">
    <verse number="19" style="v" />The LORD saw and abhorred,</para>
  <para style="q2">because of the provocation of his sons and his daughters.</para>
  <para style="q1">
    <verse number="20" style="v" />He said, “I will hide my face from them.</para>
  <para style="q2">I will see what their end will be;</para>
  <para style="q1">for they are a very perverse generation,</para>
  <para style="q2">children in whom is no faithfulness.</para>
  <para style="q1">
    <verse number="21" style="v" />They have moved me to jealousy with that which is not God.</para>
  <para style="q2">They have provoked me to anger with their vanities.</para>
  <para style="q1">I will move them to jealousy with those who are not a people.</para>
  <para style="q2">I will provoke them to anger with a foolish nation.</para>
  <para style="q1">
    <verse number="22" style="v" />For a fire is kindled in my anger,</para>
  <para style="q2">that burns to the lowest Sheol,<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">32:22 </char><char style="ft" closed="false">Sheol is the place of the dead.</char></note></para>
  <para style="q2">devours the earth with its increase,</para>
  <para style="q2">and sets the foundations of the mountains on fire.</para>
  <para style="b" />
  <para style="q1">
    <verse number="23" style="v" />“I will heap evils on them.</para>
  <para style="q2">I will spend my arrows on them.</para>
  <para style="q1">
    <verse number="24" style="v" />They shall be wasted with hunger,</para>
  <para style="q2">and devoured with burning heat</para>
  <para style="q2">and bitter destruction.</para>
  <para style="q1">I will send the teeth of animals on them,</para>
  <para style="q2">with the venom of vipers that glide in the dust.</para>
  <para style="q1">
    <verse number="25" style="v" />Outside the sword will bereave,</para>
  <para style="q2">and in the rooms,</para>
  <para style="q2">terror on both young man and virgin,</para>
  <para style="q2">the nursing infant with the grey-haired man.</para>
  <para style="q1">
    <verse number="26" style="v" />I said that I would scatter them afar.</para>
  <para style="q2">I would make their memory to cease from amongst men;</para>
  <para style="q1">
    <verse number="27" style="v" />were it not that I feared the provocation of the enemy,</para>
  <para style="q2">lest their adversaries should judge wrongly,</para>
  <para style="q2">lest they should say, ‘Our hand is exalted,</para>
  <para style="q2">The LORD has not done all this.’”</para>
  <para style="b" />
  <para style="q1">
    <verse number="28" style="v" />For they are a nation void of counsel.</para>
  <para style="q2">There is no understanding in them.</para>
  <para style="q1">
    <verse number="29" style="v" />Oh that they were wise, that they understood this,</para>
  <para style="q2">that they would consider their latter end!</para>
  <para style="q1">
    <verse number="30" style="v" />How could one chase a thousand,</para>
  <para style="q2">and two put ten thousand to flight,</para>
  <para style="q1">unless their Rock had sold them,</para>
  <para style="q2">and the LORD had delivered them up?</para>
  <para style="q1">
    <verse number="31" style="v" />For their rock is not as our Rock,</para>
  <para style="q2">even our enemies themselves concede.</para>
  <para style="q1">
    <verse number="32" style="v" />For their vine is of the vine of Sodom,</para>
  <para style="q2">of the fields of Gomorrah.</para>
  <para style="q1">Their grapes are poison grapes.</para>
  <para style="q2">Their clusters are bitter.</para>
  <para style="q1">
    <verse number="33" style="v" />Their wine is the poison of serpents,</para>
  <para style="q2">the cruel venom of asps.</para>
  <para style="b" />
  <para style="q1">
    <verse number="34" style="v" />“Isn’t this laid up in store with me,</para>
  <para style="q2">sealed up amongst my treasures?</para>
  <para style="q1">
    <verse number="35" style="v" />Vengeance is mine, and recompense,</para>
  <para style="q2">at the time when their foot slides;</para>
  <para style="q1">for the day of their calamity is at hand.</para>
  <para style="q2">Their doom rushes at them.”</para>
  <para style="b" />
  <para style="q1">
    <verse number="36" style="v" />For the LORD will judge his people,</para>
  <para style="q2">and have compassion on his servants,</para>
  <para style="q1">when he sees that their power is gone;</para>
  <para style="q2">that there is no one remaining, shut up or left at large.</para>
  <para style="q1">
    <verse number="37" style="v" />He will say, “Where are their gods,</para>
  <para style="q2">the rock in which they took refuge;</para>
  <para style="q1">
    <verse number="38" style="v" />which ate the fat of their sacrifices,</para>
  <para style="q2">and drank the wine of their drink offering?</para>
  <para style="q1">Let them rise up and help you!</para>
  <para style="q2">Let them be your protection.</para>
  <para style="b" />
  <para style="q1">
    <verse number="39" style="v" />“See now that I myself am he.</para>
  <para style="q2">There is no god with me.</para>
  <para style="q1">I kill and I make alive.</para>
  <para style="q2">I wound and I heal.</para>
  <para style="q2">There is no one who can deliver out of my hand.</para>
  <para style="q1">
    <verse number="40" style="v" />For I lift up my hand to heaven and declare,</para>
  <para style="q2">as I live forever,</para>
  <para style="q1">
    <verse number="41" style="v" />if I sharpen my glittering sword,</para>
  <para style="q2">my hand grasps it in judgement;</para>
  <para style="q1">I will take vengeance on my adversaries,</para>
  <para style="q2">and will repay those who hate me.</para>
  <para style="q1">
    <verse number="42" style="v" />I will make my arrows drunk with blood.</para>
  <para style="q2">My sword shall devour flesh with the blood of the slain and the captives,</para>
  <para style="q2">from the head of the leaders of the enemy.”</para>
  <para style="b" />
  <para style="q1">
    <verse number="43" style="v" />Rejoice, you nations, with his people,</para>
  <para style="q2">for he will avenge the blood of his servants.</para>
  <para style="q2">He will take vengeance on his adversaries,</para>
  <para style="q2">and will make atonement for his land and for his people.<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">32:43 </char><char style="ft" closed="false">For this verse, LXX reads: Rejoice, you heavens, with him, and let all the angels of God worship him; rejoice you Gentiles, with his people, and let all the sons of God strengthen themselves in him; for he will avenge the blood of his sons, and he will render vengeance, and recompense justice to his enemies, and will reward them that hate him; and the Lord shall purge the land of his people.</char></note></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="44" style="v" />Moses came and spoke all the words of this song in the ears of the people, he and Joshua the son of Nun. <verse number="45" style="v" />Moses finished reciting all these words to all Israel. <verse number="46" style="v" />He said to them, “Set your heart to all the words which I testify to you today, which you shall command your children to observe to do, all the words of this law. <verse number="47" style="v" />For it is no vain thing for you, because it is your life, and through this thing you shall prolong your days in the land, where you go over the Jordan to possess it.”</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="48" style="v" />The LORD spoke to Moses that same day, saying, <verse number="49" style="v" />“Go up into this mountain of Abarim, to Mount Nebo, which is in the land of Moab, that is across from Jericho; and see the land of Canaan, which I give to the children of Israel for a possession. <verse number="50" style="v" />Die on the mountain where you go up, and be gathered to your people, as Aaron your brother died on Mount Hor, and was gathered to his people; <verse number="51" style="v" />because you trespassed against me amongst the children of Israel at the waters of Meribah of Kadesh, in the wilderness of Zin; because you didn’t uphold my holiness amongst the children of Israel. <verse number="52" style="v" />For you shall see the land from a distance; but you shall not go there into the land which I give the children of Israel.”</para>
  <chapter number="33" style="c" />
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="1" style="v" />This is the blessing with which Moses the man of God blessed the children of Israel before his death. <verse number="2" style="v" />He said,</para>
  <para style="q1">“The LORD came from Sinai,</para>
  <para style="q2">and rose from Seir to them.</para>
  <para style="q1">He shone from Mount Paran.</para>
  <para style="q2">He came from the ten thousands of holy ones.</para>
  <para style="q2">At his right hand was a fiery law for them.<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">33:2 </char><char style="ft" closed="false">another manuscript reads “He came with myriads of holy ones from the south, from his mountain slopes.”</char></note></para>
  <para style="q1">
    <verse number="3" style="v" />Yes, he loves the people.</para>
  <para style="q2">All his saints are in your hand.</para>
  <para style="q2">They sat down at your feet.</para>
  <para style="q2">Each receives your words.</para>
  <para style="q1">
    <verse number="4" style="v" />Moses commanded us a law,</para>
  <para style="q2">an inheritance for the assembly of Jacob.</para>
  <para style="q1">
    <verse number="5" style="v" />He was king in Jeshurun,</para>
  <para style="q2">when the heads of the people were gathered,</para>
  <para style="q2">all the tribes of Israel together.</para>
  <para style="b" />
  <para style="q1">
    <verse number="6" style="v" />“Let Reuben live, and not die;</para>
  <para style="q2">Nor let his men be few.”</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="7" style="v" />This is for Judah. He said,</para>
  <para style="q1">“Hear, LORD, the voice of Judah.</para>
  <para style="q2">Bring him in to his people.</para>
  <para style="q1">With his hands he contended for himself.</para>
  <para style="q2">You shall be a help against his adversaries.”</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="8" style="v" />About Levi he said,</para>
  <para style="q1">“Your Thummim and your Urim are with your godly one,</para>
  <para style="q2">whom you proved at Massah,</para>
  <para style="q2">with whom you contended at the waters of Meribah.</para>
  <para style="q1">
    <verse number="9" style="v" />He said of his father, and of his mother, ‘I have not seen him.’</para>
  <para style="q2">He didn’t acknowledge his brothers,</para>
  <para style="q2">nor did he know his own children;</para>
  <para style="q1">for they have observed your word,</para>
  <para style="q2">and keep your covenant.</para>
  <para style="q1">
    <verse number="10" style="v" />They shall teach Jacob your ordinances,</para>
  <para style="q2">and Israel your law.</para>
  <para style="q1">They shall put incense before you,</para>
  <para style="q2">and whole burnt offering on your altar.</para>
  <para style="q1">
    <verse number="11" style="v" />LORD, bless his skills.</para>
  <para style="q2">Accept the work of his hands.</para>
  <para style="q1">Strike through the hips of those who rise up against him,</para>
  <para style="q2">of those who hate him, that they not rise again.”</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="12" style="v" />About Benjamin he said,</para>
  <para style="q1">“The beloved of the LORD will dwell in safety by him.</para>
  <para style="q2">He covers him all day long.</para>
  <para style="q2">He dwells between his shoulders.”</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="13" style="v" />About Joseph he said,</para>
  <para style="q1">“His land is blessed by the LORD,</para>
  <para style="q2">for the precious things of the heavens, for the dew,</para>
  <para style="q2">for the deep that couches beneath,</para>
  <para style="q1">
    <verse number="14" style="v" />for the precious things of the fruits of the sun,</para>
  <para style="q2">for the precious things that the moon can yield,</para>
  <para style="q1">
    <verse number="15" style="v" />for the best things of the ancient mountains,</para>
  <para style="q2">for the precious things of the everlasting hills,</para>
  <para style="q1">
    <verse number="16" style="v" />for the precious things of the earth and its fullness,</para>
  <para style="q2">the good will of him who lived in the bush.<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">33:16 </char><char style="ft" closed="false">i.e., the burning bush of Exodus 3:3-4.</char></note></para>
  <para style="q1">Let this come on the head of Joseph,</para>
  <para style="q2">on the crown of the head of him who was separated from his brothers.</para>
  <para style="q1">
    <verse number="17" style="v" />Majesty belongs to the firstborn of his herd.</para>
  <para style="q2">His horns are the horns of the wild ox.</para>
  <para style="q2">With them he will push all the peoples to the ends of the earth.</para>
  <para style="q1">They are the ten thousands of Ephraim.</para>
  <para style="q2">They are the thousands of Manasseh.”</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="18" style="v" />About Zebulun he said,</para>
  <para style="q1">“Rejoice, Zebulun, in your going out;</para>
  <para style="q2">and Issachar, in your tents.</para>
  <para style="q1">
    <verse number="19" style="v" />They will call the peoples to the mountain.</para>
  <para style="q2">There they will offer sacrifices of righteousness,</para>
  <para style="q1">for they will draw out the abundance of the seas,</para>
  <para style="q2">the hidden treasures of the sand.”</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="20" style="v" />About Gad he said,</para>
  <para style="q1">“He who enlarges Gad is blessed.</para>
  <para style="q2">He dwells as a lioness,</para>
  <para style="q2">and tears the arm and the crown of the head.</para>
  <para style="q1">
    <verse number="21" style="v" />He provided the first part for himself,</para>
  <para style="q2">for the lawgiver’s portion reserved was reserved for him.</para>
  <para style="q1">He came with the heads of the people.</para>
  <para style="q2">He executed the righteousness of the LORD,</para>
  <para style="q2">His ordinances with Israel.”</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="22" style="v" />About Dan he said,</para>
  <para style="q1">“Dan is a lion’s cub</para>
  <para style="q2">that leaps out of Bashan.”</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="23" style="v" />About Naphtali he said,</para>
  <para style="q1">“Naphtali, satisfied with favour,</para>
  <para style="q2">full of the LORD’s blessing,</para>
  <para style="q2">Possess the west and the south.”</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="24" style="v" />About Asher he said,</para>
  <para style="q1">“Asher is blessed with children.</para>
  <para style="q2">Let him be acceptable to his brothers.</para>
  <para style="q2">Let him dip his foot in oil.</para>
  <para style="q1">
    <verse number="25" style="v" />Your bars will be iron and bronze.</para>
  <para style="q2">As your days, so your strength will be.</para>
  <para style="b" />
  <para style="q1">
    <verse number="26" style="v" />“There is no one like God, Jeshurun,</para>
  <para style="q2">who rides on the heavens for your help,</para>
  <para style="q2">in his excellency on the skies.</para>
  <para style="q1">
    <verse number="27" style="v" />The eternal God is your dwelling place.</para>
  <para style="q2">Underneath are the everlasting arms.</para>
  <para style="q1">He thrust out the enemy from before you,</para>
  <para style="q2">and said, ‘Destroy!’</para>
  <para style="q1">
    <verse number="28" style="v" />Israel dwells in safety,</para>
  <para style="q2">the fountain of Jacob alone,</para>
  <para style="q1">In a land of grain and new wine.</para>
  <para style="q2">Yes, his heavens drop down dew.</para>
  <para style="q1">
    <verse number="29" style="v" />You are happy, Israel!</para>
  <para style="q2">Who is like you, a people saved by the LORD,</para>
  <para style="q2">the shield of your help,</para>
  <para style="q2">the sword of your excellency?</para>
  <para style="q1">Your enemies will submit themselves to you.</para>
  <para style="q2">You will tread on their high places.”</para>
  <chapter number="34" style="c" />
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="1" style="v" />Moses went up from the plains of Moab to Mount Nebo, to the top of Pisgah, that is opposite Jericho. The LORD showed him all the land of Gilead to Dan, <verse number="2" style="v" />and all Naphtali, and the land of Ephraim and Manasseh, and all the land of Judah, to the Western Sea, <verse number="3" style="v" />and the south,<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">34:3 </char><char style="ft" closed="false">or, Negev</char></note> and the Plain of the valley of Jericho the city of palm trees, to Zoar. <verse number="4" style="v" />The LORD said to him, “This is the land which I swore to Abraham, to Isaac, and to Jacob, saying, ‘I will give it to your offspring.’ I have caused you to see it with your eyes, but you shall not go over there.”</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="5" style="v" />So Moses the servant of the LORD died there in the land of Moab, according to the LORD’s word. <verse number="6" style="v" />He buried him in the valley in the land of Moab opposite Beth Peor, but no man knows where his tomb is to this day. <verse number="7" style="v" />Moses was one hundred and twenty years old when he died. His eye was not dim, nor his strength gone. <verse number="8" style="v" />The children of Israel wept for Moses in the plains of Moab thirty days, until the days of weeping in the mourning for Moses were ended. <verse number="9" style="v" />Joshua the son of Nun was full of the spirit of wisdom, for Moses had laid his hands on him. The children of Israel listened to him, and did as the LORD commanded Moses. <verse number="10" style="v" />Since then, there has not arisen a prophet in Israel like Moses, whom the LORD knew face to face, <verse number="11" style="v" />in all the signs and the wonders which the LORD sent him to do in the land of Egypt, to Pharaoh, and to all his servants, and to all his land, <verse number="12" style="v" />and in all the mighty hand, and in all the awesome deeds, which Moses did in the sight of all Israel.</para>
</usx>